<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine meditations upon several occasions with a dayly directory / by the excellent pen of Sir William Waller ...</title>
            <author>Waller, William, Sir, 1597?-1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 243 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 112 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39417</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18402021</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18402021</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107494</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67361)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107494)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1134:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine meditations upon several occasions with a dayly directory / by the excellent pen of Sir William Waller ...</title>
                  <author>Waller, William, Sir, 1597?-1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 208 p., [1] leaf of plates: port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Griffin for Benj. Alsop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Engraved frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [13].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meditations.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:107494:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait or Sir William Waller</figDesc>
                  <q>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> William Waller.</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107494:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DIVINE MEDITATIONS Upon SEVERAL OCCASIONS: With a Dayly Directory.</p>
            <p>By the Excellent Pen of Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> Kt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>B. Griffin</hi> for <hi>Benj. Alſop</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and Bible over againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:107494:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107494:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Will not draw the Juſtice of this Dedication into ſuſpicion by a needleſs Apology, ſince 'tis evident none elſe will reliſh them, none elſe can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them: Had I invited thoſe degenerated Souls that
<pb facs="tcp:107494:3"/> have ſo far forgotten their celestial extract, as to plunge themſelves in earthly pleaſures, to enjoy theſe Divine Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, it had been the ſame diſcourteous Courteſie, as to turn a filthy Swine into a curious Garden or clear Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, whoſe ſordid inclinations would rather chuſe to Wallow in the Mire, its own proper Element. To remove theſe earthly natures from their own groſs air, into the purer breathings of theſe Regions, is but to Tranſport Toads in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ireland,</hi> where the climate
<pb facs="tcp:107494:3"/> being contrary to their poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſtitutions muſt immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately deſtroy them: It was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually the folly and ſin of the Projectors of the Tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> to deſign a structure as high as Heaven; not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that their earthly frames muſt ſtarve and pine with the Refined breezes of thoſe Heavenly Habitations: I could wiſh therefore that the <hi>Superliminare</hi> of the Holy <hi>Herbert</hi> to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Poems were perfixt to theſe Meditations.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:107494:4"/>
               <l>Avoid <hi>Profaneneſs!</hi> come not here!</l>
               <l>Nothing but <hi>Holy, Pure,</hi> and <hi>Clear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or that which groanveth to be ſo,</l>
               <l>May at it's peril, further go!</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To enlarge in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations is a labour as <hi>vain</hi> as <hi>Impoſſible Vaine;</hi> for what Acceſſion will it make to the luſtre of the Sun, to light up our dim candle to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe upon his glorious Beams? and <hi>Impoſſible</hi> too;
<pb facs="tcp:107494:4"/> for to commend below the Dignity of the Subject is an Interpretative Reproach: Modeſty will not bluſh to ſay of theſe Papers, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the matter, they are <hi>all Glorious within;</hi> and in reſpect of the Language, their <hi>Cloathing is of wrought Gold:</hi> And Gold needs no Gilding! Tis the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement of Authentick beauties to paint; Let Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar faces owe their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions to ceruſs: And Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>million, ſuch approved peices of proportion are their own
<pb facs="tcp:107494:5"/> Orators; the Diamond needs no foile to ſet of its beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and one taſte of Honey will more effectually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend its ſweetneſs then the moſt elaborate Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick.</p>
            <p>The pious Author, being here placed in the ſhades of his privacy and retirements, ſits in the moſt advantageous po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture for an Artiſt to draw him to the life, which muſt have deluded his Art were he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the glaring ſhine of outward glory; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his own pencil who ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:107494:5"/> dare to take his picture? Let us then content our ſelves that we have here a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow into his breaſt through which we may obſerve the inward workings of his Soul which we conclude are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſincere becauſe ſecret, God and his own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence being onely privy to them.</p>
            <p>As we would not take the counterfeit of a friend, when inflamed with a Feaver, emaciated with a conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or diſcompoſed with paſſion; but in his moſt vegete, and
<pb facs="tcp:107494:6"/> healthful habit, in his moſt ſedate and compoſed hours, ſo do theſe Meditations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Author, not as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the dust and ſweat of Action; not as heated with the emotions, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations of Valour, but as one ſequeſtred from the noiſe, and buſſle of a vexing world, when he was moſt himſelf, that is when moſt in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the unſeen world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Soul is then its own faithful mirror, when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted adventitious duſt is wiped off: as the Sea is then
<pb facs="tcp:107494:6"/> the truſts looking Glaſe when leaſt ruffled with stormes and Tempeſts.</p>
            <p>If he be juſtly famous to this day, who firſt taught the Great <hi>Calvin</hi> to write, and ſpeak Latine, we need no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to evidence this pious Authors worth, than that one of the moſt mortified perſons of this our Age has profeſt that he learn't from him, <hi>the Art of Dying.</hi> A leſſon, which we are all the more concern'd to take out exactly, that we may not be to ſeek when the Soveraigne
<pb facs="tcp:107494:7"/> Arbitrator of our lives ſhall call us out to repeat it. <hi>Once we muſt die;</hi> and whatever errors we commit in that work, muſt not return tore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view, correct, and amend them. 'Tis our Intereſt then as well as our duty to die e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, that we may not bungle at it, when we come to die at our laſt day: In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to which great end the Author has bequeathed us theſe directions as a Legacy, that we may die but once, and live for ever: I ſhall add but one ſmall thing more,
<pb facs="tcp:107494:7"/> that thou hast this Coppy from his own Hand, without the Addition or ſubſtraction of one word, one ſyllable, one letter; and in this his exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, do centre the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the two great Poets, <hi>Virgil,</hi> and <hi>Ovid,</hi> to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of whom, none could add, from the latter, none could ſteal the ſmalleſt particle, without apparent injury, to their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted raptures, <hi>Farewel!</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN the Preface p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 5. r.</hi> groaneth. <hi>p. 6. l 15, dele: p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 1 r</hi> trueſt looking Glaſs. <hi>p. 106. line ult. read</hi> theſe words.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:107494:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107494:8"/>
            <head>Divine Meditations Upon SEVERAL OCCASIONS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. I.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my awaking in a dark Night.</head>
               <p>LOrd where am I? and in what world? how are all things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me (as they were in that <hi>no world,</hi> in that confuſed Maſs and Chaos) ſwadled up in bands of thick darkneſs? It is not without reaſon, that the moſt horrid things, that we can imagine (<hi>miſery, death, hell</hi> it ſelf) are repreſented by this <hi>black Solitude;</hi> there being nothing of more contrariety to our nature, than the privation of light. If it be ſo uncomfortable to be in the dark, and to have no <hi>light,</hi> how diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107494:9"/> muſt it be in a ſpiritual ſenſe to be in the dark, and to have <hi>no truſt?</hi> that is a darkneſs to be felt indeed!</p>
               <p>If <hi>this night</hi> were to continue but <hi>three dayes,</hi> (like that in <hi>Egypt</hi>) I ſhould think it <hi>a plague;</hi> how much more, if it were to be <hi>everlaſting,</hi> would it be <hi>a hell</hi> to me, though there were <hi>no other torment</hi> to accompany it? How uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivably miſerable is the eſtate of thoſe <hi>damned Souls,</hi> that lie manacled and fettered <hi>in chains of eternal darkneſs,</hi> and are not onely baniſhed from the <hi>light of the Sun,</hi> but (which is <hi>the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of darkneſs</hi>) ſhut out from the <hi>light of Gods countenance,</hi> and adjudged to eternal pains? But what <hi>an Idol</hi> am I in this condition? I have <hi>eyes</hi> and <hi>ſee not;</hi> all natural helps and parts are vain and uſeleſs, except the God of nature, vouchſafe to actuate them, and to make them inſtrumental. O my Soul, be not diſquieted with this; what though I cannot ſee for the preſent? God hath made <hi>comforts,</hi> as he hath made <hi>lights</hi> for the <hi>night</hi> as well
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107494:9"/> as for the <hi>day.</hi> There are <hi>ſongs in the night,</hi> and my mouth may be open to ſhew forth the high praiſes of God, even when I am upon my Bed, and mine eyes ſealed up in darkneſs. <hi>The ſight of the eyes is not alwayes pleaſing!</hi> how many times have <hi>mine eyes wounded my heart,</hi> when they have ſeen what they <hi>would not have ſeen?</hi> nay (which is worſe) how many times have they <hi>corrupted my heart,</hi> when they have ſeen what they <hi>ſhould not have ſeen?</hi> at the beſt, <hi>various objects</hi> are but a <hi>diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the mind,</hi> and by raiſing <hi>vain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,</hi> bring it to a <hi>needleſs indigency,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing <hi>a want</hi> of many things, which we <hi>want not. There is a kind of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency in ſeeing nothing!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a comfort, and an ineſtimable one, that in the want of the uſe of my <hi>bodily eyes,</hi> I have the benefit of <hi>a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual eyeſight;</hi> ſo that although I cannot ſee, as <hi>Cats</hi> and <hi>Bats,</hi> and <hi>Owls</hi> do, yet I can ſee <hi>as Saints, and Angels ſee,</hi> no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſitions can hinder an intellectual proſpect. Be it never ſo dark, I can
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107494:10"/> (without the help of a Candle) look <hi>into my ſelf,</hi> and in the ſenſe of my wants, looks up, <hi>to God,</hi> and find a clear lightſome paſſage through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to the throne of his grace. But what do I ſay? <hi>I can?</hi> O my God, pardon the preſumption of that language! of <hi>my ſelf, as of my ſelf, I can do nothing but ſin!</hi> I am darkneſs (there is a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night within me) and <hi>I can only ſee, that I cannot ſee!</hi> It were not only <hi>a blindneſs</hi> in me, but a <hi>remaining ſin</hi> to boot, if I ſhould ſay, <hi>I ſee.</hi> Who <hi>ſo blind, as they that are perfect?</hi> It is <hi>in thy light alone, that I ſee light! Thy gracious illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating eye, is mine eye ſight!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord let me ever enjoy the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of that aſpect, and then in the darkeſt condition (though it were <hi>the ſhadow of death</hi>) I ſhall <hi>not be afraid</hi> of any terrours; even <hi>the night ſhall be light about me;</hi> or if it be not, it ſhall be <hi>light with me.</hi> Sorrow may <hi>endure for a night, but joy will come in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> and in a morning that ſhall never ſee night! In the mean time, O my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107494:10"/> God, though I <hi>can ſee nothing</hi> here but darkneſs and obſcurity, it is my <hi>ſafety,</hi> that <hi>thou ſeeſt me;</hi> it is my <hi>happineſs</hi> that I can <hi>ſee thee!</hi> what can I wiſh for more in this world, then to be <hi>ſafe, and happy? return again unto thy reſt, O my Soul, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION. II.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Sun-riſing.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TRuly the light is ſweet, and a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant thing it is for the eyes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Sun!</hi> look out, O my Soul, and ſee <hi>a miracle,</hi> and <hi>no wonder.</hi> Behold that glorious <hi>ruler of the day,</hi> as <hi>a bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom coming out of his Chamber,</hi> deckt with beauty and excellency. If this great luminary had never ſhewed it ſelf abroad <hi>till now,</hi> and were <hi>now to be ſeen,</hi> but as <hi>a rarity, this once;</hi> with what a <hi>Perſian adoration</hi> ſhould we be ready to welcome it, and with what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107494:11"/> dejected countenances, ſhould we bid it farewel? Now that we ſee it every day, we <hi>ſcarce take notice</hi> that we ſee it: once certain it is, that we heed it <hi>nothing ſo much,</hi> as any unuſual Meteor, or fiery exhalation; <hi>ſo much more prone are we by nature to be taken with</hi> new, <hi>than with</hi> worthy, <hi>if</hi> ordinary <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet, upon a juſt account (all things conſidered) Gods <hi>ordinary works,</hi> which are <hi>eſtabliſhed in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe,</hi> are more wonderful than thoſe <hi>extraordinary</hi> miracles, which we moſt admire: for the <hi>ſtanding ſtill</hi> of this Sun at <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s arreſt, was not in it ſelf ſo ſtupendious, as the <hi>daily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs</hi> thereof, that being ſo vaſt a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as it is, it ſhould in the compaſs of a few hours circulate the World: Lord give me a true ſenſe and apprehenſion of thine <hi>eternal Power and Godhead;</hi> and of thine <hi>inviſible things,</hi> in the <hi>things that are made,</hi> even for common uſe, and which thou haſt diſtributed unto all Nations under the cope of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107494:11"/> Heaven; that ſo, as all thoſe works praiſe thee, in the determinate order of their ſervices; I may likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly give thee praiſe for them; not only becauſe thou haſt made them <hi>beautiful and excellent</hi> in their kinds, for <hi>thine own glory;</hi> but becauſe thou haſt made them <hi>ordinary</hi> and <hi>common,</hi> for the <hi>good of all thy creatures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How doth this morning light revive, and cheriſh all things, and give them as it were <hi>a reſurrection from the dead, and a new being?</hi> But even now they were buried in obſcurity, and before I can well recollect my ſelf, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in their proper colours, and ſtand as a garment new made up. O thou <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs, ariſe upon my Soul with healing in thy wings,</hi> and ſcatter thoſe ſhaddows of darkneſs, that have ſo long benighted me; enlighten the eyes of my underſtanding, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new and quicken me by the influence of thy grace, that thy light may be a new life unto me; that <hi>I may live, yet not I, but thou that liveſt in me!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:107494:12"/>
               <p>That <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſaid truely, <hi>if the Sun were wanting, it would be night for all the Moon and Stars; for nothing but the Sun can make it day:</hi> And it is as true in a ſpiritual conſideration; if it were not for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the <hi>light of the world,</hi> notwithſtanding all the illumination we can receive from <hi>reaſon and ſenſe,</hi> we ſhould be <hi>ſtill in the dark;</hi> and therefore ſome have obſerved, that our Saviour was born on <hi>the fourth day</hi> of the week, which was the ſame day of the week, wherein <hi>the Sun was created;</hi> as to ſhew that he was <hi>that Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> and that <hi>true light that lighteth every one that cometh into the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What a general bleſſing is this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficent planet? and how is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature of God emblematically re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by it? It is <hi>good unto all;</hi> it <hi>riſeth on the evil, and on the good;</hi> and <hi>without regard of perſons,</hi> ſhineth upon <hi>the poor mans Cottage,</hi> as well as upon <hi>the Princes Pallace,</hi> and <hi>nothing is hid from the influential heat thereof!</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:107494:12"/> Lord, this is a Copy of that <hi>univerſal Goodneſs,</hi> which is originally in thy ſelf; but with this difference, that what the Sun doth, as to the fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and cheriſhing of <hi>inferiour Bodies,</hi> it doth it as a natural agent, <hi>neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and inſenſibly;</hi> but what thou doſt, is <hi>voluntarily and freely</hi> done, out of thine infinite love, and goodneſs to thy Creatures. Thou art the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all bleſſing, and the God of all praiſe! Lord work upon my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature by the influence of thy grace, that I may be conformed unto thee in <hi>the extenſion of mine affections unto all;</hi> in a way of doing good, not only to my <hi>neighbors,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>love me,</hi> but to mine <hi>enemies,</hi> to thoſe that <hi>curſe, hate, and deſpightfully uſe me;</hi> that ſo I may approve my ſelf <hi>a true child of my father which is in heaven; and be perfect, even as he is perfect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet this beneficence of the ſun worketh <hi>not alike upon all;</hi> thoſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious beams that <hi>ſoften the wax,</hi> do but <hi>harden the Clay;</hi> and as they make the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107494:13"/> 
                  <hi>flowers ſmell the ſweeter,</hi> ſo they ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate no further upon <hi>the Dunghill,</hi> then to make that the <hi>more fetide, and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</hi> It is a ſad thing to be <hi>hardened by mercies,</hi> and to be <hi>the worſe for Gods being good to us!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though this <hi>ſun-light</hi> be ſo pleaſant to behold, yet it doth mine eyes no good to gaze upon it. If the luſtre of <hi>a created light</hi> be ſo dazeling; how <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approacheable</hi> muſt that <hi>divine light be</hi> wherein <hi>the great Creator</hi> dwelleth, the reſplendency whereof is the <hi>light of light?</hi> Content thy ſelf, O my Soul, with that proſpect thou haſt had of God's goodneſs (ſo far as he hath been pleaſed to reveal himſelf unto thee) but do not preſume to ſpeculate into his glory, leaſt thou be oppreſſed with it.</p>
               <p>It is impoſſible to ſee <hi>this light,</hi> but by <hi>its own light:</hi> who ever beheld <hi>the ſun,</hi> but by <hi>the light of the ſun?</hi> as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible is it to ſee <hi>the Father of lights,</hi> but by the <hi>radiancy of the Son,</hi> who is <hi>the brightneſs of his glory! or to diſcern
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107494:13"/> the things of the Spirit of God,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by <hi>the revelation of his ſpirit! The commandements of the Lord is pure, inlightening the eyes:</hi> we <hi>ſee it,</hi> and ſee <hi>by it.</hi> But what is become of all thoſe heavenly tapers, thoſe ſpangles of light, that did ſo lately adorne the skie? How hath the luſtre of this predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant light obſcured, and darkened them; It is in <hi>one ſence,</hi> a ſad exchange between <hi>the light of the Sun,</hi> and the <hi>light of</hi> the <hi>Moon and Starrs;</hi> that the Sun, though it do open, and reveal <hi>the ſight of earthly things,</hi> yet it cloſeth, and ſhutteth up the proſpect of <hi>the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Globe,</hi> ſo that we cannot diſcerne the beauty, and variety of thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bodies above us, as we may do in the night. It is <hi>the miſery of proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity,</hi> that as by reaſon of the brightneſs of that light wherewith it is environed, it giveth us a clear view of <hi>the glory of this world,</hi> and of all the vanities in it; ſo withal it darkeneth, and concealeth <hi>divine things,</hi> and thereby indiſpoſeth us to raiſe our affections unto them: And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107494:14"/> on the other ſide, it is <hi>the felicity of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity,</hi> that although the aire about it be very obſcure, yet therein we <hi>beſt diſcern God, and ſpiritual things;</hi> ſo <hi>Job</hi> in his afflicton could ſay, <hi>Now mine eye ſeeth thee,</hi> of whom before he had only <hi>heard, by the hearing of the ear.</hi> Lord thou knoweſt what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is fitteſt for me, and I preſume not to appoint thy wiſdome, but ſo far as <hi>a poor beggar may be a chooſer,</hi> I beſeech thee rather to keep me <hi>in the dark</hi> (if thorough that vaile, I may be admitted to ſee <hi>the light of thy counten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi>) then to ſuffer me to be <hi>dazeled with the luſtre of this vain world,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is <hi>nothing to be ſeen,</hi> but that which <hi>is nothing,</hi> and <hi>leſs then nothing;</hi> O let me rather enjoy <hi>light in darkneſs,</hi> then <hi>live in darkneſs,</hi> when I am <hi>in the light!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the beginning,</hi> for the firſt <hi>three dayes</hi> of the Creation week, there was <hi>no ſun at all;</hi> but yet <hi>there was light,</hi> and that light was univerſally diffuſed thorough all parts, untill it pleaſed God
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107494:14"/> to contract it into one body. O Lord, <hi>thou alone doeſt great wonders! how great are thy works?</hi> how great <hi>this work?</hi> wherein thou didſt (as I may ſay) create <hi>the effect, before the cauſe.</hi> Thou art not limited to the <hi>methods of our weak reaſon,</hi> but canſt do every thing, <hi>according to the council of thine own will,</hi> not only <hi>by,</hi> but <hi>without,</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> to meanes. There is no glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, no truſting but in thee alone, unto whom <hi>all means,</hi> and <hi>more,</hi> are <hi>alike</hi> ſubſervient!</p>
               <p>As in the Creation, during thoſe <hi>firſt three dayes,</hi> God made, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the light, and then upon <hi>the fourth day,</hi> made <hi>that light a ſun;</hi> ſo in his order of proceeding with his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he giveth them <hi>a three dayes light;</hi> the firſt <hi>of nature,</hi> when he quickeneth them in their Mothers womb, with <hi>a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoul;</hi> the ſecond <hi>of Grace,</hi> when he regenerateth them in <hi>the womb of his Church,</hi> by his <hi>Sanctifying ſpirit;</hi> the third of <hi>beatitude,</hi> in a ſtate of bliſs, when he receiveth their departed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107494:15"/> Souls into his reſt; and then upon <hi>the fourth day</hi> (that is, at the general reſurrection) when he reuniteth their Souls, and bodies in glory, he <hi>gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this light into a Sun,</hi> from which time they ſhall to all eternity <hi>ſhine forth, as the Sun in the Kingdome of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What a <hi>World will that be, when we ſhall have no Sun again?</hi> when we ſhall <hi>need none?</hi> nay, when inſtead of <hi>one Sun,</hi> there ſhall be <hi>more Suns</hi> than there are <hi>Stars in the Firmament?</hi> when <hi>every Saint</hi> ſhall be <hi>a Sun,</hi> and yet <hi>all thoſe Saints</hi> (as if they were but <hi>ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtars</hi>) ſhall receive <hi>their light from another Sun of infinite glory;</hi> from <hi>the glory of God, the Fountain of all light?</hi> that <hi>light is ſown here for the Righteous;</hi> O when will the harveſt time come? Awake, awake, O my Soul, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template that happy time, whenſoever it ſhall come. It is <hi>ſome anticipation of it,</hi> to think <hi>upon it before it comes! Watch for that morning, more than they that watch for the morning!</hi> But, Lord,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107494:15"/> it is not <hi>of him that watcheth,</hi> no more than <hi>of him that willeth,</hi> but <hi>of thee who ſheweſt mercy!</hi> O do thou, by the irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of thy grace make ſuch a clear day in my Soul, as that I may not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſee thy light</hi> here, and <hi>receive in it,</hi> and <hi>walk by it,</hi> but <hi>be it;</hi> ſo ſhall I <hi>be light in thee,</hi> and (according to that expreſſion in thine own word) thou ſhalt then <hi>walk in me! my path ſhall then be as the ſhining light,</hi> and I ſhall <hi>ſhine out more and more unto that full, clear and everlaſtingly perfect day of thy Glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. III.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my riſing out of Bed, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on my Cloaths.</head>
               <p>SLuggiſh Soul, how long wilt thou lie lazing? what, <hi>yet a little ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber? yet, a little folding of the hands?</hi> Awake, <hi>they that ſleep, ſleep in the night,</hi> do not fancy thy ſelf to be among the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107494:16"/> 
                  <hi>Antipodes,</hi> as if it were night with thee, when it is day with us. If thou wilt but open thy window, thou mayeſt with ſhame behold the Sun already mounted above our horizon, and in his ſilent language ſeeming to reproach thee, that he hath <hi>travelled round about the world but Yeſterday,</hi> and <hi>yet is up before thee this morning!</hi> let no ſleep, like an unjuſt <hi>Publican,</hi> exact <hi>more of thy time, then is his due,</hi> and make thy dayes ſhorter, then God hath made them. <hi>There is ſo much life gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as is ſaved out of ſleep!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be not too ſecure in this condition; whilſt thou art <hi>drouzing,</hi> the devil is <hi>hunting;</hi> and he hath a way to hunt Souls with <hi>Pillowes,</hi> and <hi>night-caps.</hi> Remember he is <hi>no ſluggard,</hi> but will <hi>ſurely roſte what he takes in hunting!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How ſtrangely do thoſe people live, that begin <hi>their morning at noone,</hi> and <hi>their noone at night;</hi> that <hi>turn day into night, and live backward?</hi> But it is no wonder to ſee Owls fly abroad at late hours! O my Soul, God never cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107494:16"/> thee <hi>to live in a feather-bed! life conſiſts in action; idleneſs is but a living death.</hi> And <hi>what doth the Lord require of thee;</hi> not to lie ſtill; but to ariſe, and be doing; <hi>to walke whilſt thou haſt light, humbly with thy God, and honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with thy neighbour, as a child of the day!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Up then my Soul, and <hi>caſt off the workes of darkneſs; night clothes are not a fit weare for the day.</hi> He, whom thou loveſt, calleth thee, do not ſay, <hi>I have put off my coat, how ſhall I put it on?</hi> but without delay, eccho that call, with a <hi>lo, I come, to do thy will!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But where are my clothes? O my God, what <hi>a beggerly creature</hi> am I, that have nothing to put on, but what I am faine <hi>to borrow?</hi> if it were not for the ſupply which <hi>I</hi> receive from <hi>a poor worme,</hi> from <hi>a ſilly ſheep,</hi> I could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be <hi>fine,</hi> nor <hi>warme.</hi> By right <hi>the borrower ſhould be ſervant to the lender;</hi> but Lord, thou haſt given me <hi>domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over theſe ſerviceable creditors.</hi> How ſhould I at once be humbled under the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107494:17"/> ſenſe of mine <hi>own indigence,</hi> and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully exalted in the apprehenſion of <hi>thy goodneſs</hi> to me? But <hi>what is man?</hi> nay (which is worſe) <hi>what am</hi> I? ſurely I <hi>am more brutiſh then any man;</hi> more ſottiſh then thoſe <hi>brute creatures,</hi> unto whom I am <hi>ſo much indebted.</hi> They are <hi>not proud</hi> of thoſe habiliments which <hi>they impart to me,</hi> I live upon <hi>their col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections,</hi> and yet am apt to pride my ſelf in <hi>this beggery.</hi> O my ſoul, <hi>this glorying is not good:</hi> what is it, but <hi>a glorying in ſhame?</hi> nakedneſs was <hi>the original bravery</hi> of our firſt parents in Paradiſe, and ſhall be our <hi>laſt bravery</hi> in heaven, when we ſhall be in the <hi>Angels mode.</hi> Lord correct this depraved na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in me by thy grace, that I may no longer <hi>faſhion my ſelf</hi> according to my former luſts and vanities, but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to that <hi>inward dreſs,</hi> which <hi>in thy ſight is of greateſt price;</hi> ſo though <hi>mine outſide</hi> may be <hi>plain and bare,</hi> I ſhall be ſure to be <hi>all Glorious within.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet, O my God, thou knoweſt I have need of <hi>raiment,</hi> as well <hi>as of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107494:17"/> food,</hi> and other outward accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and thou art pleaſed to allow me a <hi>providential</hi> (though not <hi>a ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous) care,</hi> for what <hi>I ſhall put on.</hi> I beſeech thee ſo to order my thoughts, that in the purſuit of theſe things, I may follow thy preſcribed method of huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry; <hi>firſt to ſeek thy Kingdom, and thy righteouſneſs,</hi> and then in <hi>the uſe of good means</hi> to <hi>truſt thee for the reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in what a new caſe am I, when I am apparelled? how warmed and comforted? bleſſed be God, that I have not that curſe upon me, mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Prophecy of <hi>Haggai,</hi> to be <hi>cloathed and not warm,</hi> thoſe <hi>cloaths can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but do me good, that are</hi> lined <hi>with thy bleſſing!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the common opinion, that our cloaths <hi>warm us,</hi> but the truth is, <hi>we warm our cloaths,</hi> and they do but <hi>keep us warm with our own heat.</hi> As it is in this, ſo it is in all earthly comforts, which have <hi>nothing of ſatisfaction in themſelves,</hi> but that placency which we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107494:18"/> take to be in them, is but <hi>a reſultance from our own minds, a warmth which we give them.</hi> Lord ſanctifie theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things unto me, that, in the fruition of them, I may ſo <hi>uſe them,</hi> as not to <hi>abuſe them,</hi> by looking for that <hi>in them,</hi> which is only to be found <hi>in thee.</hi> Thou art <hi>the bleſſing of all bleſſings;</hi> from thee I <hi>have all,</hi> in thee I <hi>enjoy all,</hi> and <hi>without thee all is nothing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O my God, it is the deſire of my Soul to be <hi>dreſſed</hi> and <hi>fitted to wait upon thee</hi> in the way wherein thou wouldeſt have me to go, but I dare not think of coming into thy preſence in <hi>an unſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Garment;</hi> in the <hi>naſty rags of the old man;</hi> and I have <hi>no other ſute of mine own but that.</hi> O do thou give that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py word of command, to have that <hi>filthy Garment taken away from me;</hi> and ſay unto my Soul, <hi>behold, I have cauſed thine iniquity to paſs away, and I will cloath thee with change of rayment.</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee furniſh thy poor Creature, out of <hi>thy divine wardrobe</hi> with thoſe graces that may <hi>moſt adorn my profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:107494:18"/> above all vouchſafe to cloath me with <hi>the Garment of mine elder Brother</hi> (that is <hi>the beſt Robe</hi>) and under <hi>that covert grant me thy bleſſing:</hi> ſo what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver may befal me here, I ſhall be ſure to riſe in a happy hour at the laſt day; when being <hi>clothed with his righteouſneſs, I ſhall be clothed upon with his Glory!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION. IV.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my retirement into my Cloſet.</head>
               <p>HOw little doth <hi>the world</hi> know the happineſs of a Cloſet? But it is no wonder, for this happineſs is <hi>not of the world:</hi> and therefore by thoſe that <hi>can diſcern nothing ſpiritually,</hi> it is eſteemed as no other, then a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in a <hi>ſedentary ſluggiſh life,</hi> or as no better then a <hi>melancholy diſcontented humour.</hi> But my Soul, thou art above theſe miſapprehenſions. Go in; ſhall I ſay into <hi>this room,</hi> or rather into <hi>this other world?</hi> into <hi>thy world?</hi> for when
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107494:19"/> thou art abroad, thou art abroad, thou art <hi>in a common world,</hi> wherein every perſon hath <hi>an inter-right</hi> with thee; but here, within the <hi>incloſure of theſe Walls,</hi> thou art in a <hi>particular world of thine own;</hi> and <hi>all is thine own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>this little Monarchy,</hi> methinks I may ſay without offence, <hi>Soul take thine eaſe,</hi> and <hi>with quiet ſenſes enjoy thine own company,</hi> it is ſomething for a man to be <hi>his own inmate, to dwell with himſelf;</hi> and no ſmall happineſs in that cohabitation to live quietly, and without <hi>a dropping houſe.</hi> There is a <hi>phyſical vertue in quietneſs; ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes in the body, and moſt diſtempers in the mind are cured by it;</hi> I may add fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that there is a <hi>heavenlineſs</hi> in it; thoſe Regions that are <hi>higheſt</hi> are <hi>quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt,</hi> and God himſelf who is <hi>higher then the higheſt,</hi> is in <hi>the fruition of himſelf,</hi> the <hi>moſt quieſcent.</hi> O my God, whilſt others affect <hi>the wings of an Eagle to fly high,</hi> let it be my prayer to have the <hi>wings of a Dove, to fly away, and be at reſt;</hi> that being ſequeſtred from the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107494:19"/> vexatious vanities of the world, I may enjoy a free converſation with thee in heaven; ſo ſhall <hi>my quietneſs</hi> be my <hi>ſtrength;</hi> and <hi>this reſt a prelibu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my eternal reſt!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet my Soul <hi>take heed unto thy ſelf in this ſolitude;</hi> it is poſſible for thee to be <hi>in ill company, when thou art alone.</hi> Be not raſh; but <hi>think what thou wouldſt think!</hi> do not affect <hi>a free will in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; evil thoughts have an evil communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in them,</hi> and may <hi>corrupt good manners: ſlight not vain thoughts; the thought of fooliſhneſs is ſin;</hi> and every <hi>fooliſh thought,</hi> as well as <hi>every idle word,</hi> muſt be accounted for; bar them out, as much as thou canſt, and though they may clamour at it, and <hi>challeng a preſcription for a thorough fare in thee,</hi> and thou art not able altogether to hinder their way, but that they will break thorough, yet never let it be <hi>with thy conſent,</hi> and ſufferance, and ſo long <hi>the treſpaſs will be on their ſide.</hi> Above all be ſure to give them <hi>no lodging;</hi> though thou canſt not hinder the birds
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107494:20"/> of the air <hi>from flying over thine head</hi> yet thou maiſt keep them <hi>from build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and neſtling in thine hair:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But my God, what ſhall I do? or wherewith ſhall I come before thee, who have not ſo much as a good thought to offer unto thee? O do thou <hi>work all my thoughts,</hi> as well as (in reference to any good) thou <hi>doeſt work all my workes in me: all my ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency is of thee. Perfect thy ſtrength in my weakneſs,</hi> and I, <hi>even when I am weak, ſhall be made ſtrong.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Methinks this place hath ſomething of a <hi>Bethel</hi> in it: I may call it <hi>the houſe of God,</hi> where I have frequently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed a ſweet and comfortable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with his divine Majeſty; and <hi>the gate of Heaven,</hi> where I have often <hi>knockt,</hi> and it hath <hi>been opened unto me.</hi> From this poor room I can freely, and without diſturbance, or interruption look up, and with an eye of faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template <hi>the glories of heaven, the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of the Saints, the perfection of thoſe tabernacles not made with hands,</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107494:20"/> thoſe inviſibilities,</hi> which <hi>mortal eye hath not ſeen,</hi> nor <hi>ear heard,</hi> nor <hi>heart conceived;</hi> from hence, I can look down upon <hi>all the workes, that are done under the Sun,</hi> and ſee that they are but as the labours of a company of ants in an ant-hill, where ſome are emploied <hi>to gather in their ſmall proviſions,</hi> and others are buiſied <hi>about their eggs,</hi> and <hi>young ones;</hi> and ſome go up, and ſome go down, croſſing and thwarting one another; and all are in action, and <hi>all is about a little heap of duſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the vain world deride theſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, and retirements; it is, and ſhall be the delight of my Soul to enjoy both: whereby I may gaine <hi>more light</hi> to my knowledg, <hi>more heat</hi> to my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and <hi>more acquaintance</hi> with my God; and from a right eſtimation of <hi>the temporal things which are ſeen,</hi> come to have a ſweet fruition of thoſe <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal things which are not ſeen.</hi> In order to this, <hi>O thou God of my praiers, and praiſes, teach me how</hi> to pray <hi>that I may</hi> meditate; <hi>and teach me how</hi> to meditate
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107494:21"/> 
                  <hi>that I may</hi> pray; ſo <hi>ſhall the words of my mouth, and the meditations of my heart, be acceptable in thy ſight;</hi> and thou ſhalt have <hi>the praiſe of thine own work in me!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION. V.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the contentment I have in my Books and Study.</head>
               <p>HEre is the beſt <hi>ſolitary company</hi> in the World: and in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar cheifly excelling any other, that <hi>here</hi> I am ſure to converſe <hi>with none but wiſe men;</hi> but <hi>abroad</hi> it is impoſſible for me to avoid <hi>the ſociety of fools:</hi> what an advantage have I by this good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, that beſides the help which I receive from hence, in reference to <hi>my life after this Life,</hi> I can enjoy the life <hi>of ſo many Ages before</hi> I <hi>lived?</hi> that I can be acquainted with <hi>the paſſages of three or four thouſand years ago,</hi> as if they were <hi>the weekly occurrences!</hi> here, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107494:21"/> travelling ſo far as <hi>Endor,</hi> I can call up the <hi>ableſt ſpirits</hi> of thoſe times; the <hi>learnedſt Philoſophers,</hi> the <hi>wiſeſt Counſellours,</hi> the <hi>greateſt Generals,</hi> and make them ſerviceable to me; I can make bold with the beſt Jewels they have in their treaſury, with the ſame freedome that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> borrowed of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and, without ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Felony make uſe of them, as mine own. I can hear, <hi>without treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing,</hi> go into their <hi>Vine-Yards,</hi> and not only eat my fill of their Grapes <hi>for my pleaſure;</hi> but put up as much as I will <hi>in my Veſſel,</hi> and <hi>ſtore it up</hi> for my profit, and advantage.</p>
               <p>How doth this proſpect at once ſet off <hi>the Goodneſs of God</hi> to me, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover <hi>mine own weakneſs?</hi> his <hi>Goodneſs</hi> in providing theſe helps for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of mine underſtanding; and my <hi>weakneſs</hi> in needing them. What a pitiful ſimple creature am I, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live <hi>to any purpoſe,</hi> without the help of ſo many <hi>other mens brains?</hi> Lord, let this be the firſt Leſſon that I learn
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107494:22"/> from theſe ſilent counſellers, <hi>to know my own ignorance:</hi> other <hi>knowledg puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth up, this edifieth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was a ſcoffing, and unhandſome ſpeech in <hi>Feſtus</hi> to <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>much learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made him mad:</hi> but it was ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſadly ſaid by the prophet <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> that <hi>every man</hi> (every idolatrous wicked man) is <hi>fooliſh, or brutiſh,</hi> (which is <hi>mad almoſt) by his own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg.</hi> It is poſſible for a man to <hi>know ſo much,</hi> that at laſt, by <hi>overvalluing his knowledg,</hi> he may come to <hi>know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as he ought to know;</hi> and we have an unhappy proof of this, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>our firſt parents;</hi> who, out of a fond deſire to know <hi>more then came to their ſhare,</hi> tranſgreſſed, and thereby brought themſelves to that paſs, that <hi>they know only their own ſhame,</hi> and were <hi>aſhamed of their own knowledg.</hi> Whilſt others pleaſe themſelves <hi>in high notions, and ſpeculations,</hi> it ſhall be my ſtudy to follow the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> rule, and <hi>to be wiſe unto ſobriety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we have a generation of people
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107494:22"/> in the world, that are ſo far from put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves upon <hi>the hazard of knowing too much,</hi> that they affect a kind of <hi>Socratical</hi> knowledg (though it be the clear contrary way) <hi>a knowledg of knowing nothing</hi> they hate learning, and wiſdom, and underſtanding with <hi>that perfect hatred,</hi> that if one could fancy ſuch things to be in paradiſe, one would think (if I may <hi>ſpeak it,</hi> as I <hi>mean it</hi> without profaneſs) that <hi>the Devil could not tempt them to come neer the tree of knowledg;</hi> I cannot ſay theſe are <hi>in a ſtate of innocency,</hi> but I am ſure they are in <hi>a ſtate of ſimplicity.</hi> But among thoſe few perſons (eſpecially thoſe <hi>of quality</hi>) that pretend to look after bookes, how many are there that affect ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to look <hi>upon them,</hi> then <hi>in them?</hi> ſome covet to have <hi>Libraries in their houſes,</hi> as Ladies deſire to have <hi>Cupboards of plate in their Chambers,</hi> only <hi>for ſhew;</hi> as if they were only to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <hi>their roomes,</hi> and not <hi>their mindes;</hi> if <hi>the only having of ſtore of Bookes,</hi> were ſufficient to improve a man, the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:107494:23"/> would have the advantage of all others; but certainly bookes were made <hi>for uſe,</hi> and not <hi>for oſtentation;</hi> in vain do they boaſt of <hi>full Libraries,</hi> that are contented to live with <hi>empty heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In oppoſition to theſe extreams, I meet with another ſort of people, that delight themſelves in reading, but it is in ſuch <hi>a deſultory way,</hi> running from one book to another, as Birds skip from from one bough to another, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, that it is no mervaile if they <hi>get nothing but their labour for their paines,</hi> when they <hi>ſeek nothing, but change, and diverſion: they that ride poſt, can obſerve but little.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is in <hi>reading,</hi> as it is <hi>in making</hi> many bookes; there may be a <hi>pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtraction</hi> in it, but <hi>little or no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</hi> I would therefore do in this, as Merchants uſe to do in their trading; who in a coaſting way, put in at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ports, and take in what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities they afford, but <hi>ſettle their factories</hi> in thoſe places onely, which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107494:23"/> are <hi>of ſpecial note:</hi> I would by the by, allow my ſelf <hi>a traffick</hi> with ſundry authors, as I happned to light upon them, <hi>for my recreation;</hi> and I would make the beſt advantage that I could of them; but I would <hi>fix my ſtudy</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe only, that are <hi>of moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> to fit me <hi>for action,</hi> which is the <hi>true end of all learning,</hi> and for <hi>the ſervice of God,</hi> which is <hi>the true end of all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Lord teach me ſo to ſtudy <hi>other mens works,</hi> as <hi>not to neglect mine own;</hi> and ſo to ſtudy <hi>thy word,</hi> which is <hi>thy work,</hi> that it may be <hi>a lamp unto my feet, and a light unto my path;</hi> my can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to work by. Take me off from <hi>the curioſity of knowing only to know;</hi> from the vanity of <hi>knowing only to be known;</hi> and from the folly of pretending <hi>to know more then I do know;</hi> and let it be my wiſdome to ſtudy <hi>to know thee,</hi> who art <hi>life eternal.</hi> Write <hi>thy law in my heart,</hi> and <hi>I ſhall be the beſt book here.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="meditation">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:107494:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION. VI.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon an entertainment of Godly Friends.</head>
               <p>WHat a deal of Heaven is there in in this company? methinkes, like <hi>Abraham,</hi> I <hi>entertain Angels;</hi> the comfort, and illumination that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from them, hath ſo much of that ſociety in it. Certainly there is no pleaſure in this world comparable to the enjoyment of <hi>the Communion of Saints;</hi> where good people are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted, and united together <hi>in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>judgment,</hi> and <hi>intereſt,</hi> as <hi>fellow members of one body,</hi> which (though <hi>many</hi>) have but <hi>one heart,</hi> and <hi>one head;</hi> and are ſo <hi>one another,</hi> that they are members <hi>one of another,</hi> that they <hi>are all one in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in the name of wonder, what is it that ſhould be ſo taking in this company? where is <hi>the wine,</hi> and <hi>the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107494:24"/> ſtrong drink?</hi> where are the <hi>coſtly oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and the <hi>Crownes</hi> of <hi>roſebuds?</hi> the <hi>Muſick, dancing, laughing?</hi> the world underſtands the language of theſe jol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities without the help of an interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: But for people to meet, only <hi>to talk one another into gravity,</hi> and to ſpend time in ſpeculative diſcourſes <hi>of another world,</hi> when they might give themſelves <hi>the pleaſure of this:</hi> if this be <hi>mirth, what doth it?</hi> It may ſeem a ſtrange and an impertinent advice of this great Moraliſt to his friend <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilius,</hi> that <hi>above all things, he ſhould be careful to learn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, how to be merry;</hi> one would think there ſhould go no great matter of Philoſophy to that: But there is a miſtake in it: True mirth is <hi>Metaphyſical, and ſupernatural.</hi> It is not <hi>the crackling of thornes under a pot; a blaze,</hi> and <hi>a noiſe,</hi> and <hi>a nothing;</hi> (the laughter of a mad man is not mirth); but it is <hi>a ſevere,</hi> and (I may ſay) <hi>a Divine thing.</hi> It is an anticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the joyes of Heaven in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful ſociety of a good conſcience,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107494:25"/> 
                  <hi>when we are alone;</hi> and (together with that) of conſcientious friends, <hi>when we are in company.</hi> They are <hi>the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hearts, that keep the continual Feaſt.</hi> It is one of the Devils lyes, and that of which he hath made as great advantage, as of any, that <hi>Religion is a dull flat melancholy thing;</hi> whereas in truth, <hi>there is no ſuch cleere, defecate mirth, as that which cometh from the Springs above.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ſpeaking of the coming of our Saviour in the fleſh, gave this Character of him, <hi>That he ſhould not be ſad,</hi> (ſo it is rendered in the <hi>vulgar tranſlation</hi>) that he ſhould not be of a ſullen, retired diſpoſition, but amicable, and free; and it was verified in his converſation. <hi>He was anointed with the oyle of gladneſs,</hi> and we have that <hi>Spiritual unction</hi> from him. Let the men of the world deride this heavenly mirth, as <hi>the Covetous Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees derided the true riches,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpake of, as a fantaſtical thing; they do but like thoſe, that make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves merry, at the ſight of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:107494:25"/> 
                  <hi>dancing a farr off,</hi> when they <hi>cannot hear the muſick</hi> whereby their geſtures and motions are directed, and therefore judge them to be antick, and ridiculous: They take this mirth to be no other then a folly, and <hi>laugh at they know not what;</hi> becauſe being at ſuch a diſtance from the godly, they cannot take notice of <hi>the heavenly har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and accord,</hi> that is between their <hi>orderly converſation,</hi> and <hi>the aires of Gods ſpirit,</hi> quickening, and inlivening them with <hi>joyes unſpeakable, and full of glory.</hi> Nothing but <hi>ignorance is the mother of this miſopinion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what are theſe friends, that are ſo wellcom? are they <hi>perſons of honour,</hi> or <hi>intereſt;</hi> is there any thing to be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by them? the faſhion of the world is, to <hi>ſerve the Ball</hi> only to thoſe <hi>that can return it;</hi> and to <hi>bid thoſe only,</hi> that can <hi>bid againe.</hi> It is a ſad word; <hi>Not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called; but God hath choſen the fooliſh, weak, baſe inconſiderable things of the world, things
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107494:26"/> that are nothings, to route and confound all humane wiſdome and might, and to annul things that are.</hi> The Lord <hi>ſeeth not, as man ſeeth;</hi> vainglorious fooles may pride themſelves in that, which is <hi>none of their own</hi> (the vertue and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity of their anceſtors) or in that which hath <hi>no being at all, but in fancy,</hi> riches and eſtate: It is not flaggs, and pedegree, but <hi>a noble heart,</hi> that <hi>makes a noble perſon; true goodneſs is true great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and <hi>Gods bleſſing, the true riches; he that hath that, hath all</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſlight account as there is made of theſe good people, and of ſuch as theſe, they are <hi>the Children of the King of heaven,</hi> and though poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly their names may not be extant in <hi>the Heralds bookes,</hi> they will be <hi>found written in the book of life.</hi> Our <hi>little great ones</hi> of the world may think them only fit, to ſtand at <hi>the lower end of the roome,</hi> or to <hi>ſit under the footſtoole;</hi> but with their good leave, they that ſhall one day <hi>ſit down with</hi> Abraham, <hi>and</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>in the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> are good enough now, to be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107494:26"/> gueſts at the beſt table upon earth.</p>
               <p>How happy are the hours that are ſpent in ſuch company as this? to ſpeak more properly, they are not ſpent but gaind: So much <hi>time</hi> thus redeemed, is ſo much <hi>life</hi> clearly gotten; there is a prolongation of <hi>life</hi> in a <hi>holy Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> it is one thing <hi>to be in the world,</hi> and another <hi>to live in it.</hi> They only live, that live well. Vitious perſons, that give themſelves up to their <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> are <hi>dead</hi> whilſt they <hi>live,</hi> and are but a kind of walking <hi>Ghoſts;</hi> but the living, the living, they praiſe God, and they onely <hi>live,</hi> that do praiſe him.</p>
               <p>There is nothing that hath a greater influence upon our lives, than the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany we keep, generally <hi>Men</hi> are like that <hi>Mercurial Planet,</hi> good or bad ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>their conjunction with others.</hi> There is in all ſocieties an attracting, and aſſimilating <hi>quality;</hi> and altho thorough the corruption that is predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant in our natures, this is more apparent in the operation <hi>of evil,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>of Good Company,</hi> yet there
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:107494:27"/> is true grace, this Magnetick Vertue will ſhew it ſelf, and thoſe that are <hi>touched</hi> with it, will endeavour to <hi>work</hi> upon others, and <hi>to make</hi> them like themſelves; ſo <hi>Philip</hi> will draw <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel; Andrew</hi> will draw <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> (when converted) wil ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en <hi>his Brethen.</hi> And of this the <hi>worſt times</hi> are the <hi>beſt Witneſſes;</hi> when tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the common oppoſition of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, the affections of thoſe that are good, are the more inflamed each to other: for as <hi>Roſes</hi> and <hi>Garlick</hi> ſet near together, do by extraction of contrary juices out of the Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come both, in their ſeveral kinds, the ſtronger ſented; and the <hi>Roſes</hi> are the more ſweet and oderate, by the fetide and ſtinking neighbourhood of the <hi>Garlick;</hi> ſo by the contrary workings of oppoſite parties, the <hi>Good</hi> are made very <hi>Good,</hi> and the <hi>Bad</hi> very <hi>Bad;</hi> and thoſe that are <hi>good,</hi> are meliorated, and imbettered, even by the illneſs of thoſe that are <hi>bad.</hi> O my Soul be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with whom thou doſt aſſociate; it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107494:27"/> may be diſcretion to carry a <hi>fair civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> to thoſe that are <hi>without,</hi> but let thy delight be fixed upon the <hi>Saints</hi> that are in the Earth; the touch of their converſion will derive vertue to thee. Be not conformed to the Men of the world, but let their contrary qualities ſerve, as by a ſpiritual <hi>Antiperiſtaſis,</hi> to ſtrengthen thy vertue, and to make it the more compact in it ſelf; ſo <hi>if thou canſt not amend others,</hi> thou ſhalt be ſure however <hi>to be amended thy ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But alas, what are all worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts? <hi>this good fellowſhip will not hold.</hi> We cannot ſit by it, like thoſe <hi>long lived Fathers before the flood,</hi> who might meet, and be merry together <hi>two or three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years,</hi> and part with a promiſe to ſee one another againe <hi>ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares after.</hi> We are <hi>but of Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and know not what to morrow may bring forth;</hi> a few yeares, or months, or poſſibly a leſs time, may determine all our jollity. This were ſad indeed, <hi>if we had no hope,</hi> but having that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor hold, we may comfort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:107494:28"/> with this, that wherever we are <hi>ſeparated,</hi> we can enjoy the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>of one anothers praiers,</hi> and meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>at the Throne of Grace:</hi> And tho death may part us here <hi>for a while,</hi> it will be but with <hi>a good night one to another,</hi> as when we go to bed, and <hi>to morrow</hi> we ſhall meet <hi>never to part.</hi> In the mean time, <hi>O my Soul think</hi> what a bleſſing it is to have <hi>the eternal God to be thy friend,</hi> who in the defailliance of all theſe tranſitory comforts, will <hi>not faile to make up all loſſes with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> But <hi>will God indeed dwell with men on the earth?</hi> will <hi>the high and lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty one that inhabiteth eternity,</hi> vouchſafe <hi>to humble, and abaſe himſelf ſo low,</hi> as not only <hi>to take notice of,</hi> but in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite condeſcention <hi>to enter into cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, into friendſhip</hi> with poor mortal ſinful creatures? with ſuch a deſpicable worme as I am? to call me friend, as he doth thoſe that obey his commands? what? <hi>friend worme? friend duſt? O the depth!</hi> Lord, <hi>what is man?</hi> what <hi>am I,</hi> poor <hi>no man, a nothing,</hi> that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:107494:28"/> thou <hi>ſo regardeſt me?</hi> O my God, I am unworthy to be called thine, in any relation; unworthy to be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the number of <hi>thine hired Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> much more to be accounted in the rank <hi>of thy friends;</hi> but it is thy pleaſure to call <hi>things that are not, as if they were,</hi> and ſuch is the influence of thy power, that by vertue of <hi>that call,</hi> thou canſt make <hi>things to be,</hi> what <hi>they were not.</hi> O let the power of thy gracious vocation have a perfect work upon me <hi>to change me,</hi> and I <hi>ſhall be changed,</hi> to <hi>convert me, and I ſhall be converted;</hi> ſo though by nature, I am <hi>enmity againſt thee,</hi> by grace I ſhall be <hi>reconciled to thee;</hi> I ſhall then fear thee and thy goodneſs; ſhall fear and love thee; and I ſhall love thoſe that are conformable to thy goodneſs, becauſe I fear thee; I ſhall not only have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with <hi>thine excellent ones here</hi> upon earth, but together with them enjoy ſociety with <hi>thee O Father, Son, and holy ſpirit</hi> to all eternity in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="meditation">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:107494:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. VII.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſight of a full Table.</head>
               <p>LOrd do not hold it a preſumption in thy poor duſt, and aſhes, that I humbly deſire, as thy Prophet <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> did, to talk with thee; <hi>what is man, that thou takeſt knowledge of him?</hi> thy word is mine anſwer, that tells me, it is <hi>a pittiful thing, compounded, and made up of ſin, and corruption;</hi> its <hi>Father was earth,</hi> and its <hi>Grand-father was nothing;</hi> it <hi>walketh in a vain ſhew,</hi> and is, in its <hi>greateſt eſtate, a Lye;</hi> and <hi>at its beſt, altogether vanity,</hi> which is ſo much leſs <hi>then nothing</hi> before thee. But <hi>behold I have taken upon me to ſpeak unto thee, O let not my Lord be angry, if I ask thee now, what man is</hi> not, that thou makeſt ſuch account of him, and ſo provideſt for him? thine other creatures, even thoſe that are the cheif of thy wayes, are contented with their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107494:29"/> 
                  <hi>ſingle portions;</hi> thy <hi>Behemoth</hi> is ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with <hi>that ordinary</hi> which <hi>the mountaines bring him forth,</hi> and he lookes no further; ſo is the <hi>Leviathan</hi> pleaſed with his recreation in the great and wide ſea, and that element is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for him. But man (as if all were too little for his grandeur) hath no bounds, <hi>thou haſt put all things under his feet,</hi> Earth, Sea, Aire, Fire, pay contribution to his ſubſiſtance, and comfort; <hi>what couldſt thou have done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that thou haſt not done? O Lord, our Lord, how excellent is thy name? all thy workes praiſe thee;</hi> how ſhould <hi>man</hi> praiſe thee, for <hi>whoſe ſervice</hi> thou haſt made <hi>all thy workes?</hi> what <hi>a deal of labour is here for the mouth?</hi> what <hi>a concurrence of art with nature,</hi> to pleaſe the gluttony, not only of <hi>the mouth,</hi> but of the <hi>eye?</hi> people affect <hi>an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity in luxury,</hi> as if their <hi>wits</hi> lay in their <hi>bellies</hi> and not in their <hi>braines.</hi> It is not enough to have <hi>good meat,</hi> if it have not a relliſh of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies;</hi> it muſt be ſo ſpiced, that an <hi>Aegyptian</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:107494:30"/> would think it were rather <hi>imbalmed to be buried,</hi> and kept for <hi>Mummy,</hi> then <hi>ſeaſoned to be eaten;</hi> it muſt be ſo <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſiſied</hi> and ſo <hi>diſguiſed</hi> in the dreſſing, that every diſh muſt be <hi>a riddle,</hi> as if it were a ſpecial point of reputation for a man to eat he knowes not what: If our Forefathers could ſee our <hi>hachees,</hi> and <hi>olliaes,</hi> and <hi>hodgpodges,</hi> and ſuch like commixtures, as we make of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral meats together, they would take them to be no better, then <hi>the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges of full ſtomacks,</hi> and think that, <hi>like doggs,</hi> we affected <hi>to eat our meat twice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>to what purpoſe is this waſte?</hi> how many empty ſtomacks might this ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity have filled? poſſibly <hi>leſs at the table,</hi> and <hi>more at the door,</hi> might have done better. Certainly, <hi>we are not the better</hi> for it: this high feeding doth but cloud the underſtanding with fumes, and vapours, and pampers luſt, and breeds ill humours, and makes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for wormes, and ends in excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and who would place any feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:107494:30"/> in that, which being received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, muſt paſs at laſt by <hi>ſo ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a way</hi> from him? But for prevention of all <hi>ſurfeiting,</hi> the witty folly of this time hath found out another way, how to make <hi>coſtly entertainments,</hi> and <hi>no bodyes belly the fuller</hi> for them; an art <hi>to furniſh a table with nothing, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> with <hi>quelque choſes,</hi> and <hi>appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of meat.</hi> This is perfectly <hi>to ſpend money for that which is not bread;</hi> and it is juſtly puniſhed in the diſſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that followes it; for, as <hi>in a dream of a feaſt,</hi> ſo here, a man <hi>ſeemeth to eat,</hi> and <hi>to drink,</hi> but after all is done his Soul is <hi>empty and faint, and crav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> What is this, but to play with Gods bleſſings, as little children play with their meat, when they have weak, and ſquaimiſh, or no ſtomacks? this nicety, and wantonneſs is far from the plainneſs, and ſimplicity of the <hi>good old world,</hi> when <hi>a ſhoulder of mutton</hi> was ſet by, for <hi>the ſpecial enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of a King,</hi> in deſignation;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:107494:31"/> and <hi>a peece of veale, a diſh of butter, a meſs of milk, and a few cakes baked upon the hearth</hi> was accounted <hi>a fit welcome, and treatment for Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am not ſo ſtraight laced, as not to allow <hi>a convenient latitude</hi> in the uſe of Gods Creatures; not only for <hi>neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> but for <hi>comfort,</hi> and <hi>delight,</hi> a due regard being had to <hi>the quality of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and to <hi>the emergency of occaſions.</hi> Our ever bleſſed Saviour ſtuck not to honour diverſe <hi>feſtival intertainments with his gracious preſence.</hi> But that which is a ſcandal to me, is the ſinful abuſe of this liberty; when plaine Maiſter <hi>Nabal</hi> will needs make good his name in feaſting it like a King; and when nothing leſs will ſerve <hi>Dives</hi> then <hi>fairing deliciouſly every day:</hi> it is no wonder if <hi>his end were damnation,</hi> whoſe <hi>belly was his God.</hi> We are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to rejoyce in the lawful uſe of the creatures, but we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to abuſe them either thorough <hi>profuſeneſs or wantonneſs or cruelty.</hi> What an ugly ſight is it to ſee men <hi>eat</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:107494:31"/> not only <hi>as to live,</hi> but as if they <hi>lived only to eat?</hi> to ſee them <hi>eat,</hi> as if they were <hi>at day labour,</hi> and in <hi>their voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> turning Gods <hi>curſe into wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> when with the paines they take, <hi>they eat their bread in the ſweat of their faces.</hi> O my God, what ſhall I ſay, or what ſhall I not ſay of them? <hi>Their throats are open Sepulchers,</hi> wherein to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their graces, and parts, and eſtates, they <hi>bury themſelves, in themſelves.</hi> They are no better then <hi>living vaults,</hi> or <hi>ſewers,</hi> only of uſe for the <hi>conveiance of filth, and ordure:</hi> ſuch <hi>beaſtly creatures,</hi> as it is a hard matter to ſpeak of them <hi>in cleanly terms.</hi> Who can take in a Dunghill without offence?</p>
               <p>In <hi>oppoſition to this exceſs,</hi> there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother generation of people, that run into <hi>a contrary extream,</hi> affecting <hi>a ſhew of wiſdome in humility, and neglect of the body;</hi> who refuſe and reiect Gods bleſſings, out of a ſeeming fear leaſt they ſhould abuſe them; and upon that account <hi>abſtaine from meates,</hi> which
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:107494:32"/> 
                  <hi>he hath created to be received with thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving;</hi> but <hi>who hath required this at their hands? every creature of God is good, and nothing to be refuſed,</hi> that comes from his divine bounty. <hi>Ahaz</hi> was never a wit the more tenderer conſcienced, for <hi>refuſing to ask a ſigne</hi> when it was <hi>offered him.</hi> We do but provoke <hi>Gods patience,</hi> when we will not accept the <hi>free tenders of his goodneſs,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord keep thy ſervant in a middle condition, between luxuriancy, and penury; <hi>feed me with food conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for me;</hi> that as on the one ſide, I may not <hi>thorough fulneſs deny thee;</hi> ſo on the other, I may not <hi>thorough want be reduced to take irregular wayes.</hi> Give me ſuch <hi>a mannerly appetite</hi> (as to the things of this world) that conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diligently what thy providence hath ſet before me, I may reſt <hi>contented</hi> and <hi>ſatisfied with thy carving,</hi> without <hi>reaching over the board for a better bit,</hi> or rudely ſnatching it <hi>from my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours trencher;</hi> ſo ſhall I in the middeſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:107494:32"/> of all <hi>ſtraights</hi> enjoy <hi>a ſufficiency,</hi> and in <hi>that enough</hi> have <hi>as good as a feaſt.</hi> If <hi>enough be too little, too much will not be enough.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION. VIII.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a fit of the Gout.</head>
               <p>LOrd, <hi>when thou with rebukes doeſt correct man for iniquity,</hi> what a moth is he in thine hands? and how eaſily cruſhed? <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaith <hi>he is cruſhed before the moth;</hi> ſo that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his opinion, <hi>the moth, ſhould be the better man of the two.</hi> I am here <hi>a lecture of mortality to my ſelf;</hi> and yet in truth, I can hardly <hi>expound</hi> my ſelf, and ſay what I am, in this condition. I am <hi>an infirmity of the world,</hi> rather then <hi>any part of it;</hi> a <hi>living Hoſpital;</hi> or, to ſpeak more properly, <hi>the Ghoſt of my departed ſelf;</hi> here I <hi>dwelt once,</hi> but <hi>now,</hi> here <hi>I lie,</hi> and am <hi>mine own monument,</hi> with <hi>the figure of a man,</hi> and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:107494:33"/> 
                  <hi>nothing within,</hi> but <hi>a dead mans bones,</hi> and <hi>corruption.</hi> How <hi>near nothing</hi> am I? I have ſo much of <hi>an idol</hi> in me, which is <hi>nothing,</hi> as I have <hi>feet,</hi> and <hi>walk not.</hi> I can neither go, nor ſtand nor hardly ſtir, but as <hi>my pain quickens</hi> me; and yet <hi>I</hi> cannot without a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, <hi>lie ſtill. My pain is my life.</hi> O my Soul, <hi>when the pillars, upon which the houſe ſtandeth, begin to faile, it is high time for thee, to think of remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>May I ſay, <hi>why am I thus?</hi> whether ſhould I go to enquire, O my God, but unto thee? I know thou doeſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but upon <hi>juſt grounds,</hi> and for <hi>good ends.</hi> Thou art <hi>righteous,</hi> but I am <hi>a ſinful creature: I do remember my faults this day:</hi> How I have loved <hi>to wander</hi> in the world: My <hi>ſteps</hi> have turned out of thy way; and mine <hi>heart</hi> hath walked after <hi>mine eyes;</hi> and I have polluted, and ſtained <hi>the garments of my profeſſion.</hi> Tis therefore juſt with thee, to <hi>puniſh me as a fool, and a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant;</hi> to <hi>ſtock,</hi> and <hi>whip</hi> me; to <hi>ſhut
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:107494:33"/> me up,</hi> and to make me ſmart for it, as children are ſhut up, and correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when they have run abroad, and durtied themſelves. <hi>I have ſinned, what ſhall I do unto thee, O thou Preſerver of men? I have borne chaſtiſement, and by thy grace I will offend no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is no leſs then a ſignal mercy, that I am not taken away <hi>at once,</hi> with <hi>a ſuddain ſtroke,</hi> by <hi>a dead palſie,</hi> or <hi>appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexy,</hi> or ſome ſuch ſpeeding diſeaſe; that I am not chaſed out of the world, as a viſion of the night, and hurled out of my place, as with a ſtorme; that I do not <hi>go down in a moment to the grave, in mine unrepented ſins;</hi> but that I have time given me, by this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, to ſit my ſelf for mine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed change. Lord Sanctify this mercy to me, that whilſt I do live, I may indevour to ſpend my <hi>little rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of time</hi> here ſo, as I would <hi>ſpend mine eternity</hi> hereafter, in glorifying thee; and then let death come never ſo ſuddainly, it will come but <hi>like a friend;</hi> the <hi>ſooner, the better wellcome!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:107494:34"/>
               <p>But why ſhould I be ſo much moved with the ſenſe of this weakneſs? <hi>there is no new thing happened unto me,</hi> but what is ordinarily incident to my years. This, and other the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, are in the courſe of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable age, but as <hi>the accidents of duſt, or durt, or raine in a long journey;</hi> which every rational man will expect, and reckon upon before hand. <hi>Lord give me a true ſenſe of the frailty of my condition, and I ſhall no more wonder at mine infirmities, then I wonder at my life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what do I ſpeak of infirmites? I may rather juſtly bleſs God for <hi>the long continued health,</hi> which for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years <hi>I have formerly enjoyed,</hi> then grudge at <hi>my preſent ſuffering.</hi> I have been a young man <hi>a great while,</hi> and therefore it is but reaſon I ſhould be contented to be <hi>an old man a little while:</hi> what? <hi>ſhall I receive good at the hands of God, and ſhall I not receive evil?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But why do I miſcall my Gout? ſhall a heathen Philoſopher <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:107494:34"/> able, upon the ſtrength of a natural reſolution, to proteſt in the middeſt of his pain in this infirmity, that <hi>no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity ſhould ever make him confeſs it to be an evil;</hi> and ſhall not grace have ſo much power upon me, as to make me acknowledge that <hi>it is good for me to be thus chaſtened?</hi> ſhall I fly out into <hi>impatience</hi> when God corrects me <hi>for my profit?</hi> they that will not <hi>lie ſtill</hi> when God whips them, do but gaine <hi>the more ſtripes;</hi> and by their <hi>impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> make it appear that they <hi>were not corrected enough before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay Lord, I bleſs thee, not only for <hi>thy ſtaff</hi> but for <hi>thy rod,</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be one of thy ſmarteſt ones, and by the continuance whereof I am brought thus low, yet I find <hi>the end thereof to be dipt in hony,</hi> tending to mine edification, not to my diſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This very infirmity under which I lie, hath the reputation to be of <hi>a medicinal nature;</hi> as it contracteth <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther malignant humours into one channel,</hi> and ſpendeth them with it ſelf, ſo let
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:107494:35"/> all thy chaſtiſements, O Lord, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate upon me, for the purging of mine iniquity, and the taking away of my ſin, and I ſhall reckon them in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of my bleſſings.</p>
               <p>What though theſe paines be <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent?</hi> they are the <hi>leſs likely to continue;</hi> either they will <hi>end themſelves,</hi> or <hi>end me;</hi> the difference is not much; <hi>either way there will be an end, and that ſhortly.</hi> The life of man is <hi>of few dayes, and full of trouble:</hi> And therefore when I think <hi>how ſhort my time is,</hi> I am contented, becauſe it is <hi>ſo full of trouble,</hi> and when I conſider <hi>how troubleſome it is,</hi> I am comforted with the thought, <hi>that it is ſo ſhort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now Lord, <hi>what waite I for? my hope, my only hope, is in thee.</hi> Shall I ſay, <hi>remove thy ſtroke away from me?</hi> let me alone? far be that from me; deliver me, O my God, from that <hi>penal impunity;</hi> and vouchſafe rather to continue thy gracious <hi>rod upon</hi> me, ſo long as thou ſhalt ſee it <hi>good;</hi> for ſo long I am ſure it ſhall be <hi>for my
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:107494:35"/> good;</hi> and I ſhall look upon it as a dear bleſſed gout to me. Shew thy mercy to me, as thou didſt to thy Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in <hi>puniſhing mine inventions: Chaſten me, ſo thou love me; ſcourge on, ſo thou receive me,</hi> and it ſhall be my conſolation. O give me not only <hi>ſtrength to bear</hi> theſe paines, but <hi>thankfulneſs for them,</hi> and <hi>wiſdome to improve by them;</hi> that I may neither <hi>deſpiſe thy chaſtening,</hi> nor be <hi>weary of thy correction:</hi> So ſhall thy <hi>rod</hi> (like the rod of <hi>Aaron</hi>) be <hi>productive,</hi> and not only <hi>bloſſome,</hi> but <hi>bring forth fruit</hi> unto me, even <hi>the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſs.</hi> Make me ſuch <hi>when I am well, as I would be when I am ſick.</hi> In all conditions, let <hi>thy grace be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for me; perfect thy ſtrength in my weakneſs, and imperfection;</hi> and then I ſhall take <hi>pleaſure in my paines,</hi> and <hi>glory in mine infirmities;</hi> and be able to ſay with that great <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> when <hi>I am weak I am ſtrong, and when I am ſick, I am well.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="meditation">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:107494:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION. IX.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my recovery out of the Gout.</head>
               <p>IS this a <hi>recovery,</hi> or a <hi>reſurrection?</hi> It was but a while ago, that I had <hi>two feet in the grave,</hi> and that I was ready to claime my <hi>laſt kindred with wormes,</hi> and corruption; and in what an Eagle condition am I now? how <hi>renewed,</hi> or rather <hi>reſuſcitated?</hi> me thinkes I am (as if I had <hi>outlived my death) mine own ſurviour,</hi> the <hi>poſterity of my ſelf:</hi> Certainly life doth not conſiſt <hi>in living,</hi> but in <hi>well being;</hi> health is <hi>the life of life,</hi> and without that, we have but <hi>a name that we live, but we are dead.</hi> There is nothing to be preferred before the <hi>health of the body,</hi> but holineſs, which is <hi>the heal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h of the Soul.</hi> O Lord, thou art <hi>the God of life, and death;</hi> thou <hi>killeſt, and thou makeſt alive; thou woundeſt, and thou healeſt; thou, even thou art he, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:107494:36"/> there is no God with thee.</hi> I drew near unto deſtruction, but upon my cry unto thee, it pleaſed thee to ſend thy Soveraine word to heal me, and I was healed. O that I could therefore praiſe thee for thy goodneſs, not only with <hi>my lips,</hi> but with <hi>that life,</hi> which thou haſt ſo often re-given me. <hi>The living, the living, he ſhall praiſe thee, as I do this day,</hi> and as I deſire to do all my remaining dayes.</p>
               <p>But am I ſo perfectly well? I may ask my ſelf <hi>how</hi> I <hi>do,</hi> without offence: and it is not an impertinent inquiry. Bleſſed be God, <hi>my houſe of clay</hi> is in a comfortable meaſure <hi>repaired</hi> and made <hi>tenantable</hi> again for a while. But <hi>how is all within?</hi> how doth the <hi>principal one</hi> (ſo <hi>Job</hi> calleth <hi>the Soul</hi>)? it is <hi>my Soul,</hi> that is <hi>my ſelf;</hi> my body is but <hi>mine old ſute new mended;</hi> the <hi>ſheath of my Soul,</hi> (as it is ſtiled by <hi>Daniel</hi>); the health, and proſperity of that, would ſignify little to me, except (according to the tenor of St. <hi>Johns</hi> wiſh unto <hi>Gains) my Soul alſo proſper; a ſick Soul
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:107494:37"/> in a ſound body,</hi> is <hi>the worſt conſtitution that can be.</hi> It is written in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> touching the reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of <hi>Jeruſalem, that the inhabitants thereof ſhall not ſay, I am ſick, for the people that dwell therein ſhall be forgiven their iniquity.</hi> O Lord, I am ſick till mine iniquity be forgiven. Thou haſt ſhewed mercy to my <hi>worldly part,</hi> to my <hi>lay part;</hi> O heal my <hi>Spiritual part;</hi> which <hi>needs thy mercy moſt,</hi> and will <hi>relliſh it beſt.</hi> Untill that be done, I am <hi>ſick,</hi> though never <hi>ſo well.</hi> But admitting (with all humble thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) my preſent being in perfect health; I have no reaſon to think it will continue long; all things under the Sun are ſubject to viciſſitude, and change; and whilſt that I ſay ſo, I am changed my ſelf. My very health, is but <hi>a brooding of ſickneſs,</hi> and every ſickneſs is <hi>a pang of death.</hi> My whole life is no other then <hi>a gradual dying:</hi> I remember <hi>the firſt time I died,</hi> was when mine <hi>infancy expired in my youth;</hi> the next was, when my <hi>youth ended in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:107494:37"/> middle age;</hi> which was followed by the determination of that, in <hi>mine old age;</hi> and yet I have no leſs then <hi>two deaths more</hi> to look for; the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>mine old age in death</hi> it ſelf; and the <hi>death of death,</hi> in the <hi>death of Chriſt.</hi> Who would covet ſuch <hi>a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful life,</hi> which the <hi>longer it laſteth,</hi> the <hi>oftener it dieth?</hi> nay which in truth is ſo far from <hi>a true laſting,</hi> that it taketh up <hi>no time at all;</hi> there is <hi>a time to be born,</hi> and a time to die, ſaith <hi>the Preacher,</hi> but there is <hi>no time aſſigned to live,</hi> becauſe <hi>our whole life, is but a time of dying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I had <hi>a leaſe of health for tearm</hi> of <hi>life,</hi> I could not but look upon it (at my years) as <hi>near worne out.</hi> When I was at my beſt, I was but <hi>graſs;</hi> now that the <hi>flower of that graſs is faded,</hi> in this <hi>dried, withered condition,</hi> what am I better then <hi>meer hay, and ſtubble?</hi> O my Soul, be not ſecure upon this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, <hi>there is nothing that doth ſooner draw</hi> on ſickneſs, <hi>then a fond preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of health: many had never been
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:107494:38"/> 
                  <hi>ſick ſo ſoon,</hi> if they had not been <hi>well too ſoon.</hi> Health requires a good hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry. But in a ſpecial manner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how it is poſſible for that body to be <hi>well long,</hi> that hath but <hi>a ſhort time to be.</hi> Wouldſt thou <hi>redeem</hi> this time, and ſo <hi>extend</hi> it? labour <hi>to be good.</hi> Vertue is not ſubject to time, but will <hi>out-live death it ſelf.</hi> What is the <hi>health of my body,</hi> but the <hi>ſtrength of my priſon?</hi> who would glory in that? I read of ſome pious men, that have <hi>lamented their recovery out of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as finding themſelves to be worſe when they were better, and beſt when they were ill.</hi> Lord look upon thy poor Priſoner of hope, and in thy good time deliver me well <hi>out of my ſelf;</hi> and in the mean time make me truly thankful for any comfort, or accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation that I enjoy in my preſent condition. <hi>Without thy Sanctifying grace thy mercies are judgements; and this health will be but a killing proſperity to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Health is one of God's Talents,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:107494:38"/> which they, unto whom it is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are to account for; and if they do <hi>not improve it</hi> to his ſervice, they might be ſick <hi>better cheap.</hi> That <hi>health is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilential,</hi> that makes the poſſeſſor thereof <hi>luxurious</hi> and <hi>diſorderly.</hi> O my God, let it be my care to devote <hi>my life,</hi> and particularly <hi>my health</hi> (the <hi>beſt of my life</hi>) unto thee, from whom alone I derive both <hi>health and life.</hi> Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid oblations are but the offerings of <hi>the refuſe.</hi> I confeſs mine are little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than ſuch, at this time of mine age, but my truſt is in the goodneſs of thine eye, that thou wilt not in any wiſe reject thoſe that come unto thee, though at <hi>the eleventh hour.</hi> O my God, and moſt gracious Father, ſanctifie all thy diſpenſations unto me, and then they ſhall co-operate together for my good. <hi>My reins ſhall inſtruct me in the night ſeaſon;</hi> my <hi>Gout</hi> ſhall make me <hi>run unto thee;</hi> and my recovery ſhall inable me to <hi>miniſter unto thee,</hi> as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> wives Mother did, ſo ſoon as her <hi>fever</hi> had left her. Bleſſed be thy
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:107494:39"/> name, that <hi>I have been ill,</hi> and thy name be praiſed that <hi>I am well.</hi> Let me <hi>never live</hi> longer than <hi>I praiſe, and bleſs, and glorifie thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION. X.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my impriſonment.</head>
               <p>WHat is there in an impriſonment, that ſhould make that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo formidable? it is not the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couthneſs</hi> of it (we cannot ſay this is <hi>new</hi>) for it is <hi>common to all:</hi> we are all <hi>Priſoners by Nature, during life;</hi> even before we were born, we ſuffered <hi>a confinement in the womb</hi> that bear us; lying for ſo many months as we lived there, incloſed in the loweſt parts of the earth in a polluted, dark, narrow Rome, where we could not ſo much as be turned, without hazard of our lives, and when we came into the world, we were but <hi>removed</hi> (as by a <hi>writ</hi>) to <hi>another priſon;</hi> or rather we were born
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:107494:39"/> (like Snails) with <hi>our priſons upon our backs.</hi> Our Souls, (which are <hi>the man</hi> in us) being <hi>captivated in our bodies,</hi> and ſo cooped up, that they are diſabled thereby to act or operate, further then, <hi>as through a grate,</hi> according to the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row latitude of our corporeal organs. What is the whole World, but as it were <hi>a common Jail,</hi> wherein we are all impriſoned? and however ſome may have a larger and better acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation therein than others, yet <hi>all are within the rule.</hi> I read of <hi>Nicolo Donato</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> that he was foretold by an Aſtrologer (who had calculated his Nativity) that he ſhould die in a <hi>noble Priſon;</hi> which was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards applied to <hi>the reſtrained, limited honour of that Dukedom,</hi> wherein he ended his dayes: to let the Prediction paſs; I may truely affirm, that the greateſt, and moſt reſplendent fortunes in the world, are no better than <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious captivities,</hi> and <hi>honourable Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> and they that enjoy them may account themſelves in the condition of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:107494:40"/> that Greek Emperour <hi>Michael Balbus,</hi> who <hi>took poſſeſſion of his Chair of State, with a pair of Shackles about his heels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what are the inconveniencies of a Priſon? I deny not but that there may be a <hi>juſt reſentment of the loſs of liberty</hi> He that doth <hi>not feel it, wanteth ſenſe;</hi> but he that <hi>cannot bear it, wanteth reaſon, if not grace;</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ſuffering be, <hi>impatience doth but aggravate it.</hi> When we lie like <hi>wilde Bulls in a net,</hi> fretting and ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt the providence of God, we do but impeſter, and intangle our ſelves the more, and (like thoſe ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh <hi>Thracian Captives, that</hi> 
                  <note place="bottom">Florus l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>brake their teath with biting and gnawing their chaines</hi>) by <hi>our impatience we do both puniſh our own ferity, and thereby, make ſport to our enemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is the <hi>bare confinement,</hi> a matter ſo to be ſtartled at? We may as well think the <hi>fixed Stars</hi> unhappy, becauſe they cannot wander. Things are <hi>beſt kept</hi> when they are <hi>lockt up;</hi> many men
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:107494:40"/> have been preſerved by this meanes from greater dangers, which they might have incurred, if they had been at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; and their impriſonment hath been really <hi>a ſafe cuſtody</hi> unto them. How ever, <hi>it is for Children to cry, when they may not go abroad.</hi> True liberty is to be found <hi>within doores.</hi> What tho my <hi>body</hi> be confined? my <hi>Soul is not.</hi> I may poſſibly be diſabled by this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, from <hi>performing good actions,</hi> but that cannot hinder me from <hi>enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good thoughts; from communing with mine own heart; from having my conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with God in Heaven.</hi> Thoughts are free. Let the impriſonment be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo cloſe, and <hi>ſtraight,</hi> if I be not <hi>ſtraightend in my ſelf, I am at liberty;</hi> it is not the narrowneſs of <hi>the roome,</hi> but of <hi>the mind,</hi> that makes the priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on incommodious; <hi>no man ſuffers by it, but he that is unwilling to ſuffer;</hi> for <hi>he that will do, what he muſt do, is a free man,</hi> becauſe <hi>he does what he will: a free impriſonment,</hi> is better then <hi>a ſervile liberty.</hi> They are <hi>the priſoners in truth,</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:107494:41"/> that are <hi>captivated to their own luſts</hi> and <hi>paſſions,</hi> and <hi>intereſts.</hi> It is <hi>not evil to ſuffer, but to do evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I am hear immured in an <hi>obſcure baſe condition:</hi> What then? <hi>true vertue is a jewel, that can give a luſtre in the dark.</hi> If the <hi>worth of a meer moral man</hi> (as was <hi>Socrates</hi>) could be thought ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to take off the ignominy, and reproach of a priſon, upon the account of his lying there, how much more ſhould <hi>the honour of a Chriſtian</hi> illuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and dignify the baſeſt Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon?</p>
               <p>But I am <hi>ſeparated and cut off</hi> from the ſociety of the world: <hi>The further off the better,</hi> except <hi>the world were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> What is there in the world, but <hi>the luſt of the fleſh,</hi> and <hi>the luſt of the eyes,</hi> and <hi>the pride of life?</hi> and what can there be more proper for remedy of theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, then this confinement? wherein, as to <hi>the firſt,</hi> my <hi>body</hi> is ſufficiently <hi>kept under,</hi> and <hi>brought into ſubjection;</hi> for although I cannot ſay, that I am lodged as our <hi>King Edward the Second</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:107494:41"/> was, in a vault, among dead carcaſſes; yet in a civil way I am buried here, and am but a kind of <hi>a living Corps; a mortification to my ſelf.</hi> As for <hi>mine eyes</hi> they are ſecured from the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any <hi>vain objects,</hi> having little elſe to behold, but <hi>bare old, ruinous walls;</hi> the emblems of mine own <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed condition;</hi> and in this deſolate, forlorn habitation, what exerciſe can there be <hi>for pride,</hi> except it be in a holy way, <hi>to deſpiſe the world? company, and not ſolitude is the Scene of pride.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O my Soul, is it not an happineſs to be freed from theſe ſnares? wilt thou be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted for being ſhut out of a peſt-houſe?</hi> What, though thou beeſt as <hi>a Sparrow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</hi> and that no eye take notice of thee? <hi>It is for players to be out of counten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, when no body ſees them act; a good Conſcience is a thouſand ſpectators.</hi> Nay, be not deceived, thou art <hi>not alone,</hi> when thou art <hi>moſt alone:</hi> God is here, <hi>and he that is higher then the higheſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth thee;</hi> Chriſt ſo <hi>with thee,</hi> that he is <hi>in thee; perſecuted in thee;</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:107494:42"/> in thine affliction;</hi> the Holy Ghoſt is <hi>thy comforter;</hi> the Angels are <hi>thy Guardians,</hi> they keep thee, they Miniſter unto thee; and is not this good company?</p>
               <p>But there is <hi>a diſhonour</hi> that ſticks to this condition; which is uſually fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with contempt, and ſcorn: True, <hi>if the cauſe of committment were diſhonorable;</hi> if I <hi>ſuffered as a male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor:</hi> But when the cauſe is Gods, and that I <hi>ſuffer for doing well,</hi> I am ſo far from being <hi>aſhamed of my chain, that I glory in it, as in a favour from Gods own hand.</hi> What <hi>have I, that I have not received?</hi> my very <hi>ſufferings,</hi> as well as <hi>the grace of believing,</hi> are to be reckoned among <hi>my receipts;</hi> to me <hi>it is given, not only to believe, but to ſuffer.</hi> As to <hi>the contempt of the world, there is nothing more contemptible; no man is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to that, but he that lyes under a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt within himſelf. Retain thine own dignity, O my Soul, and thou art above it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But poſſibly thou maiſt ſhrink at the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:107494:42"/> 
                  <hi>apprehenſion of poverty, and want,</hi> which are uſual concomitants of a captive e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; be not caſt down, nor diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this. <hi>He that hath himſelf, and is in poſſeſſion of his own Soul, hath loſt nothing. I am yet richer then I was when I came into the world.</hi> Bleſſed be God, I have yet all that <hi>Jacob</hi> could wiſh; <hi>bread to eat, and rayment to put on; whilſt many better then I have not ſo much. Whatſoever is more then that, is more then needs. Job</hi> gave God <hi>thanks, when he had nothing before him; Paul,</hi> when <hi>he had nothing, had all.</hi> I can claim nothing from God, as <hi>due</hi> unto me, but <hi>the wages</hi> of <hi>my ſins;</hi> and that is <hi>ſomething worſe then nothing.</hi> Be thankful, O my Soul, <hi>for what thou haſt;</hi> be humbled <hi>for what thou haſt not:</hi> in all conditions labour to <hi>be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent;</hi> and in <hi>that contentment,</hi> with Gods bleſſing, <hi>thou wilt find all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is <hi>the continuance of an impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment,</hi> that may ſeem tedious, and be grievous: Certainly <hi>that cannot be long;</hi> for <hi>the life of man, is but of ſhort
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:107494:43"/> continuance:</hi> It can be but like <hi>an ill lodging in an Inn,</hi> and we ſhould bear it accordingly; what tho <hi>the night be long;</hi> it is <hi>but a night,</hi> and we ſhall be <hi>gone in the morning.</hi> Remember, O my Soul, that <hi>a long impriſonment</hi> is not ſo bad, as <hi>an everlaſting one.</hi> Bleſs God that thou art <hi>not laid in chaines of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> with the Devil, and his Angells, <hi>reſerved unto the judgment of the laſt dreadful day.</hi> Be not <hi>weary of well ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,</hi> no more then of <hi>well doing:</hi> think of <hi>the glorious Army of Martyrs;</hi> How did many of them languiſh with a deſire to be in thy condition, and <hi>reckoned themſelves in priſon,</hi> till they were <hi>in priſon?</hi> thou <hi>haſt not yet reſiſted unto blood,</hi> as they did; thou art in the hands of thine <hi>heavenly</hi> Phyſitian, who beſt <hi>knowes thine infirmity,</hi> and thy <hi>conſtitution,</hi> and <hi>complexion,</hi> and what is <hi>fitteſt for thee,</hi> beyond <hi>all that thou canſt think;</hi> what if he, ſeeing that <hi>ſharp, and quick remedies</hi> be not ſo <hi>proper</hi> for thee, and that thou canſt <hi>not bear</hi> them, do put thee in this <hi>ſlow
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:107494:43"/> courſe of Phyſick;</hi> to ſpend thy diſeaſe by <hi>a ſtrict, reſtrained diet?</hi> wilt thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to diſpute his preſcription? do not, but obey, and follow it.</p>
               <p>But what if this impriſonment ſhould be but <hi>praecurſory to a further, a greater,</hi> and it may be <hi>a capital puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> I may conſider in what hands I am; that I am under the power of <hi>a frantick People,</hi> that have caſt off their obedience to <hi>all lawful authority,</hi> and know not how to <hi>weigh out Juſtice</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any, without putting <hi>their ſword in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſcales:</hi> O my Soul thou mayeſt do wiſely to look <hi>beforehand</hi> thorough thy danger, to <hi>the uttermoſt end thereof;</hi> and to arm thy ſelf againſt the worſt that may be; but in taking this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective, make uſe of <hi>thy reaſon,</hi> not of thy <hi>paſſion:</hi> a <hi>provident care,</hi> and a <hi>ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous deſpondency</hi> are <hi>two things.</hi> Do not puniſh thy ſelf with may be's. Do not antidate afflictions, and make thy ſelf miſerable at preſent, by an appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion that thou mayeſt come to be miſerable hereafter. He that in a <hi>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:107494:44"/> ſolicitous way</hi> takes <hi>thought</hi> for to morrow, <hi>labours under</hi> that <hi>ſuffering</hi> to day, which he <hi>apprehendeth</hi> for to morrow; and cannot but fear <hi>more then he ſhould,</hi> becauſe he fears ſooner <hi>then he ſhould;</hi> He doth in a ſort put the lye upon our <hi>bleſſed Saviour,</hi> as if <hi>the evil of the day were not ſufficient unto it.</hi> Theſe querulous fancies argue an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixedneſs of heart, <hi>as the creaking of a board ſheweth it to be looſe, and not well faſtened.</hi> The Moraliſts can tell us in this caſe, that <hi>there is nothing more eaſily deceived, then humane foreſight:</hi> That in ſuch future contingencies (as it is obſerved in acute diſeaſes) our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions are very uncertain; that there is a <hi>levity in evil,</hi> as well as <hi>in good fortune;</hi> both <hi>alike ſubject</hi> to <hi>viciſſitudes,</hi> and <hi>changes,</hi> and <hi>neither of them long laſting;</hi> that we many times apprehend things <hi>to come,</hi> that <hi>do not come,</hi> and that our expectations do <hi>as often fail us in our fears,</hi> as in <hi>our hopes;</hi> that in dangers imminent, our <hi>fear of them,</hi> may exceed <hi>the dangers we fear;</hi> death
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:107494:44"/> it ſelf may be overfeared, ſo that by <hi>running from it,</hi> we may <hi>run into it. (Nabal</hi> died, <hi>for fear of dying</hi>); that thoſe hazards that threaten us moſt, may break up of themſelves, as we ſee <hi>the clouds that gather, and look black up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, do often blow over without a ſhower;</hi> that <hi>great appearances</hi> of evil are ſome times averted by <hi>petty accidents,</hi> as ſome ſay, <hi>that lightening may be put by with the wind of a mans hat;</hi> and that it is good therefore to <hi>intermix hope with fear,</hi> and <hi>fear with hope,</hi> ſo to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and ballance one affection with another. But theſe Philoſophers are like <hi>Meteors,</hi> ſomething <hi>above earth,</hi> and a great deal <hi>below Heaven:</hi> O my Soul, <hi>have faith in God,</hi> and let <hi>thine heart be fixed on him,</hi> and thou <hi>ſhalt not be afraid of evil tidings;</hi> thou <hi>ſhalt never be mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Take no thought for the morrow,</hi> as to the evil thereof, <hi>for the morrow ſhall take thought for the things of it ſelf.</hi> Thou art a poor captive exile, yet do not make haſt thorough unbeleif to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; <hi>who art thou that feareſt the fury
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:107494:45"/> of the Oppreſſor, as if he were ready to deſtroy,</hi> who ſhall <hi>himſelf be deſtroyed and made as graſs?</hi> and <hi>where is the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Oppreſſor?</hi> O my God, <hi>my time is in thine hand,</hi> and what can <hi>man do</hi> unto me? nay what can <hi>the Devil</hi> do? He may, by a <hi>divine permiſſion, for a ſeaſon</hi> (if need be) caſt me into priſon; but it ſhall be only <hi>to try</hi> and <hi>purifie,</hi> and <hi>whiten me.</hi> It is not in his power to do me ſo <hi>much hurt,</hi> but for <hi>my greater good.</hi> He cannot take <hi>my liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and my life</hi> both from me; but in <hi>taking the one,</hi> he muſt <hi>give me the other;</hi> he cannot <hi>take my life,</hi> but withal he muſt <hi>reſtore me my liberty;</hi> and that in ſuch a way as he can never take it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from me more. The <hi>worſt</hi> that he can do, is but that which is <hi>beſt of all;</hi> and therefore <hi>at what time I am afraid, I will truſt in God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord ſanctifie this diſpenſation to me (this rod of thine own appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) and <hi>teach me to underſtand the language of it.</hi> I confeſs I have abuſed my <hi>former liberty</hi> to a <hi>licentiouſneſs,</hi> and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:107494:45"/> therefore this reſtraint is but <hi>a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> unto me, and the <hi>proper wages of my ſin.</hi> O my God, <hi>unto thee belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth mercy, for thou haſt rendred to me according to my work. It is of thy never failing compaſſion, that I am not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Thou art merciful in thy juſtice, and juſt in thy mercy.</hi> O take what vengeance thou wilt of <hi>mine inventions,</hi> ſo thou <hi>forgive my ſin;</hi> lay what bands ſoever it ſhall pleaſe thee upon <hi>my body,</hi> ſo thou free <hi>my ſoul,</hi> and <hi>inlarge my heart to run the way of thy Commandments.</hi> Give me not only a <hi>patient,</hi> but a thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſenſe of any ſufferings, which I <hi>may,</hi> or <hi>do</hi> undergo, for the advancement of thy glory; and let me never think <hi>my penny too little,</hi> which I receive from thee, if it be accompanied with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>bearing the heat of the day in thy ſervice;</hi> but give me the grace to look upon that <hi>honour,</hi> as the <hi>beſt part</hi> of my <hi>pay;</hi> and until the time, that <hi>thy Word</hi> do come for <hi>my deliverance,</hi> let <hi>thy Word</hi> try me, ſo ſhall I at laſt come out gold; in the mean while, in the <hi>worſt</hi> of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:107494:46"/> I ſhall be thy <hi>free-man,</hi> which is <hi>the beſt and moſt noble of all conditions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. XI.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my Releaſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen the Lord turned again my captivity I was like them that dream.</hi> Me thought I had been made a Priſoner for divers years, by a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuary violence; and in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition toſſed, like a ball, from one place to another; remote from my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; where I was as <hi>unknown,</hi> yet <hi>well known;</hi> as <hi>dying,</hi> and yet <hi>living; perſecuted,</hi> but <hi>not forſaken; caſt down,</hi> but <hi>not deſtroyed;</hi> and me thoughts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſudden, all theſe <hi>as it were</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings vaniſhed, and I was reſtored to <hi>my liberty,</hi> to <hi>my family,</hi> and <hi>friends</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. At the firſt, like <hi>Peter,</hi> I was in a manner intraunced, as if I had ſeen a <hi>Viſion,</hi> and I could hardly beleive mine eyes; but recollecting my ſelf,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:107494:46"/> I found ſufficient reaſon to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as that great Apoſtle did, that <hi>the Lord had ſent his Angel, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me out of the hand of mine enemies, and from all the expectation of thoſe that hated me.</hi> What ſhall I do, or what ſhall I ſay unto thee, <hi>O thou preſerver of men?</hi> thou art <hi>exalted above all thanksgiving and praiſe.</hi> Lord, open <hi>my lips,</hi> and I ſhall be inabled at once, both <hi>to praiſe thee for this mercy,</hi> and to praiſe thee <hi>for opening my lips, and inabling me to praiſe thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How ſweet is liberty after a reſtraint?</hi> certainly a <hi>proſperous condition</hi> is never ſo well reliſh'd as after an <hi>affliction;</hi> as <hi>wine</hi> is then beſt taſted, when we have firſt taſted a <hi>bitter Olive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as <hi>hony is good,</hi> and yet in the <hi>exceſs</hi> thereof <hi>nauſeous:</hi> So liberty (how <hi>ſweet ſoever in it ſelf</hi>) may (if taken beyond the meaſure of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency) draw on <hi>a furfet of licentiouſneſs.</hi> It is <hi>in that,</hi> as Phyſicians ſay it is <hi>in health; a high degree thereof may be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</hi> O my Soul, labour to <hi>mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:107494:47"/> thine affections</hi> in all conditions; and now that God hath been pleaſed to <hi>fill thy cup</hi> again, pray for <hi>a ſteddy hand,</hi> that thou maiſt <hi>carry it without ſpilling:</hi> Otherwiſe, this ſuddain change, from <hi>ſuch a confinement,</hi> to ſuch <hi>an inlagement,</hi> will be but like <hi>a ſuddain good ſigne immediatly after a bad one,</hi> which (according to the old rule of divination by the intrails of beaſts) was accounted to be <hi>of unlucky Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> it may be a prognoſtick, that <hi>a worſe thing will happen unto thee.</hi> In <hi>all time, not only of my tribulation, but of my weal, and proſperity, good Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it may be <hi>a moot point,</hi> whether I am much <hi>ſafer</hi> now, then I was before. My former reſtraint was in the nature of <hi>a ſafegard,</hi> or of <hi>a harbour</hi> to me, where though I were in a manner <hi>land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lockt,</hi> yet I lay ſecure, and <hi>out of the wind:</hi> now that I am abroad, I may ſay I have <hi>more Sea roome,</hi> but withall I am more <hi>expoſed to foul weather,</hi> then I was before. There is no condition
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:107494:47"/> under the Sun, <hi>ſo purely, and ſimply good,</hi> but that it hath <hi>an allay of evil in it,</hi> and that to ſuch a proportion, that (as it is in baſe mony) <hi>the allay</hi> is, for the moſt part, more then <hi>the true mettal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But is liberty then ſo indifferent a thing, that there ſhould be but <hi>a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring caſt</hi> between it and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? there muſt needs be a wider difference between them, then ſo; for it is ſaid, that <hi>God doth not willingly greive the Children of men, to cruſh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feat the Priſoners of the earth,</hi> but that <hi>he hath pleaſure in the proſperity of his Servants;</hi> and therefore <hi>in their liberty,</hi> without which there can be but <hi>little taſte in proſperity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The greateſt bleſſings that come from the hand of God, are characteriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this bleſſing: <hi>The Goſpel</hi> is ſtiled <hi>a Proclamation of liberty to the captives,</hi> and <hi>an opening of the priſon to them that are bound;</hi> the Spirit of God is termed <hi>a free Spirit,</hi> and <hi>where that is, there is ſaid to be liberty;</hi> we are <hi>called unto li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:107494:48"/> and commanded <hi>to ſtand faſt in it;</hi> we ſhall be <hi>judged by the law of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty;</hi> this as to <hi>our Spiritual condition.</hi> And as to our <hi>outward freedom,</hi> it may be a ſufficient argument of the value that God ſets upon it, that he laid a particular command upon his people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they ſhould <hi>be tender of one anothers liberty;</hi> and to that end, bound them to the obſervation of <hi>the ſeventh,</hi> and <hi>fiftieth years,</hi> for <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe,</hi> and <hi>manumiſſion of thoſe that were held under ſervice;</hi> and that he pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed thoſe violators thereof in the Siege of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with ſo much ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity; <hi>by proclaiming a liberty to the Sword, Peſtilence, and Famine againſt them</hi> for it: Liberty is in it ſelf an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable bleſſing, and <hi>ſuch a jewel</hi> as every man may ſet <hi>his own price upon it,</hi> and it is worth it to him; if we cannot enjoy it as we would, or know not how to bear and uſe it, as we ſhould; it is either our own unhappineſs, or our fault: <hi>The old bottles are to be blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not the new wine.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:107494:48"/>
               <p>But <hi>what is liberty?</hi> there may be a miſtake in that, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaketh of ſome in his days, that <hi>talked much of liberty and promiſed it to others, whilſt they themſelves were the Servants of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;</hi> there may be <hi>a ſervility,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>an oſtentation of liberty.</hi> They that are captivated to their own inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affections are no better then Slaves, let their quality be otherwiſe what it will. <hi>True liberty</hi> doth not conſiſt <hi>in a power over others,</hi> but in a <hi>command over our ſelves.</hi> He is not a freeman that <hi>can do what he will,</hi> but he that <hi>will do what he ſhould;</hi> and who is <hi>a law unto himſelf,</hi> and <hi>can rule his own Spirit:</hi> Neither can that be called properly a liberty, which is <hi>an obſtinate oppoſition of lawful authority;</hi> ſuch an inflexibility, as will bow to nothing: We do not ſay that <hi>Lions and Wolves</hi> are <hi>at liberty</hi> in their woods, but that <hi>they run wild</hi> there; and ſo for thoſe <hi>deſpiſers of Dominion</hi> that will run their own irregular wayes, and think (as God ſpake
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:107494:49"/> ironically of the <hi>Babel builders)</hi> that <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will be reſtrained from them, which they have imagined to do,</hi> they may be ſaid to be rather <hi>Savage, and brutiſh,</hi> then <hi>free.</hi> The beſt is, they are, both the one, and the other, alike in this, as well as in their ferity, that as they have not the <hi>will to obey,</hi> ſo they have not the <hi>wit to command,</hi> and therefore break, and divide among themſelvs, and ſettle nothing. God who hath determined <hi>the bounds of our habitations,</hi> hath likewiſe ſet <hi>bounds unto our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> beyond the which they that are <hi>proudeſt,</hi> and <hi>ſwell themſelves higheſt, are not to paſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have read of King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſtored to his liberty by <hi>Claudius,</hi> after a long impriſonment under <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius,</hi> he <hi>conſecrated his chain to God in the Temple at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>in memory of his former ſuffering and in recognition of Gods mercy to him in his deliverance:</hi> The example is good, and carries a good light with it. <hi>And now</hi> Lord <hi>what ſhall I render unto thee for the like
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:107494:49"/> mercy in this inlargement of my conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> Shall I offer up my chain <hi>unto thee?</hi> Lord, <hi>accept my whole ſelf, body, ſoul, ſubſiſtence, the ſervice of my all, as an entire oblation and thank-offering devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thy Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O my Soul, <hi>praiſe thou the Lord, and all that is within me, bleſs his holy name, who hath</hi> heard thy groaning, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed thee from deſtruction, and <hi>brought forth thy righteouſneſs as the light, and thy judgment as the noon day. Rejoyce in this day of thy proſperity,</hi> but withal <hi>conſider,</hi> that there is <hi>no day ſo clear,</hi> but may be <hi>overcaſt before night;</hi> the clouds may return again after the rain. Be not ſecure, but <hi>walk circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly,</hi> leaſt if thou uſe this <hi>liberty</hi> for an <hi>occaſion</hi> to <hi>carnal ends,</hi> and for a <hi>cloak of maliciouſneſs,</hi> thy <hi>laſt</hi> ſtate prove worſe than thy <hi>firſt.</hi> Thy <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> is now at liberty; let not thy <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> be ſo too, but keep them under reſtraint, ſo ſhalt thou lead <hi>thy captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty captive.</hi> Lord, vouchſafe to inlarge my heart, not that I may <hi>walk in the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:107494:50"/> counſel of the ungodly,</hi> but that I may purſue <hi>the way of thy commandments.</hi> O lead me <hi>into thy truth; thy word is truth, thy ſon is thy word;</hi> and if <hi>thy Son do make me free, I ſhall be free in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION. XII.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſight of a fair Houſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHat a goodly Fabrick is here?</hi> Our firſt Parents were never ſo houſed. For ought that doth appear, <hi>they</hi> took no more care at firſt for build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than the <hi>Birds</hi> or <hi>Beaſts</hi> did: there were then no <hi>Royal Pallaces,</hi> for the <hi>ambitious Spider</hi> to weave in; but Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was the <hi>common Architect,</hi> as well as <hi>Cook</hi> and <hi>Caterer.</hi> A <hi>ſhadie Tree,</hi> or the covert of a <hi>Grotto,</hi> or <hi>Cave,</hi> ſerved for all Lodgers: Man was never ſo <hi>happy,</hi> nor ſo well provided for, as in that condition, which we eſteem <hi>moſt miſerable,</hi> when he had neither <hi>cloaths
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:107494:50"/> to put on,</hi> nor <hi>houſe to put his head in.</hi> If we look to the <hi>ſecond edition of the World,</hi> after the Floud, and to the generation of the Faithful therein (to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> thoſe <hi>heirs of Promiſe)</hi> they dwel <hi>in Tents,</hi> and, like the Sun, were carried about in their <hi>movable Tabernacles;</hi> ever in a <hi>tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> but <hi>heavenly eſtate.</hi> But what do I ſpeak of Man, or of the Son of Man, that is a Worm? Our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> himſelf, who was Lord of <hi>Heaven and Earth,</hi> by whom <hi>all things</hi> were made, that were made, when he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Man, and dwelt on the Earth, was not ſo well accommodated as the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Creatures, <hi>the Foxes, and the Birds of the air;</hi> they had <hi>their holes,</hi> and they had <hi>their neſts,</hi> but he had <hi>not where to lay his ſacred head:</hi> His <hi>firſt</hi> lodging was <hi>in another mans houſe,</hi> and his <hi>laſt</hi> in <hi>another mans Grave:</hi> in the mean time <hi>the mighty Man,</hi> he had <hi>the Earth,</hi> and <hi>the honourable Man dwelt in it;</hi> the Earth was his Houſe, he was the <hi>only Dweller;</hi> when the <hi>Goodman</hi> was but
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:107494:51"/> a <hi>Sojourner;</hi> and the <hi>God-man</hi> (if I may ſpeak it with all humble reverence) our bleſſed Saviour was little more than a <hi>beggar</hi> in it; who then would put any extraordinary value upon theſe worldly contentments, ſeeing how they are diſpenſed? they are but <hi>the crums that fall under the Table,</hi> of which the <hi>dogs</hi> have the greateſt ſhare. It is ſaid, that that great Apoſtle <hi>knew not what he ſaid,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>it was good being here;</hi> our true happineſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in our <hi>not being here.</hi> O my Soul, let the Men of the World pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>with their portion in this life,</hi> and joyn houſe to houſe, and lay field to field, till there be no place for a neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood about them; but do thou rejoyce, that this is <hi>not thy continuing place;</hi> thou knoweſt where to be <hi>far better</hi> then here; even in that <hi>heavenly Manſion prepared for thee, whoſe builder and maker is God. Never look to be in a ſettled condition, till thou comeſt thither!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How are our vanities heightened? and a what vaſt exceſs are we grown
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:107494:51"/> from that primitive ſimplicity? when inſtead of contenting our ſelves with what nature affordeth, in order to our preſervation from the injuries of the air, and weather; we exhauſt, and weare out <hi>the materials of nature,</hi> and <hi>rack the inventions of art,</hi> to pleaſe <hi>the luſt of our eyes,</hi> which may quickly have <hi>too much,</hi> but can never <hi>have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough</hi> to ſatisfy their ſeeing. We build <hi>Houſes like Townes,</hi> and <hi>Townes like Countries</hi> (for their capacity, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent) when God knowes <hi>contentment may be lodged in a little roome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what was the reaſon of that plainneſs, and homelineſs of thoſe good people of old? was it becauſe they were ignorant, and poor, and had not the wit, nor ability to be <hi>ſuch magnificent fools,</hi> as we are? certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no, thoſe holy Patriarks were not ſo plainly bred, but that they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Kings, and Courts well enough; ſometimes ſcorning to be beholding to them, and at other times being courted by them. They were not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digent
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:107494:52"/> perſons, but according to the way of thoſe times, rich in Flocks, and and Herds; they had great families, and wanted not for Gold, and Silver, nor for any other accommodation: but the truth is, <hi>they looked for a heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly country,</hi> and for <hi>a habitation of Gods making;</hi> looking upon no houſe as worth the conſideration, but that <hi>which is not made with hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet there is no hurt in theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments; they are things, not in themſelves <hi>ſimply evil;</hi> for then the righteous would have no portion at all of them; <hi>Abraham</hi> would have been as poor as <hi>Lazarus;</hi> neither are they <hi>poſitively good;</hi> for then the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed would not have <hi>ſo large a ſhare in them; Dives</hi> would not have <hi>fared ſo deliciouſly every day;</hi> but they are <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferencies,</hi> either <hi>good or bad,</hi> according as they are <hi>well, or ill uſed.</hi> It is free for any man to take comfort in a good houſe, and to delight himſelf (as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> did) in <hi>his workes, and buildings, and plantations;</hi> but then it muſt be
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:107494:52"/> upon <hi>Solomons</hi> tearms too, ſo as his <hi>Wiſdom alſo do remain with him.</hi> The fault is not in the <hi>having,</hi> but in the <hi>abuſing</hi> of theſe things, by <hi>truſting in them,</hi> and <hi>bottoming our ſelves</hi> upon them. Let our houſes be never ſo ſtrongly, and maſſily built, if (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Bildads</hi> expreſſion) <hi>we lean upon them,</hi> they ſhall <hi>not ſtand,</hi> but we ſhall (like <hi>Samſon</hi>) bring them <hi>down about our own ears,</hi> and our <hi>truſt ſhall be a Spiders web. Nebuchadnazzar</hi> might have enjoyed his great <hi>Babilon,</hi> the <hi>houſe of his Kingdom,</hi> long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, if he had not prided himſelf in it, but when he came to boaſt of <hi>the might of his Power,</hi> and of <hi>the Honour of his Majeſty,</hi> it was juſt with God <hi>to Seal an ejectment</hi> againſt him, and to turn his <hi>Majeſty</hi> to graſs, to have his <hi>dwelling,</hi> and <hi>intercommoning with the beaſts of the field.</hi> The only way to <hi>uſe the world,</hi> as we <hi>ſhould uſe it,</hi> is ſo to <hi>uſe it,</hi> as if we <hi>did not uſe it.</hi> It was a curſe among ſome people, <hi>to wiſh that a man might affect building;</hi> and it is
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:107494:53"/> no better then a malediction to thoſe, who ſo doat upon it, that (as <hi>Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> told the young man that was fond of his new houſe) <hi>they ſeem not ſo much to</hi> poſſeſs their houſes, <hi>as their</hi> houſes <hi>ſeem to</hi> poſſeſs <hi>them;</hi> and who are ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with this vanity, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow more time upon it, then they can afford to the ſervice of God. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſeems to ly under ſome note for this, in that he was <hi>Seven years in building the houſe of the Lord,</hi> but <hi>he was thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years</hi> in building <hi>his own houſe: but</hi> that is not without reflection. <hi>God doth not take well from his people, when they are more careful to accommodate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their</hi> cieled houſes, <hi>then</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair his houſe.</p>
               <p>This is a fair building, but who is within? <hi>the Maſter</hi> ſhould dignifie <hi>the houſe,</hi> and not <hi>the houſe the Maſter.</hi> It is pitty that any ſuch places ſhould be <hi>Owles neſts.</hi> If there be no body of worth within, to give it reputation, the <hi>Maſons and Carpenters</hi> that built the Houſe, may challenge more Honor
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:107494:53"/> then the <hi>Maſter of the houſe.</hi> It is not the <hi>beautiful front,</hi> nor the <hi>rich furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> but the <hi>noble heart,</hi> and the <hi>rich mind</hi> of the owner, that recommends the houſe. What a miſerable thing is it to conſider, that for the moſt part, in this corrupt age wherein we live, <hi>great houſes</hi> are in effect, but mear <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators of debauchery, and viciouſneſs.</hi> The <hi>Devil keeps the houſe,</hi> and he that is called <hi>the Maſter</hi> is but <hi>the Signe of the Tavern, or the Owle in the Ivy buſh.</hi> It was the honour of <hi>Abraham</hi> that he kept <hi>a religious family,</hi> and <hi>command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and taught his houſhold to keep the way of the Lord;</hi> but that is <hi>fanaticiſm</hi> now. Our great ones can tell how <hi>to live without God in the world,</hi> allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves ſuch <hi>a latitude</hi> in their way, as if the way of God were <hi>too narrow</hi> for their quality to walke in. They are ſo far from <hi>improving thoſe that are about them</hi> in the knowledge and practice of religion, that, like people that have the plague, they <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to infect others</hi> with their vices,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:107494:54"/> and to make them as ill as themſelves, as if it were <hi>a point of honour to go to hell with a great traine.</hi> They have a ſtrange perverſneſs in them; they covet to have <hi>good houſes, good ſtuff, good fare,</hi> and to have <hi>every thing good,</hi> to their very <hi>horſes and dogs,</hi> but <hi>themſelves,</hi> and <hi>their Houſhold.</hi> Juſtly may thoſe houſes <hi>Spue out their Maſters, and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> that live only <hi>to drink, and ſpue</hi> in them. <hi>This is a ſore evil, which I have ſeen under the Sun,</hi> namely <hi>riches, and theſe outward conveniences, kept for the poſſeſſors thereof to their hurt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have read a <hi>Rabbinical</hi> ſtory of <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> that being warned by God <hi>to build a houſe for himſelf, for that he had yet five hundred years to live;</hi> he anſwered, that <hi>for ſo ſhort a time it was not worth the labour.</hi> Let the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor be anſwerable for the credit of the ſtory: All the uſe that I ſhall make of it, is but to obſerve the folly of theſe times, wherein <hi>we that cannot calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late our lives by hundreds of years,</hi> but by the <hi>day,</hi> by the <hi>Span,</hi> by the <hi>inch,</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:107494:54"/> are yet as ſollicitous, as if we were to live to <hi>the laſt day of the world.</hi> We go (according to that expreſſion in <hi>Syracedes) two wayes at once;</hi> we <hi>build, as if we were to live for ever;</hi> and <hi>we eat, and drink, as if we were to dye to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi> The vain, as well as wicked <hi>Nero,</hi> when he had built his Pallace to to that vaſtneſs, that the Epigrammatiſt made it a queſtion, <hi>whether the houſe ſtood in the City of</hi> Rome, <hi>or the City of</hi> Rome <hi>in the houſe;</hi> he called it <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory;</hi> and that not inſignificantly (whatſoever he intended by it); for there is <hi>a tranſitorineſs,</hi> and (as I may ſay) <hi>a mortality in buildings,</hi> as well as in <hi>perſons. Man dyes; and where is he? his place ſhall know him no more.</hi> The <hi>houſe decayes, and falls;</hi> and <hi>where is that?</hi> within a few years, no body ſhall know <hi>the place of that any more; the memorial of both is periſhed with them:</hi> And yet ſuch is the ſottiſh ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity of people, that though they ſee, and cannot but know theſe things, yet they figure to themſelves <hi>imaginary
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:107494:55"/> perpetuties,</hi> and adopt <hi>their houſes in their own names,</hi> and pleaſe themſelves with the inward thought that <hi>their dwelling places ſhall continue for ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all generations: this their way, is their folly, yet their poſterity approve their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O my Soul, <hi>never look to be well ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this low moriſh vale of tears.</hi> Whatever is built here, muſt <hi>needs ſink,</hi> for want of <hi>a ſolid foundation,</hi> which this looſe rotten ground will not admit. There is no foundation ſtandeth ſure, but that which is of God. <hi>Except he build the houſe,</hi> and <hi>the houſe be built upon him</hi> (upon his bleſſing) it will never be <hi>weather proof.</hi> Take example there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from that <hi>feeble folk,</hi> that make <hi>their houſes in the rock,</hi> build upon <hi>that rock,</hi> which is <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and with that good, and noble <hi>Eleazar,</hi> take up <hi>thy habitation in his wounds;</hi> embrace that rock, and thou ſhalt never want a ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; no not in that day, when <hi>the dens, and rocks of the mountaines</hi> ſhall not afford that curteſy to the greateſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:107494:55"/> upon earth: and when thine <hi>earthly houſe of this tabernacle ſhall be diſſolved, thou ſhalt have a building of God, and be clothed upon with thy houſe, which is from Heaven, and ſhall ſtand for ever!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. XIII.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſight of Pictures in a Gallery.</head>
               <p>HOw many <hi>artificial miracles</hi> are there in this roome? how are mine eyes at once <hi>pleaſed,</hi> and <hi>diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> I may truly ſay, <hi>the eye is not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with ſeeing.</hi> How many wayes at once, have I to look? here, without taking the pains to go abroad I can go abroad within doores, and in a ſmall table ſee, a whole Contry, diverſified with Hills, and Dales, with Boſcage, Campagnes, Cities, Rivers, Sea's, all ſo perfectly repreſented, that a Poet would make a queſtion upon it, <hi>whether it were a natural work of art, or
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:107494:56"/> an artificial work of nature.</hi> In another place, I can behold a beauty drawn with that ſweetneſs, and ingenuity of aſpect, that it might paſs for a picture <hi>of a mind,</hi> as well as <hi>of a face.</hi> There, is <hi>a peace of devotion,</hi> ſet forth ſo <hi>mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly</hi> that it would <hi>move devotion</hi> to ſee it; and near unto that, a picture <hi>of a dead friend,</hi> ſo exactly reſembling him, and with that vivacity, that if <hi>the eyes were to be the only judges,</hi> one would think it <hi>lived,</hi> and <hi>ſpake,</hi> and were <hi>the party,</hi> and not <hi>the picture.</hi> To fill up the meaſure of mine admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, all this variety is expreſſed by the help of <hi>a few colours,</hi> blended toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and laid on with a pencil, made up of a few hoggs haires; ſuch mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, and utenſils, as an ignorant ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by, would judge only fit, to <hi>foule ones fingers,</hi> and <hi>ſpoil ones clothes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O my God, whilſt I feed mine eyes upon <hi>theſe workes of mens hands,</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but glorify and adore <hi>thine excellent working,</hi> who haſt <hi>created all things, and who doſt worke all our workes in us.</hi> Let
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:107494:56"/> others admire the men that made <hi>theſe pictures,</hi> I admire the God that made <hi>theſe men;</hi> I admire that picture (as I may ſo call it) which was of <hi>Gods own making;</hi> the <hi>impreſſion of his image in man.</hi> There is no peace in the world comparable to that.</p>
               <p>Pleaſant pictures (ſuch as are meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for recreation, and diverſion) may ſeem to be inoffenſive; and yet in a bedrol of ſins enumerated by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> I find them mentioned, with a particular denunciation againſt them. There is nothing ſo innocent in the world, but by <hi>a too much affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> may be abuſed, and turned into ſin: I would therefore make uſe of <hi>the pleaſures of this world,</hi> as I would do of <hi>the pictures in this gallery;</hi> walk by them, and look upon them with <hi>a tranſient eye,</hi> but not <hi>ſtop my way,</hi> nor <hi>ſpend my time</hi> upon them.</p>
               <p>What is this ſublunary world, but (as it were) <hi>a painters ſhop,</hi> wherein we ſee nothing but <hi>appearances, and fancies,</hi> and not any thing of <hi>reallity?</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:107494:57"/> All the glory of it, is but <hi>a painted bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> it <hi>ſwells,</hi> and <hi>lookes bigg,</hi> and <hi>Caſts fine colours,</hi> and then <hi>breaks,</hi> and <hi>vapours into nothing; The friendſhip of the world,</hi> which (if any thing) ſhould be <hi>real,</hi> is (for the moſt part) but <hi>ſo much picture, and complement,</hi> but daubing; <hi>Plato</hi> calls it by a right name, <hi>Rhetorical friendſhip;</hi> and Rhetor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick is no other then a kind of <hi>painted language.</hi> What are <hi>the beauties of the world,</hi> which vaine men ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, and are ſo inveigled with, but (at the beſt) in their native favour <hi>deceitful, and vaine?</hi> and thus far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling pictures, as all their comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs conſiſteth <hi>in the due proportion of lineaments,</hi> and in the <hi>clearneſs</hi> and <hi>freſhneſs of colours,</hi> which are the very elements of painting: As for others, many of them may paſs for no other then <hi>living pictures;</hi> ſo painted, and patcht, that being compared with their pictures, which are made for them, it might be a queſtion, which were <hi>the principals,</hi> and which <hi>the copies;</hi> for
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:107494:57"/> both are <hi>painted like;</hi> only of the two, their own faces may be ſaid to be the worſt, becauſe they <hi>are not like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> I could wiſh that we had not too many <hi>Chriſtians in Picture;</hi> ſuch <hi>hypocrites,</hi> as think it <hi>religion enough, to ſeem religious.</hi> Theſe are <hi>double fac'd pictures;</hi> one way ſo putting to ſhew the <hi>beauty of holineſs</hi> in their <hi>profeſſion,</hi> as if (according to the language of the <hi>Lycaonians) Gods were come down in the likeneſs of men;</hi> another way ſo repreſenting the <hi>uglineſs of ſin,</hi> in their practice, as if <hi>men were come up in the likeneſs of Devils.</hi> I confeſs, that of late, the number of <hi>theſe kind of peeces</hi> (thorough an inundation of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery, and profaneſs among us) is <hi>ſo much abated,</hi> that a man (with the ſafety of his charity) might wiſh, <hi>there were more hypocrites ſtirring again;</hi> for tho thoſe <hi>painted Sepulchres,</hi> might by their ſpecious appearance <hi>deceive ſome;</hi> theſe open Sepulchres do by their peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lential corruptions, <hi>infect more.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween both, all roomes are filled up;
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:107494:58"/> if there be fewer <hi>ſeemingly righteous</hi> then there were; there are the more that are <hi>openly vicious;</hi> ſuch as have the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of beaſts, as of <hi>Goats, Swine, Apes, Peacocks, Aſſes,</hi> and ſo we are ſufficiently furniſhed <hi>with pictures</hi> ſtill.</p>
               <p>The world loves to be couſened, and (as it is in juggling) <hi>the more curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous the deceit is, the more it pleaſeth, tho it be known to be a deceit,</hi> ſo the picture of <hi>the grapes, that couſened the birds;</hi> and that of <hi>the vaile, that couſened the painter,</hi> were therefore held excellent peeces, becauſe they deceived the ſight with ſo much art. <hi>How commendable is truth, when the meer reſemblance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is enough to give commendation to falſhood!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Likeneſs to nature is the perfection of art,</hi> and <hi>likeneſs to the God of nature is the perfection of grace.</hi> God is the Original of all perfection, and we are expreſsly commanded to be <hi>conforme unto his Image;</hi> that is, <hi>not in his power, and glory;</hi> the Angels affected that, and fell; nor in his <hi>knowledg, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:107494:58"/> our firſt parents coveted that, and tranſgreſſed; but in his <hi>holineſs, and righteouſneſs; in being good, and doing good.</hi> Lord teach me <hi>to copy out thy divine nature, in thoſe attributes wherein thou art imitable,</hi> that ſince I cannot be like thee <hi>as thou art the moſt high; I may indeavour to reſemble thee, as thou art the moſt lowly, and meek, and holy, and beneficent God.</hi> It is my <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,</hi> as well as my <hi>crime,</hi> that I have ſo long <hi>borne the image of the firſt man,</hi> which was <hi>of the earth, earthly;</hi> vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe I beſeech thee, to ſtampe <hi>the image of the ſecond man, the Lord from heaven,</hi> upon my corrupt nature, and by the renewing of my mind, ſo transform me, that whilſt others pleaſe themſelvs in their walk thorough <hi>the gallery of this world</hi> with beholding vain objects, and entertaining the luſt of their eyes with them, miſtaking <hi>ſhadowes for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</hi> and <hi>pictures for realities;</hi> call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (but not in thy ſence) <hi>things that are not, as if they were;</hi> I may have <hi>the eyes of my faith</hi> fixed upon <hi>thine image,</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:107494:59"/> as the only object of my delight; <hi>ſo ſhall I be ſatisfied, when I awake out of this dreaming life, with thy likeneſs, and be like unto thee, when I ſhall ſee thee as thou art in glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. XIV.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſight of a Parret in a Cage.</head>
               <p>WHat hath <hi>this poor bird</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that ſhe ſhould be <hi>made a Priſoner?</hi> I ſee others <hi>of our own cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate</hi> fore <hi>at liberty,</hi> whilſt this <hi>far fetcht ſtranger is in hold.</hi> Surely our vanities are <hi>ſharp ſet,</hi> when they come <hi>to ſtoop at a feather.</hi> But what is it, that the luſt of the eyes will <hi>not fly at?</hi> to trade for <hi>Apes, and Peacocks</hi> is no new thing. The world hath ever been given to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect trifles, and the miſcheif is, that while we <hi>take them up,</hi> they <hi>take us,</hi> and ſo we are <hi>in the cage too.</hi> We ſhall never be able to ſet <hi>a juſt price</hi> upon
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:107494:59"/> any thing, ſo long as we ſuffer <hi>our fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to be the cleark of the Market.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this Parret had been of <hi>a common plumage,</hi> ſhe might to this day have <hi>pearcht,</hi> where ſhe was <hi>hatcht;</hi> now her <hi>unfortunate beauty</hi> hath betraied her to this <hi>captivity.</hi> Thus many times the things that ſhould be <hi>for our advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> become unto us <hi>an occaſion of fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>what language is this?</hi> who would not think but that <hi>the Devil were in the Parret,</hi> as well as he was <hi>in the Serpent?</hi> and yet, it is but a <hi>ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the air,</hi> and of little ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; there are ſuch babblers to be found among us, without the help of a lanthorne, that have the art of <hi>ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much,</hi> and <hi>ſaying nothing;</hi> and I wiſh it were a rarer thing to hear <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets ſpeak like men,</hi> then to hear <hi>men ſpeak like Parrets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet I ſee this good language houlds but <hi>during pleaſure;</hi> upon the leaſt provocation, the bird returns to her own <hi>natural clamour</hi> again. <hi>How
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:107494:60"/> many are there that can beſtow goodly words upon God, ſo long as he is pleaſed to pleaſe them:</hi> and yet are ready <hi>to curſe him to his face,</hi> if he do but touch them in <hi>their perſons,</hi> or <hi>eſtates?</hi> ſuch <hi>tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher diſciples,</hi> as can follow Chriſt, with a plauſible formality, ſo long as they may <hi>eat of the loaves, and be filled;</hi> but when <hi>perſecution ariſeth, are by and by offended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O God, whilſt the world is taken with gariſh toyes, and things that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not profit; let it be the delight of my Soul <hi>to apprehend thee,</hi> and to be <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by thee.</hi> Teach me ſo to look upon thy works, that they may be <hi>a leſſon,</hi> not <hi>a ſnare to me:</hi> So ſhall I, even in <hi>the vanity of the creature,</hi> read <hi>thy glory;</hi> and from <hi>the folly of the world</hi> receive <hi>ſome inſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="meditation">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:107494:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION. XV.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon hearing good Muſick.</head>
               <p>I cannot but think that <hi>Soul out of tune,</hi> that is <hi>not affected</hi> with Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. For tho I am not of the opinion of that <hi>fidling Philoſopher,</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined <hi>the Soul to be a harmony;</hi> yet I do really believe, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that ſtriketh ſo immediatly, and incorporeally upon the powers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as <hi>Muſick</hi> doth. It <hi>inſinuateth</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Spirits, and hath ſuch <hi>a ſecret familiarity</hi> with them, that it diſpoſeth them to <hi>variety of paſſions,</hi> conformable to the <hi>ſeveral changes,</hi> and <hi>inflexions</hi> thereof. It <hi>ſtilleth the child</hi> at the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes breaſt, and layeth it a ſleep; it <hi>cheareth the labourer</hi> at his work, <hi>the gally ſlave</hi> at his Oar; it rouzeth <hi>the Souldier in the field,</hi> and exciteth him to action. Hiſtory telleth us of <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> his practice of <hi>phyſick, by Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:107494:61"/> and of his curing of diverſe ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes by that meanes; and experience verifieth the poſſibility thereof, in the recovery of thoſe that are ſtung with the <hi>Tarantula,</hi> by the ſame way. As to the operation thereof upon the mind, every one almoſt, that hath ears to hear, may be called to witneſs, whether ſome aires, and tunes, do not ſenſibly <hi>attriſt,</hi> others <hi>comfort;</hi> ſome <hi>move,</hi> others <hi>moderate</hi> affections. To ſay nothing of thoſe fables of <hi>Orpheus,</hi> and <hi>Amphion;</hi> the one reported to have <hi>charmed birds and beaſts;</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid to have <hi>moved ſtocks and ſtones</hi> by their harmonious accents; the moral whereof tended only to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the <hi>power of perſwaſion,</hi> and the efficacy thereof, <hi>to reduce brutiſh, and ignorant people to civility,</hi> and <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitation,</hi> and <hi>politie;</hi> tho withall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring (in that alluſion to Muſick) that even in thoſe rude times of old, there was a ſenſe of the operation of it upon the Spirits, and natures of men; for which cauſe both <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:107494:61"/> recommended the uſe of it, in their ſtates, and common weals, as benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to the regulation of manners. It may be enough to ſay, that there is a kind of <hi>divine power in harmony,</hi> work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even upon <hi>thoſe Spirits,</hi> which are of <hi>a nature exalted above the Spirts of men:</hi> this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſufficiently witneſſed by the word of God, in thoſe famous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha.</hi> What <hi>the reaſon</hi> of theſe ſtrange effects ſhould be, is beyond <hi>the compaſs of reaſon</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agine. <hi>Lord! whilſt this harmony delights</hi> mine ear, <hi>let the conſideration of thine infinite wiſdome, whereby thou haſt</hi> made all things in number, weight, and meaſure (in <hi>a harmony to be ſeen),</hi> affect <hi>my heart,</hi> that ſo while I <hi>admire</hi> thee in what I <hi>hear, and ſee;</hi> I may <hi>adore</hi> thee in what I <hi>cannot comprehend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How <hi>raviſhing</hi> is this pleaſure; and how is my Soul <hi>elevated</hi> with it, even to an <hi>extaſy?</hi> that <hi>whether it be in the body, or out of the body,</hi> me thinks I can hardly ſay; certainly there is nothing of greater uſe for the raiſing, and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:107494:62"/> of our affections towards God, then <hi>the ſinging of his high praiſes in Pſalmes, and Hymmes, and Spiritual Songs.</hi> The <hi>primitive Chriſtians</hi> were ſo taken with it, that in the times of perſecution, at their <hi>conventicles before day,</hi> they could not forbear making <hi>their melody to the Lord,</hi> though many times <hi>they were diſcovered by it,</hi> to their extream hazard. It is written by <hi>a Father,</hi> that in the little Town of <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leem,</hi> near unto which he lived, <hi>there was nothing almoſt to be heard, but that heavenly muſick, reſounding in all places; from the ſhop to the plough;</hi> there was <hi>no mirth, but in ſinging Pſalms.</hi> O the goodneſs of God, who knowing our infirmity, how much more we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to that which <hi>delights,</hi> then to that which <hi>profiteth,</hi> hath ſo contrived it; that by <hi>borrowing</hi> from melody that pleaſure which <hi>toucheth our ears,</hi> he doth by the <hi>ſmoothneſs, and ſoftneſs</hi> thereof, as by <hi>a holy ſtealth,</hi> convey a treaſure of Good things <hi>into our hearts;</hi> ſo that whilſt we think <hi>we ſing, we
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:107494:62"/> learn;</hi> and in doing that wherein <hi>we delight,</hi> we are taught that, whereby <hi>we profit.</hi> It is obſervable that <hi>the ſweetneſs of Muſick conſiſteth in diſcords</hi> (high, low, mean) there can be <hi>no harmony in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſons.</hi> If there be not <hi>a diſtinction in ſounds, how ſhall it be known, what is piped, or harped?</hi> but then thoſe diſcords muſt be <hi>propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionately accorded,</hi> or the ſound will be <hi>ingrate,</hi> and <hi>odious;</hi> and it is no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the point <hi>of Government;</hi> there muſt be <hi>a diſtinction of degrees obſerved; a ſuperiority,</hi> and <hi>an inferiority;</hi> with <hi>a due order</hi> held between them; every one retaining <hi>his proper place;</hi> the <hi>treble</hi> muſt not be ſtrung, where <hi>the baſe</hi> ſhould be, nor <hi>the mean</hi> where <hi>the treble</hi> ſhould be: every one muſt be kept in his <hi>proper tone,</hi> neither <hi>too flat,</hi> nor <hi>too ſharpe;</hi> one pin ſhould not be wound up <hi>too high,</hi> nor another let down <hi>too low,</hi> (which was noted by <hi>Apollonius</hi> to have been <hi>Nero</hi>'s fault in Government) but every one in his <hi>peculiar ſtation,</hi> muſt be kept in <hi>a due
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:107494:63"/> harmony:</hi> So we ſee <hi>Octaves,</hi> or <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apazons,</hi> (though ſo many notes diſtant, yet (as by a ſecret ſimpathy) <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond,</hi> the one to the pulſe and touch of the other, and make the ſweeteſt concord. <hi>Parity</hi> (at the beſt) <hi>is but a kind of orderly confuſion;</hi> there can be no Muſick in it.</p>
               <p>But there be ſome <hi>ſtrings,</hi> which are called <hi>falſe ones,</hi> which by reaſon of the inequality, and unevenneſs of their making, will never be brought to <hi>accord with the reſt,</hi> but will <hi>perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly jar;</hi> It were well if we had not too many Spirits of that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>neven jarring tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> that nothing will ever work them to any agreement. <hi>I would they were cut off that trouble the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what a deal of time is ſpent <hi>in tuning,</hi> before we can come to have <hi>any Muſick?</hi> and how eaſily and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is that delight of the Sons of men interrupted, by <hi>the ſlipping, or break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a ſtring</hi> or <hi>the miſtopping of a fret?</hi> the caſe is alike in our moſt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:107494:63"/> pleaſing earthly enjoyments; there is hardly any pleaſure we take, but it coſts us <hi>pains to take it;</hi> and when we have it, every <hi>little accident</hi> is enough to <hi>diſcompoſe it.</hi> If we <hi>ſet our hearts</hi> upon it, and make it <hi>our buſinneſs,</hi> we <hi>ſtop upon a wrong fret;</hi> and if we <hi>ſcrue it up too high in our eſtimation,</hi> or <hi>let it down too low,</hi> to the ſervice of baſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ends, we run the hazard of making it <hi>break, or ſtip,</hi> or yeild <hi>no ſound at all</hi> to pleaſe us. <hi>There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ſure, then that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſure under the Sun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O my Soul, if there be ſo much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be taken in that, which</hi> we call Muſick hear, <hi>which (when all comes to all) is but a ſound, ariſing from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion of a few guts, or wire ſtrings faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a concave frame, or inſtrumet of wood, moved by the fingers of men, and it may be accompanied with their voices; raiſe thy ſelf upon the wings of faith, and love, to the contemplation of</hi> that truly melodious harmony, <hi>whereof thou ſhalt, by the grace of God, be a partaker in</hi> the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:107494:64"/> quire of Heaven <hi>without interruption to all eternity; when the voices of</hi> Saints, and Angells <hi>ſhall be conjoyned with the harpes of God in everlaſting</hi> Hallellujas <hi>unto him that ſitteth upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb for ever,</hi> and ever. Lord, I have had enough, and enough of <hi>the ſcraping of this world;</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it may for the time afford ſome pleaſure to mine ear, yet it is <hi>ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary,</hi> and to my Soul <hi>ſo unſatisfactc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> that I humbly beſeech thee to fit me for <hi>a better conſort,</hi> even that ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial one; where <hi>all mouths ſhall be filled with thy praiſe,</hi> and <hi>with thy hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our;</hi> and <hi>where my lips ſhall rejoyce, when I ſing unto thee, and my Soul which thou haſt redeemed.</hi> Here <hi>the beſt of thy Servants</hi> have been weary of their <hi>crying,</hi> there the <hi>meaneſt of them</hi> ſhall never be weary <hi>of their ſinging;</hi> they ſhall <hi>reſt from their labours,</hi> but they ſhall never reſt from their <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy'es, to the Lord God almighty;</hi> that <hi>labour</hi> ſhall be <hi>their reſt.</hi> There ſhall need <hi>no keeping time</hi> in that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:107494:64"/> Muſick, for none ſhall be <hi>out in their part,</hi> and <hi>time ſhall be no more.</hi> O my Soul, what doſt thou here? <hi>I waite for thy Salvation, O Lord, but Lord how long?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. XVI.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſight of a pleaſant Garden.</head>
               <p>THere is no humane pleaſure that hath ſo much <hi>of antiquity,</hi> and <hi>of the ſtate of innocency</hi> in it, as the pleaſure of a Garden. The firſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, and mention that we have of pleaſure in the world, is with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>that garden in Eden,</hi> which was of <hi>Gods own plantation,</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he gave <hi>intertainment to our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> as in a room dreſt up on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to receive them, and to give them delight. But yet, all was not made <hi>for meer delight</hi> there; there was that which <hi>was good (good for foood)</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:107494:65"/> as well as that which was <hi>pleaſant to the ſight. All the pleaſures that are of Gods making, are good; vanity came in with ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How happy might we have been in that <hi>Primitive condition,</hi> if ſin had not <hi>corrupted it?</hi> when without <hi>fears for to day,</hi> or <hi>cares for to morrow,</hi> we might have lived <hi>immortally bleſſed,</hi> in a conſtant communion with God, and in the affluence of all good things in him; when <hi>our roſes</hi> ſhould have had <hi>no briers;</hi> when our <hi>pleaſures</hi> ſhould have had nothing but <hi>an innocent ſweetneſs</hi> in them, and we might have <hi>gathered them without ſcratching our fing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> without <hi>raveling our Conſciences:</hi> when <hi>the voice of the Lord God walking in the garden,</hi> would have been an invitation to us, to have <hi>walked with him,</hi> and <hi>not a terrour</hi> to have <hi>driven us from his preſence. O Adam!</hi> what haſt thou done? what <hi>a happy eſtate</hi> haſt thou forfeited, for <hi>an inconſiderable trifle!</hi> How haſt thou by <hi>one bit of an Apple</hi> (a ſower one) ſet both <hi>thine
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:107494:65"/> own,</hi> and <hi>thy Childrens teeth on edge,</hi> to all thy ſucceding generations? but bleſſed be God, who hath ſent his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>ſecond Adam, the Lord from Heaven,</hi> who by the merits of his ſufferings hath <hi>redeemed that forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and infeoffed us in <hi>a better eſtate,</hi> then we were in <hi>before the fall:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we who were of the <hi>earth earthly,</hi> are made conformable to <hi>the image of the heavenly;</hi> and intitled to <hi>a celeſtial paradiſe,</hi> into which <hi>no Serpent</hi> ſhall ever be able to enter, and out of which we ſhall <hi>never be ejected.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is worth the noting, that if our firſt Parents had <hi>not tranſgreſſed,</hi> but had continued in their <hi>imparadiſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diton,</hi> they ſhould not have enjoyed <hi>an idle lazy felicity.</hi> God did not put them into the Garden, as we <hi>put beaſts into a good paſture,</hi> to <hi>graze</hi> and <hi>batten;</hi> or as he placed the <hi>Leviathan in the Sea, to play therein;</hi> but <hi>to dreſs,</hi> and <hi>keep it;</hi> to <hi>employ their time in doing good in it;</hi> and <hi>that exerciſe of their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> ſhould have been unto them
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:107494:66"/> there, as <hi>the doing of Gods will is to the bleſſed Angels in Heaven, a maine part of their beatitude.</hi> It is a comfortable thing <hi>to live in a good vocation;</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, without that, we cannot prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly be ſaid <hi>to live. A calling, or vocation,</hi> is, in the language of the law, tearm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>an Addition;</hi> but it is <hi>ſuch an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> as <hi>a figure is to a cyphar;</hi> it is that, that makes us <hi>ſomething in the world;</hi> and without which, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that are, are but like Nulls in a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, only remarkable, becauſe they ſignify nothing: O my Soul, conſider this; <hi>it is better to dye, then not to live;</hi> and they <hi>live not,</hi> that <hi>live to no end.</hi> Make it thy buiſineſs ſo to live, as that when God ſhall call thee, thou maiſt be found in the way of thy calling, <hi>doing thy Lords buiſineſs;</hi> which is the way to be admitted into <hi>the joy of thy Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is written of our bleſſed Saviour, that <hi>he affected a garden,</hi> and <hi>frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it often with his diſciples.</hi> God doth not prohibit us the liberty, and free
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:107494:66"/> uſe of lawful pleaſures, ſo long as we do not <hi>ſet our hearts, and affections</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, but make uſe of them, as we do of our gardens, for <hi>recreation,</hi> and <hi>diverſion,</hi> and not <hi>to dwell in;</hi> and ſo long as we <hi>look up to him</hi> in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them, as <hi>the God of our comforts</hi> and have our rejoycing in him. O my Soul, take him whom thou loveſt, for an example, and ſtudy to improve this delight to a ſanctified uſe: when thou art here, <hi>in company,</hi> to edify others (as he did his diſciples) by a holy communication, Miniſtring grace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; and <hi>when alone</hi> to ſpend thy time, and exerciſe thy thoughts (as he alſo did) <hi>in Meditation, and praier.</hi> Nay let his <hi>burial, and reſurrection</hi> (both which were <hi>in a garden</hi>) be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances unto thee, to put thee in mind, (in the middeſt of thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights) that thou art <hi>implanted with him into death;</hi> that like as he was <hi>raiſed up from the dead, by the glory of the Father,</hi> even ſo thou alſo ſhouldeſt be <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the likeneſs of his reſurrection, to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:107494:67"/> walk in newneſs of life.</hi> Let theſe thoughts be thine <hi>intertainment,</hi> and thy garden will be <hi>ſo much paradiſe</hi> unto thee. He that <hi>walkes with God,</hi> can never want <hi>a good walke,</hi> and <hi>good company.</hi> There is <hi>no garden well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived,</hi> but that which hath an <hi>Enoch's walk</hi> in it.</p>
               <p>How <hi>cleanly</hi> are theſe <hi>Allies</hi> kept? and how <hi>orderly</hi> are the <hi>Hedges</hi> cut, and the <hi>Trees</hi> pruned and nailed, and not an irregular <hi>Twig</hi> left? there is no ſuch care taken for the <hi>weeds,</hi> and <hi>buſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> and <hi>brambles</hi> that grow abroad. God is careful to preſerve the <hi>Garden of his Church</hi> in all <hi>decency</hi> and <hi>order;</hi> and will not ſuffer it to be overgrown with <hi>errours</hi> or <hi>prophaneſs;</hi> but is (like a good Husbandman, if <hi>I</hi> may ſay ſo with all humbleneſs) ever at work a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it; either <hi>weeding</hi> out, what his heavenly hand hath not <hi>planted;</hi> or if need be, lopping, and cutting off luxuriant branches, that bear not <hi>fruit;</hi> or purging thoſe that do bear, that they may bring forth more <hi>fruit.</hi> But as
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:107494:67"/> for thoſe that are without, he lets them alone to grow wild, not giving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo much trouble (to ſpeak after the manner of men) as either to dig about them with his <hi>Chaſtiſements,</hi> or to dung and inrich them with his <hi>Mercies,</hi> but leaving them to their own <hi>barrenneſs,</hi> and to the <hi>curſe</hi> attending it. God in his judgement begins at his <hi>own Houſe;</hi> and if ſo, what ſhall the end be of thoſe, that are not of his <hi>Houſhold? It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God,</hi> though for <hi>correction</hi> an <hi>edification;</hi> but it is infinitely more fearful, and horrid, <hi>to fall out of his hands;</hi> to be, as <hi>without the pale of his providence,</hi> left <hi>to bring forth fruit unto our ſelvs.</hi> Why ſhould thoſe that are of the Church of God be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged under their croſſes, and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when as they are but <hi>the effects of his divine husbandry,</hi> whereby <hi>to melior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and improve them?</hi> their ſufferings, are but ſignes of his owning them to be true plants of his own ſetting; and that they grow where they ſhould
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:107494:68"/> do. Lord, do <hi>any thing</hi> to me, rather <hi>then nothing:</hi> Let thy <hi>pruning knife</hi> be never <hi>ſo ſharp,</hi> and <hi>cutting,</hi> it can do me <hi>no hurt,</hi> ſo long as it <hi>tends to make me good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At preſent</hi> this is a ſweet place, but what will it be <hi>a few months hence?</hi> at what time the liberality of nature will (for this Seaſon) be ſpent, and her charity to us, will have reduced her to a bare condition? When winter is come all this verdure, and fragrancy is gone; and we may go <hi>ſeek the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, in the garden;</hi> and the place thereof ſhall not know it. How vain and tranſitory, and fugitive, are all earthly pleaſures? <hi>like flowers, they wither, even whilſt we are ſmelling to them,</hi> and <hi>periſh in the uſing;</hi> the <hi>faſhion of the world,</hi> as well as of the garden, <hi>paſſeth away.</hi> It was well ſaid of a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that <hi>in this inferior viſible world, there is nothing to be ſeen, but the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and appearances of things,</hi> but that <hi>in the inviſible, in the ſuperior world, there are ſolids, and ſubſtances
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:107494:68"/> to be found, as in their proper region.</hi> In vain do we look for <hi>any thing in any thing here,</hi> when there is <hi>a ſuperſcription of vanity</hi> written <hi>upon all things under the Sun.</hi> If any body would know, <hi>what vanity is?</hi> the word of God will tell him, it is <hi>ſomething leſs then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> if any would be ſatisfied what nothing is; I can tell him, <hi>it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> and it is ſo, becauſe it is not, becauſe <hi>it hath no being.</hi> He is wiſe, that knows how to take things, as they are, in their true entity. <hi>The world can never deceive us, ſo long as we are led by truth, and not by opinion.</hi> He is not confined in the receiving of mony, that takes <hi>braſs coine</hi> according to <hi>the true value of the mettal,</hi> and <hi>as braſs coine.</hi> O my Soul, learn this wiſdome; <hi>uſe pleaſures, as pleaſures;</hi> and whilſt thou laieſt hold on <hi>theſe follies,</hi> do as <hi>Solomon</hi> did, retaine the wiſdome to know they are but follies. Do not <hi>ſet thine eyes upon that which is not; or</hi> which (if, in any ſence, <hi>it be)</hi> is never at ſuch a conſiſtence, but
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:107494:69"/> that even whilſt it is, it may be ſaid, it was; ſo fluid, that like water, the more it is embraced, and graſped, the more it ſlips away. But look up, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider; <hi>the things here below,</hi> which <hi>are ſeen, are temporary,</hi> and of ſhort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, but the things which are above, <hi>and which are not ſeen, are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi> Thoſe, and none but thoſe, are the <hi>true pleaſures, which are at Gods right hand for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. XVII.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſight of a fair horſe, well mannaged.</head>
               <p>WHat <hi>a noble Generous creature</hi> is this? and how anſwerable to that character of a brave goodly horſe, which was delivered by God himſelf out of the whirlwind? <hi>His creſt</hi> ſeems to be <hi>clothed with thunder; the glory of his Noſtrils is terrible; he ſwalloweth the ground with fierceneſs and rage; and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:107494:69"/> ſaith among the trumpets ha, ha; he mocketh at fear; he paweth, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in his ſtrength; and is ready to go on to meet the armed men, as if he ſmelt the battel afar off, and heard the thunder of the Captains, and the ſhouting.</hi> God ſeemeth (if I may ſo ſpeak) to take pleaſure in deſcribing this peice of his own workmanſhip, ſetting forth (as in the deſcription of the <hi>Leviathan) his parts, and his power, and his comely proportion.</hi> Where God thinks it <hi>not fit to conceal</hi> the commendation of his works, they ought to be had <hi>in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance,</hi> and to be glorified by us. <hi>All thy works praiſe thee O Lord, and thy Saints ſhall bleſs thee in all thy works.</hi> O my Soul praiſe thou the Lord, as in other things, ſo in this particular op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of his hands, which he himſelf hath praiſed, and <hi>ranked with the cheif of his wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be matter of juſt admiration, even to the moſt knowing perſons, to conſider how <hi>the ſtrength, and fierceneſs of this creature is ſubdued, and ſubjected
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:107494:70"/> to the ſervice, and mannagement of a weak infirme man;</hi> who is ſo far unable to cope with ſuch an enemy upon even tearmes, that he cannot withſtand the kick of his foot. <hi>Lord what is man, that thou ſhouldſt thus magnify him,</hi> and <hi>put the fear, and dread of him upon all thine inferior creatures, and deliver them into his hand?</hi> Certainly they are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to nature,</hi> or rather to <hi>the God of nature,</hi> that think man ill dealt with, becauſe he is not <hi>ſo long laſting,</hi> as moſt <hi>vegetables</hi> are; nor ſo <hi>ſtrong and active,</hi> as many <hi>ſenſitive creatures</hi> are: not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the great creator aiming at a higher end in man, is in theſe lower faculties <hi>leſs intent,</hi> and <hi>elabor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate;</hi> as having in <hi>that excellent gift of reaſon</hi> (wherewith he is indued) not only <hi>repaired,</hi> and <hi>compenſated</hi> thoſe defects unto him, but <hi>exalted him above all other creatures;</hi> and inabled him thereby to command their parts and qualities, wherein they exceed him, and to make uſe of them for his own ſervice.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:107494:70"/>
               <p>But <hi>what merit is there in man, that ſhould thus mount him, and ſet him on horſe-back?</hi> It is true, in his <hi>creation,</hi> God innobled him, by impreſſing the Signature of his own Image upon him, and by giving him <hi>that dominion over the workes of his hands;</hi> but <hi>man being in honour continued not,</hi> but by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication fell; whereby he became <hi>not only like the beaſts that periſh,</hi> ſo that they might ſay, <hi>man is become like one of us;</hi> but <hi>inferiour to them,</hi> and ſubject to their annoyance, to be miſcheived, and maiſtered, and (as it were) <hi>to be ridden</hi> by them. <hi>All other creatures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the honour, and dignity of their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation:</hi> all that hoſt (ſo the word of God calls it) all that army of creatures, doth punctually obſerve the diſcipline, and paſs upon the duty impoſed on them by their maker; and act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: but man only, who was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated <hi>general of</hi> that army, could <hi>not command himſelf,</hi> but being miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governed by his own corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, did <hi>imbaſe,</hi> and <hi>abbaſterdiſe</hi> that
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:107494:71"/> noble kind wherewith God had hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or'd him. <hi>O the riches of free grace!</hi> the reprobate Angels <hi>ſinned but once,</hi> and were <hi>immediatly, and irrecoverably dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;</hi> the <hi>ſenſitive creatures never ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and yet are <hi>ſubdued to the bondage of corruption;</hi> Man, whom God had made <hi>little inferiour to the elect Angels,</hi> and <hi>ſuperiour to all the works of his hands in this ſublunary world,</hi> he doth <hi>nothing,</hi> and can <hi>do nothing of himſelf, as of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but ſin in every imagination of the thoughts of his heart,</hi> and hath thereby rendered himſelf juſtly liable to death and hell: and yet, as if God had lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him <hi>better then himſelf,</hi> it pleaſed him <hi>to give himſelf</hi> (his only <hi>begotten</hi> Son, <hi>Coeſſential, Coequal</hi> with himſelf) to be <hi>a ranſome</hi> for his ſins, and by <hi>the all-ſufficiency</hi> of that redemtion, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, to re-inveſt him in his <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer command</hi> here, and to intitle him to <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven</hi> hereafter. <hi>O the depth!</hi> How much ſhould man <hi>love,</hi> to whom ſo much is given, and ſo much forgiven?</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:107494:71"/>
               <p>I cannot but have a charity for thoſe poor ignorant people, who upon the firſt ſight of horſe men, <hi>took the men, and the horſes to be but one and the ſame creature.</hi> But taking them as they are diſtinct; who would not think, but that (as it was in <hi>the viſion of the living creatures, and the wheels) the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the one, were in the other,</hi> and that <hi>one Soul acted both?</hi> So doth the beaſt anſwer <hi>to every, the leaſt motion</hi> of the rider, and obey his mannage. What is is this but <hi>an emblem of ſence guided by reaſon?</hi> This horſe may paſs for <hi>the repreſentative of a well governed man.</hi> The great <hi>Moraliſt</hi> made that uſe of the deſcription of a brave ſerviceable Horſe in <hi>Virgil,</hi> to apply it to the Character of a gallant perſon; profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that if he were to commend <hi>Cato,</hi> he <hi>could not expreſs his conſtant, regular, noble carriage in better tearmes. How beautiful is vertue, and a well comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded courage in a man, when the bare ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of that gallantry,</hi> (tho ſo far ſhort) <hi>is ſo well becoming, even in a beaſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:107494:72"/>
               <p>But we have a caveat given us, <hi>Not to be as the horſe;</hi> which is exemplified, in our turning to our own <hi>precipitate courſes, as the horſe ruſheth heedleſly into the battel,</hi> and in <hi>our pampering,</hi> and <hi>fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting</hi> our <hi>corrupt affections,</hi> when (like <hi>fed horſes</hi>) we <hi>neigh after our luſts.</hi> What <hi>a beaſt is man, when he ſuffers his ſenſe to tranſport him beyond his reaſon?</hi> Surely, ſo much worſe then <hi>the horſe, and mule, which have no underſtanding,</hi> as he hath <hi>an underſtanding, which he himſelf hath imbrutiſhtand abaſed below his Species.</hi> He is brutiſh (as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith) <hi>in his very knowledg.</hi> The <hi>man</hi> may <hi>ride</hi> the <hi>horſe,</hi> but ſo long as the <hi>ſenſe rides</hi> the <hi>reaſon,</hi> the <hi>beaſt rides the man.</hi> In vain doth he raine in his horſe with bit, and bridle, who lets himſelf looſe to an <hi>unbridled converſation.</hi> O my God, I have a <hi>natural reſtyneſs in me,</hi> which I beſeech thee <hi>to break;</hi> and and therefore when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever my follies would <hi>fly out,</hi> and attempt to <hi>run away with me;</hi> uſe me like my ſelf, <hi>a whip for the horſe,</hi> and <hi>a rod for the fooles back;</hi> and if I will
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:107494:72"/> not <hi>hear the voice,</hi> let me <hi>feell the ſmart of it. Bleſſed is he whom thou chaſteneſt, and teacheſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A horſe is <hi>a plain dealing creature,</hi> and, tho very <hi>ſerviceable,</hi> yet (if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked) <hi>as ready to caſt a King, as a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar;</hi> he is <hi>no courtier;</hi> and therefore it was upon that account, that <hi>Carneades</hi> adviſed Princes, and great men <hi>to practiſe horſemanſhip, that they might be uſed to ſomething that would not flatter them.</hi> I hold it but <hi>decent to be ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the quality of publick, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perſons;</hi> but he that will be <hi>rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by their humours,</hi> muſt pardon me if I eſteem him to be of ſomething <hi>a lower degree then a horſe,</hi> and worthy to be <hi>Spur-galled</hi> if he do not (at the leaſt) <hi>try their horſemanſhip that back him,</hi> whither <hi>they can keep the ſaddle, and ſit faſt, or no.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I find it written, as an expreſſion of honour to the houſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> that <hi>God had made them as his goodly horſe in the battel; and</hi> yet in other places it is ſaid, that <hi>a horſe is but a vain thing,</hi>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:107494:73"/> and (without the divine protection) utterly unable <hi>to deliver any by his great ſtrength.</hi> Surely <hi>God is a jealous God,</hi> tender of his honour; and tho he do <hi>allow</hi> and <hi>appoint meanes</hi> for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and preſervation, yet he will not by any meanes that we ſhould <hi>truſt in any, but him.</hi> The woe, is not to thoſe that <hi>ride,</hi> but to thoſe that ſtay <hi>on Horſes, becauſe they are many, and ſtrong.</hi> Let who ſo will, put their confidence <hi>in Chariots, and in horſes; I will remember the name of the Lord my God, and ſtay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</hi> He is <hi>a ſure refuge, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent help: The horſe is prepared againſt the day of battel, but ſafety is of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="meditation">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:107494:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. XVIII.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſight of Bowlers in a Green.</head>
               <p>WHat <hi>an emblem of the world</hi> have we here <hi>in this Green?</hi> what <hi>making and abetting of parties?</hi> What <hi>caſting to attain ends?</hi> ſome <hi>one way,</hi> and <hi>ſome another;</hi> according as they are <hi>biaſſed?</hi> and moſt are <hi>ſhort,</hi> or <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> or <hi>wide;</hi> and few there be, that get to ly <hi>neer the mark they aime at. All are very buiſy,</hi> and <hi>clamorous;</hi> and yet none enjoy the <hi>ſport ſo much,</hi> as thoſe that have <hi>no part in it, but are ſtanders by, and diſſintereſſed perſons.</hi> It is a priviledg next to that of God, and his Angels, to be <hi>a ſpectator in the world.</hi> Lord, whilſt others affect to be <hi>gamſters</hi> here, let me be in the number of thoſe that <hi>look on;</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe that <hi>look up;</hi> ſo ſhall I have <hi>a double advantage,</hi> both in my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:107494:74"/> from <hi>looſing any thing</hi> here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where I <hi>adventure nothing;</hi> and as I ſhall be ſure to <hi>winn all that I can deſire</hi> hereafter, whilſt I <hi>ſet mine affections on things above.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is <hi>a meaſuring caſt,</hi> whether it be <hi>better ſport to ſee the bowling, or the bowlers;</hi> of the two, <hi>the laſt</hi> would make one <hi>laugh moſt;</hi> and therefore I think <hi>the beſt part of the ſport lyes on their ſide.</hi> Certainly there cannot be a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>jeaſt ſeen,</hi> then the <hi>antick figures,</hi> into which <hi>they ſcrew themſelves;</hi> nor a greater <hi>abſurdity heard,</hi> then the <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible advice</hi> that they caſt after their <hi>ſenſeleſs bowles;</hi> now and then, to have them <hi>rub;</hi> now and then, to have them <hi>flye;</hi> and to obſerve their <hi>impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> (many time, to <hi>a degree of deſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi>) if they chance not to run <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondently to their flexures,</hi> and <hi>cringes.</hi> What is the difference in point of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, between asking <hi>Council of a ſtock and giving Council to a block?</hi> The Moral of it may ſerve to informe, us that <hi>all paſſions, in their exceſſes, are unbecom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:107494:74"/>
               <p>But where is the fault, if the bowle do go wrong? is it not in <hi>the hand</hi> that miſguided it? and yet rather then faile, we can lay the blame, either up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the <hi>lightneſs,</hi> or <hi>heavineſs,</hi> or <hi>biaſs of</hi> the bowle. <hi>We are naturally loth to own what we do amiſs, and are willing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our errours upon others; tho never ſo much guilty our ſelves.</hi> We know whoſe plea it was, <hi>the woman did it,</hi> and <hi>the Serpent did</hi> it, but that would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit.</p>
               <p>It is true, tho a bowle be <hi>never ſo well delivered from the hand,</hi> it may meet with <hi>ſuch rubs in the way,</hi> as may either <hi>retard,</hi> or <hi>divert</hi> it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there muſt be a conſideration had accordingly, to give it <hi>a fit ſtrength,</hi> to carry it thorough thoſe <hi>accidents.</hi> They do well that <hi>begin well,</hi> and ground <hi>their deſignes well,</hi> but if they do <hi>not allow for a rub in their caſt,</hi> it is odds if ever they <hi>get home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a great advantage (eſpecially to <hi>an unskilful bowler</hi>) to have a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing friend <hi>to give him ground;</hi> and it is
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:107494:75"/> no otherwiſe in the mannagement of affairs in the world. The <hi>greateſt, and moſt prudent perſons,</hi> that have liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their generations, have been moſt careful in this point, to have <hi>men of advice about them.</hi> To ſay nothing of thoſe <hi>Perſian Monarchs,</hi> that had their <hi>Counſellers,</hi> whom they called <hi>their eyes,</hi> to guide them in the conduct of their Government; nor of the <hi>Aſyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Ahaſuerus,</hi> whoſe manner it was, <hi>in matters of law and judgment,</hi> to conſult <hi>his wiſe men, that knew the times; Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, the man after Gods own heart,</hi> had his <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> an <hi>oraculous Counſellor,</hi> if he had had <hi>honeſty to his wiſdome; Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt of all men, was not without his <hi>Et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am,</hi> and <hi>Haman,</hi> and <hi>Chaliol,</hi> and <hi>Darda;</hi> and if <hi>Rehoboam</hi> would have <hi>taken that ground</hi> which was given him by <hi>thoſe old men,</hi> that had <hi>ſtood before his Father,</hi> he might have done well, but his <hi>biaſs wheeled him to the young men, that were brought up with him,</hi> and ſo by their miſguiding him, he loſt <hi>ten Tribes at a caſt;</hi> where
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:107494:75"/> 
                  <hi>no Council is, people fall, but in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Counſellers there is ſafety.</hi> How ſafe, and happy are they that have God <hi>to give them ground</hi> who is <hi>the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller?</hi> and that can hear his voice di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting them, and telling them, <hi>this is the way, walk in it?</hi> O my God, <hi>give me a hearing heart</hi> (according to the praier of that <hi>wiſe and roial Servant</hi> of thine) <hi>that thy pure Commandment may enlighten mine eyes, to diſcerne the way wherein I ſhould go;</hi> ſo ſhall I be ſure not to <hi>caſt away mine indeavours,</hi> whilſt I follow thine advice, who art both <hi>my guide, and my way, and the only way of truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is an unlucky thing to have <hi>a bowle lye ſhort in a good ground;</hi> for thereby, it doth not only <hi>looſe the caſt it ſelf,</hi> but it becometh <hi>a ſtumbling black unto others:</hi> We have <hi>many ſuch ſhort caſts</hi> made in the world, by thoſe who begin well (in <hi>the Spirit</hi>) and, with the Lawyer in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> run far <hi>toward the Kingdom of God,</hi> but then <hi>grow weary of well doing,</hi> and <hi>end in
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:107494:76"/> the fleſh;</hi> in <hi>Agrippa's Almoſt;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are both <hi>looſers themſelves,</hi> and <hi>hindrances to thoſe that would willingly fling home;</hi> and ſo become anſwerable <hi>both for their own, and for other mens ſins. That condition muſt needs be ſad, that cannot be amended, but by knocking</hi> up.</p>
               <p>It is a part of the ſport to ſee, <hi>how by a lucky hit, an unlikely bowle may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times come to lie neer, which without that chance, would have been far enough off.</hi> There be ſuch bowlers among us, that get more by <hi>juſting and knocking, then by fair play,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet it is here, as it is abroad in the world, <hi>the beſt bowles may have the worſt luck;</hi> all the huddle is about <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>none are ſtruck at,</hi> but thoſe that <hi>lie next the Maſter.</hi> O my Soul, whilſt others, with ſo much trouble, and hazard to themſelvs, are <hi>caſting at greatneſs, and honour,</hi> let it be thy buiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>to aime at goodneſs,</hi> which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>only true greatneſs;</hi> and then however the world may <hi>ſtrike at thee,</hi>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:107494:76"/> even to the <hi>turning of thee, out of the green,</hi> the greateſt blow it can give thee, will but make thee <hi>a toucher in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITATION. XIX.</hi> Of Hunting.</head>
               <p>It is obſerved by ſome, that <hi>hunting</hi> hath an <hi>ill name in Scripture;</hi> and that we do not read in all thoſe ſacred Records, of <hi>any one good man,</hi> that did affect it. <hi>Nimrod</hi> the <hi>mighty,</hi> and <hi>the firſt hunter,</hi> who was in after-times deified in memory of it, under the name (as ſome write) of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation, which we call <hi>Orion,</hi> with the <hi>dog-ſtar</hi> at <hi>his heeles;</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> the cunning hunter, are both therein ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently branded, the one for his <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi> the other for <hi>his profaneneſs:</hi> the very <hi>tearm of hunting</hi> is ſeldom therein uſed, but <hi>in an evil ſence;</hi> ſo we read of <hi>violent men, hunting one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother;
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:107494:77"/> of evil, hunting violent men;</hi> of the <hi>adultereſs, hunting the precious life;</hi> of <hi>falſe propheteſſes, hunting Souls.</hi> All which notwithſtanding, it will not conſequently follow, that hunting is in it ſelf illicite, becauſe <hi>the name</hi> of it is <hi>thus applied,</hi> or becauſe <hi>the thing it ſelf</hi> hath been, and is by many <hi>abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> To ſay nothing of thoſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments uſed by ſome Philoſophers, in juſtification of it; as that it is <hi>a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe,</hi> whereby mens <hi>Spirits</hi> are <hi>quickned and ſharpened,</hi> and their <hi>bodyes corroborated,</hi> and <hi>hardened,</hi> and <hi>fitted</hi> to undergo <hi>the ſervice of the field;</hi> and that it is but <hi>juſt, and natural,</hi> for men to take this freedom, upon the account of <hi>their dominion over the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> which are <hi>naturally theirs:</hi> It may be enough to ſay, that God hath in his word permitted it, with this only caution, that <hi>the blood of thoſe creatures, that were taken, and killed in hunting, ſhould be powerd out, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with the duſt;</hi> which was but the ſame prohibition that was given
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:107494:77"/> againſt <hi>the eating of any fleſh whatſoever, with the life thereof.</hi> Gods <hi>permiſſion</hi> is the <hi>beſt commiſſion</hi> we have for <hi>the uſe of any pleaſures,</hi> and therefore may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to authorize this. I might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge out of Hiſtory, that Saint <hi>John the beloved diſciple</hi> is reported to have been a great lover of this ſport, as ſome proof that <hi>a good man might, and</hi> that no leſs then a holy pen-man of the Scripture <hi>did affect it.</hi> But I paſs it by. O my God, thou knoweſt that our fraile, and weak bodyes have <hi>need of recreations, and divertiſments,</hi> as well as of <hi>food and raiment,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and ſuſtaine them in a good habitude; let me not live to abuſe this liberty, which thou art pleaſed to allow, either by <hi>over affecting it,</hi> or by turning my delight in it to <hi>a Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary wontonneſs,</hi> but do thou teach me by thy grace, ſo to uſe thy Creatures, in a moderate, ſober way, as <hi>having a dominion,</hi> but <hi>not a tiranny over them;</hi> and that it may be my principal end by this exerciſe to improve <hi>my
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:107494:78"/> health, and ſtrength</hi> to the <hi>advantage of thy ſervice;</hi> that there may be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of <hi>holineſs</hi> upon <hi>the belly,</hi> as well as upon <hi>the bowels;</hi> upon my <hi>pleaſures,</hi> as well as upon my <hi>moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or neceſſary actions,</hi> ſo as what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I do, (whether <hi>I hunt,</hi> or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I <hi>eat or drink) I may do all to thy glory!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What <hi>a breach of the peace hath ſin made in the world?</hi> not only between <hi>God, and man,</hi> and <hi>man and man,</hi> but even <hi>between brute creatures.</hi> Had it not been for <hi>that common make bate,</hi> the <hi>Lion and the Kid,</hi> the <hi>Wolfe and the Lamb,</hi> the <hi>Hound and the Hair,</hi> might have <hi>laine down together as good Friends.</hi> It is a ſad thing to conſider that <hi>ſin is the Maſter of the game among us,</hi> and that <hi>we are faine to be beholding to the Devil for our ſport.</hi> O my God! <hi>let the ſence of this, lay ſuch a reſtraint upon mine affections, that whilſt I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> this ſport, <hi>which is occaſioned by</hi> the entrance of ſin, <hi>I may never be ſo fooliſh as to make</hi> a ſport of ſin, <hi>but that I may
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:107494:78"/> make it</hi> my game to hunt that out; <hi>and</hi> to deſtroy that, which would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe <hi>purſue me to my deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There be <hi>ſeveral ſorts of chaſes</hi> in the world; ſome of <hi>beaſts of prey;</hi> others <hi>weak, harmleſs creatures.</hi> The firſt was <hi>noble,</hi> and had <hi>a gallantry</hi> in it; when men took pleaſure in <hi>freeing their countries from what was noxious, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive;</hi> but as people grew <hi>degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and baſe,</hi> ſo they became weary of <hi>ſporting with danger,</hi> and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves with <hi>ſmaller game,</hi> ſuch as they might <hi>play at</hi> with more <hi>ſafety</hi> and now the <hi>poor Deer</hi> and <hi>Hare,</hi> do in effect <hi>pay for all: They that do leaſt hurt, ſuffer moſt.</hi> It is no otherwiſe in the courſe, and practiſe of the world, wherein thoſe <hi>of ſtrength, and power, inſtead of oppoſing others that are in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to reſt their violence, do commonly turn upon ſuch as can make leaſt defence,</hi> and <hi>devoure thoſe that are more righteous then themſelves.</hi> There is <hi>game enough</hi> in the world <hi>beſides,</hi> but the <hi>poor man</hi>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:107494:79"/> that <hi>departeth from evil,</hi> is <hi>the eaſieſt prey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what <hi>an inſatiety</hi> is there in all theſe delights, which with ſo much <hi>paines,</hi> and <hi>clamour</hi> we purſue? when we have <hi>taken</hi> what we <hi>hunted through thick and thin, the roaſting comes to a poor buſineſs. All the delight ſeemes to be in the paines we take.</hi> Our very <hi>pleaſures,</hi> as well as our <hi>cares,</hi> grow in the <hi>thorny ground,</hi> as it is ſaid in <hi>the parable of the ſeed.</hi> There <hi>is no end in worldy deſires,</hi> but even <hi>when we have what</hi> we would, <hi>we find we have not what</hi> we would! O my Soul, let this very <hi>diſatisfaction</hi> teach thee that there is nothing here worth <hi>the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring.</hi> The game we hunt would not be <hi>in ſo much danger,</hi> but for <hi>the ſent thereof,</hi> which it <hi>carries with it ſelf,</hi> and yet <hi>leaves behind it,</hi> and upon which <hi>it is followed.</hi> As we <hi>hunt other creatures,</hi> ſo we our ſelves are <hi>hunted by that roaring Lion,</hi> the Devil, <hi>that ſeeks to devour us;</hi> and yet we might be ſafe enough from him, if it were not <hi>for the corruption that
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:107494:79"/> is in our own natures;</hi> but <hi>every man</hi> hath an <hi>evil man</hi> within him, and there lyes <hi>the ſent,</hi> upon which we <hi>are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued.</hi> Deliver me, O Lord, <hi>from the evil man; from that evil man, which is my ſelf in my ſelf, and I ſhall not fear what the Devil can do unto me!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have often ſeen <hi>a hunted Hare,</hi> when ſhe is <hi>hard run,</hi> get into <hi>a flock of ſheep,</hi> and put the hounds <hi>to a loſs,</hi> by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among them <hi>in their walk,</hi> O my Soul, as thou deſireſt to ſave they ſelf from the deſtroier, follow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of that poor creature, <hi>go thy way by the foot-ſteps of Chriſts Flock, and keep cloſe to the Shepheards tents,</hi> ſo ſhalt thou put that enemy of thine to <hi>a loſs,</hi> and remaine ſafe under <hi>the protection</hi> of <hi>the great Shepheard of the Sheep,</hi> who will in no wiſe <hi>caſt thee out,</hi> and out of whoſe hand <hi>none can pluck thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is remarkeable that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that hunts ſo like <hi>a Hare,</hi> as <hi>a Lion;</hi> both uſing alike the <hi>ſame arts,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:107494:80"/> and doublings,</hi> when they are chaced. <hi>There is a coincidence in extreames: Fear and courage</hi> may many times <hi>act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,</hi> and are not incompatble in the ſame ſubject. One may generate the other. <hi>Deſperation,</hi> which is <hi>the depth of fear,</hi> doth many times (being <hi>ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by neceſſity) excite courage,</hi> and <hi>beget hope. Temerity,</hi> which is <hi>the hight of courage,</hi> doth often (from <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of danger</hi>) breed <hi>caution,</hi> which is <hi>a diſcreet fear.</hi> Lord grant me ſuch a ſanctified commixture of both theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in the temper of my mind, that in the greateſt trials, and dangers, when I am moſt put to preſerve my ſelf, I may uſe <hi>no other doublings</hi> than ſuch as may conſiſt with the <hi>Hare and the Lion,</hi> with <hi>a fear of thee,</hi> and <hi>a bouldneſs in thee;</hi> that even at what time <hi>I am afraid, I may truſt in thee;</hi> ſo ſhall I whilſt <hi>I fear thee, fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is <hi>a great diſadvantage in hunting, to meet with too much game,</hi> and to have <hi>ſeveral Hares on foot at once;</hi> and it is
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:107494:80"/> no otherwiſe in <hi>the purſuit of worldly affairs;</hi> they that buiſy themſelves <hi>in ſtarting ſeveral deſignes, and projects to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> do nothing but change, and run from one think to another, and ſo <hi>come home with their labour for their paines;</hi> like thoſe <hi>pragmatical Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> they are <hi>buiſy bodies working not at all; all they do comes to nothing.</hi> Lord, whilſt others looſe themſelves in the <hi>vanity of their own imaginations,</hi> and are <hi>incumbred in many things,</hi> and thoſe (for the moſt part) farr from any tendency to the ſervice of Chriſt; let it be the delight of my Soul, and the indevour of my life, to hunt after <hi>the one thing needful,</hi> and to fix <hi>my choice upon that good part, which ſhall not be taken away from me.</hi> O my God, <hi>thou art the only adequate object of my deſires; thou haſt promiſed that thou wilt be found of thoſe that ſeek thee, and that thou wilt not be ſought in vain. My Soul follows</hi> hard after thee <hi>(thee, and none but thee) O let me find thee, and be found in thee; So ſhall I at once,</hi> take
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:107494:81"/> and be taken; apprehend, and be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, <hi>and in both be made everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly happy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. XX.</hi> Of Fiſhing.</head>
               <p>OF all recreations, <hi>Fiſhing</hi> is the <hi>moſt agreeable to contemplative Spirits,</hi> as being <hi>a ſedate quiet ſport;</hi> free from thoſe <hi>clamours,</hi> and <hi>diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances</hi> of the ſenſes, which uſually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company other <hi>pleaſures of the field;</hi> and not <hi>ſo ingroſſing the mind,</hi> but that withal it is at a freedom to <hi>intertain it ſelf with good thoughts,</hi> in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, it is by ſome of the School, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred <hi>before hunting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet how delightful ſo ever it may be as a <hi>recreation,</hi> it is but <hi>a poor bniſineſs to make a trade of;</hi> and if we were <hi>called to it</hi> under that notion, we ſhould quickly be ready <hi>to leave our nets, to follow a more beneficial vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:107494:81"/> Such is the power and oper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of fancy upon the will, that by repreſenting <hi>the pleaſure of freedom</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it (which it naturally affecteth) it can induce it to <hi>like or diſlike</hi> the ſame thing, <hi>more or leſs,</hi> according to the <hi>liberty, or conſtraint,</hi> wherewith it act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it. <hi>There is a pleaſure in willing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But how hath God honored this <hi>deſpicable trade,</hi> and the followers of it, with his <hi>preſence,</hi> and <hi>miracles?</hi> paſſing by <hi>the wiſemen after the fleſh,</hi> the <hi>migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> the <hi>noble;</hi> and chooſing a few <hi>ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, weak, mean Fiſhermen,</hi> with their cloths hardly dry upon their backs, to <hi>promulgate the glad tidings of his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> to every creature; calling them from <hi>mending their nets,</hi> to <hi>mend,</hi> and <hi>reforme</hi> the <hi>world? O the infinite wiſdom of the fooliſhneſs of God! O the unreſiſtable ſtrength of his weakneſs.</hi> Bleſſed be God for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>let no fleſh glory in is preſence!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It hath even been the <hi>ambition of the Devil,</hi> to be like <hi>the moſt High,</hi> in the immitation of his actings. As <hi>Chriſt</hi>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:107494:82"/> hath his <hi>Fiſhers of men,</hi> ſo hath that wicked one <hi>his,</hi> who many times (to conceal themſelves from the eye of the world, and that there may be the leſs perſpective into their methods) do <hi>croude into Chriſt's boat,</hi> and put hard to have <hi>an oare in it,</hi> as if they were of his gang; <hi>transforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into his Miniſters of righteouſneſs.</hi> It is the miſery of the Sons of men, that many times they are not ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as they ſhould be, to <hi>try the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits whether they be of God,</hi> or no; whether it be <hi>a good, or a bad Angel</hi> that is <hi>ſtirring in the waters:</hi> And hence it is that for want of diſtinguiſhing rightly between the <hi>motions of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of Chriſt, and the <hi>ſuggeſtions, and illuſions of the Devil,</hi> it comes to paſs that ſo many fall into the <hi>ſnare of the Devil,</hi> and are caught by him, as the <hi>fiſhes that are taken in an evil net.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that are Maſters at this Sport, do not when <hi>a fiſh bites,</hi> immediatly <hi>twitch him up,</hi> but having <hi>ſtruck him,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:107494:82"/> give him line,</hi> and let him ſeemingly <hi>run away with the baite,</hi> whereby <hi>to booke him</hi> the <hi>more ſurely,</hi> and at laſt, with the more eaſe <hi>to draw him up.</hi> It is no otherwiſe, when a ſinner <hi>bites at a temptation,</hi> and the Devil <hi>ſtrikes him,</hi> he is contented to give him Scope to enjoy <hi>the pleaſure of his ſin for a ſeaſon,</hi> but it is to have the <hi>ſurer hold</hi> of him, and to <hi>make a pray</hi> of him with the <hi>leſs trouble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When fiſh are <hi>inclined</hi> to bite, a ſmall thing, <hi>a flie,</hi> or the very <hi>likneſs of a flie,</hi> an <hi>artificial flie,</hi> will be <hi>a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient bate</hi> for them. We are ready to ſmile at the ſimplicity of thoſe poor Creatures, to ſee them ſo eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; and yet do not conſider with what facility we our ſelves are taken, when we <hi>catch at the worthleſs vanities</hi> of the world; and are <hi>taken with the appearances of</hi> honour, riches, pleaſures, which are deceitful, and have nothing in them. But that is true, which the plain dealing Confeſſor told <hi>Philip</hi> the Second of <hi>Spain</hi> (who <hi>doted upon
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:107494:83"/> a Lady, that was none of the handſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt)</hi> It is all one to the <hi>Devil, how,</hi> or by <hi>what meanes</hi> he <hi>takes</hi> a <hi>man,</hi> (whether with an <hi>ill favoured face,</hi> or with <hi>a Beauty) his pleaſure lyes in the taking;</hi> and <hi>thoſe are welcomeſt to him that will be damned with the moſt eaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ordinary with thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in fiſhing, to <hi>bait certain places</hi> where the fiſh are <hi>apteſt to frequent;</hi> but in this point, the Devil hath the advantage above all others, that he hath <hi>his baits in all places; Count, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Pulpit, Bench;</hi> fitted for <hi>all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, all ages, all complexions;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to <hi>all that is in the world, the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the Pride of life.</hi> Who can eſcape his ſnares? O my God, when I reflect upon mine own condition, how mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable do I find it to be? <hi>which of all his baits</hi> (that have fallen within my reach) <hi>have I not bitten at, and ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? and now how many hooks have I within me?</hi> where is the <hi>ſweetneſs,</hi> where is the <hi>pleaſure,</hi> where is the <hi>profit</hi>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:107494:83"/> of thoſe ſins whereof I am now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed? now by a ſad experience I find, that as I have caught the baits, ſo the hookes have caught me. Who <hi>ſhall</hi> deliver me? Who <hi>can?</hi> None <hi>can,</hi> and <hi>will,</hi> but that graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ever bleſſed Redeemer, who gave himſelf a ranſon for me, and by his own death hath made a way for me to eſcape; who hath not only <hi>freed me,</hi> but <hi>taken him that took me;</hi> and that, by being <hi>taken himſelf by him;</hi> conquering him <hi>by death,</hi> that had <hi>the power of death;</hi> and by the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of that victory, <hi>leading my cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity captive.</hi> What ſhall I render? <hi>To him be all glory, and praiſe and thanks.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="meditation">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:107494:84"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. XXI.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Sun-ſetting.</head>
               <p>BY what inſenſible degrees, and yet how ſpeedily, hath the Sun travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his day's journy? it was but ſome hour's ſince, that he aroſe, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf to our Hemiſphere from the uttermoſt end of Heaven, and he hath allready finiſhed his Circuit to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end thereof. Certainly <hi>day unto day uttereth ſpeech,</hi> and in their ſilent language ſeem to put me in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that I am <hi>going,</hi> or rather (as <hi>Job</hi> phraſeth it) poſting my circuit too from <hi>earth to earth: From the duſt, out of which I was originally taken, to the duſt, into which I muſt finally be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I look back to the morning of <hi>my life,</hi> and conſider my <hi>time paſt,</hi> methinks it is but a very little while, ſince I came out of the Chamber of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:107494:84"/> my <hi>Mothers Womb.</hi> How ſoon is <hi>the tale of threeſcore and ſeven years told?</hi> ſhall I ſay, according to the impropriety of ſome Languages, that <hi>I have</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years? nay rather I may ſay, <hi>I have them not;</hi> according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> (tho ſomething in another ſenſe) ſo much of mine <hi>age is departed from me;</hi> and is as dead, <hi>as nothing</hi> to me. None can ſay <hi>he is the ſame Yeſterday, and to day,</hi> but he that is <hi>for ever.</hi> How is my time ſtolen away, and ſo much of my ſelf gone with it? before I can well take notice, what a clock it is with me, I find my ſelf in the evening, or rather the night of mine age. It is a ſad thing for a man to ſleep out his beſt time (as it was fabled of <hi>Epimenides)</hi> and not to wake till he be old; and then to bid the world good morrow, when the world may <hi>bid him good night.</hi> Lord, ſince the time paſt is ſo fluid, and <hi>tranſitory,</hi> that it is gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I can ſay <hi>what it is;</hi> and <hi>the time to come ſo un certain,</hi> that I know not
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:107494:85"/> 
                  <hi>what may be to morrow;</hi> no not what the <hi>next moment</hi> may bring forth; teach me, I beſeech thee; ſo to husband <hi>my time preſent,</hi> that in this <hi>my day,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this <hi>my Now</hi> (which is all I can call mine) I may ſo live to thy praiſe, and glory, as I would live mine eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hereafter, which (without paſt, or future) is <hi>an everlaſting preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The motion of this glorious Planet is hardly to be diſcerned, but in <hi>riſing</hi> and <hi>ſetting</hi> of it; at noon, when it is at the height, it ſeems to be <hi>at a ſtay,</hi> as if it were there to ſtand ſtill, as it did upon <hi>Gibeon.</hi> The like may be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the courſe, and progreſs of our lives; when we are gotten up to <hi>our middle age,</hi> which is our <hi>Meridian</hi> (when we are in the ſtrength of our years) we appear to be at <hi>a kind of conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> not ſenſible of any motion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our appointed change; but in <hi>the beginning and ending of our dayes,</hi> we may without any great difficulty remark how we <hi>gradually riſe, and ſet.</hi> It is apparent how our infancy grows up from <hi>a ſenſitive, to a rational condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:107494:85"/> and how by little, and little, our <hi>reaſon comes to maturity;</hi> from <hi>ſpeaking as Children, underſtanding as Children,</hi> and <hi>thinking as Children,</hi> we become in time men, <hi>and put away childiſh things.</hi> And ſo likewiſe, when <hi>the evil daies</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertake us, and <hi>the years wherein we have no pleaſure,</hi> it is for the moſt part eaſie to obſerve, by what degrees <hi>our ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow goes down.</hi> Lord I am now <hi>near my Sun ſet,</hi> and cannot but plainly ſee my ſelf <hi>haſtening to the place of my long home;</hi> my Sun, and Light, and Moon, and ſtars grow dark, <hi>the Clouds return after the rain,</hi> and one infirmity follows upon another: O let theſe ſigns of my approaching night, be as ſo many <hi>tolls of my paſſing Bell</hi> to warn me that <hi>my daies are extinct,</hi> and that <hi>my grave is ready for me,</hi> that accordingly I may make my ſelf <hi>ready for my grave,</hi> and not ſuffer my ſelf to <hi>fall aſleep</hi> when I ſhould be <hi>fitting my ſelf to go to bed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With what a full faced, glorious Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, doth the Sun now look upon this inferior world, and in his <hi>loweſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, appear greater,</hi> than at another time?
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:107494:86"/> it is no otherwiſe with a noble hearted Chriſtian, who though he be never ſo <hi>low laid in the opinion of the World,</hi> yet retaineth <hi>an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndejected countenance,</hi> and breaketh thorough all interpoſitions, with ſo much the greater bravery, and luſtre.</p>
               <p>It is a pleaſing ſight to ſee the Sun in his going down, how he doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew forth his own <hi>reſplendency</hi> to the uttermoſt, but many times, out of his abundance, <hi>irradiate the Clouds</hi> about him, and guild, and enamel them with his departing beams. <hi>A dying Saint is a ſetting Sun,</hi> and in his going down to the grave doth not only <hi>ſhew his own brightneſs, and glory,</hi> but often <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates the divine tincture thereof to all about him,</hi> and gives them occaſion by the light thereof, <hi>to glorifie their father, which is in heaven.</hi> Let the fooliſh World <hi>adore the riſing Sun,</hi> God grant I may <hi>ſet clear,</hi> and by my dying exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple illuſtrate others, and thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to praiſe him, <hi>Better is the end of a thing than the beginning, and the day of death, than the day of birth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:107494:86"/>
               <p>But let the Sun ſet <hi>never ſo clear,</hi> we ſee it many times followed by <hi>miſts, and noiſom vapours</hi> (the ancient Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians ſent their imprecations and curſes after it): <hi>there is no perſon</hi> ſo innocent, <hi>but when he is laid in his grave, may have his</hi> memory bemiſted (as it were) <hi>and clouded by the ſtinking vapours of malice, and envy.</hi> Our Saviour himſelf (that <hi>Sun of righteouſneſs</hi>) was <hi>no ſooner ſet</hi> (tho with ſo much glory, that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, even his enemies, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to be <hi>the Son of God</hi>) but the <hi>chief Prieſt and Phariſees</hi> endeavoured to cover his ſacred name with darkneſs, aſperſing him as <hi>a deceiver, and bribing the Guards to belie his Reſurrection: if they have done theſe things in the green tree, what can the drie expect? the diſciple is not above his Maſter; and the charities of the World are ſtill the ſame,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is <hi>a ſad thing to have a guilty ſoul:</hi> this Sunſet, which otherwiſe I might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with comfort, as putting me in mind of the approaching time of my reſt, is to me <hi>an exprobration;</hi> at once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring me of the command, <hi>not to
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:107494:87"/> ſuffer the Sun to go down upon my wrath;</hi> and condemning me for ſuffering <hi>ſo many Suns to go down in my paſſion.</hi> O my God, if thou ſhouldſt deal with me according to my deſerts, <hi>in what a Cloud ſhould I ſet?</hi> But thy goodneſs ſhines in my wickedneſs. O let the brightneſs thereof diſpel, and ſcatter thoſe Clouds that are in my perverſe nature; and then although the days of my life have been frequently <hi>overcaſt by my exorbitant paſſions, I ſhall hope in this evening of it, to go down in the ſerenity of thy mercy, and to ſet in thy love!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what do I ſpeak of <hi>riſing, and going down,</hi> as if the Sun <hi>went higher, or lower,</hi> at one time then another, and were ſubject to <hi>excentrick motions?</hi> that glorious luminary, however it appears unto us, is conſtant to one, and the ſame rode; and is <hi>as high at night, as it is at noon, or morning.</hi> It is ſo with a mind well trained, and exerciſed in vertue, and piety; which although, as to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, it may appear <hi>ſubject to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riations,</hi> (now and then <hi>abuſed,</hi> now and then <hi>abounding</hi>) yet in it ſelf, it is
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:107494:87"/> 
                  <hi>above all ſublunary changes,</hi> neither <hi>ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor dejected,</hi> and keepeth an even courſe, in <hi>a conſtant equi-diſtance</hi> from <hi>earth,</hi> and all <hi>earthly things.</hi> Lord give me <hi>that mind,</hi> that whatever my ſtate and condition be, I may keep ſtill at one, and <hi>the ſame height,</hi> and in <hi>a regular motion;</hi> that <hi>in all mutations,</hi> I may be <hi>one, and the ſame man:</hi> So ſhall I be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in my conformity to thee, <hi>who art ever the ſame, without ſhadow of change.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>the Sun is ſet,</hi> and how ſoon are all things benighted with it? what <hi>are all the comforts of this World, when the light of Gods countenance is withdrawn?</hi> when thou O Lord <hi>hideſt thy face,</hi> it is no marvel <hi>if we be troubled.</hi> As thy light is a rejoycing to us, ſo <hi>the privati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of it, is at once both <hi>uncomfortable, and dangerous:</hi> thou <hi>makeſt darkneſs, and it is night, wherein all the beaſts of the forreſt do creep forth:</hi> in a ſpiritual ſenſe, when it is <hi>night within us,</hi> all our <hi>luſts, and corruptions</hi> are in motion, and that <hi>roaring Lion,</hi> that ſeeks to devour us, is moſt <hi>ſtirring and active: darkneſs, and cruel habitations go together.</hi> O thou
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:107494:88"/> 
                  <hi>who art the true light of the World, and whom no darkneſs can comprehend; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten my darkneſs; be my Sun,</hi> and I ſhall have no need <hi>of this Sun;</hi> be <hi>my ſhield,</hi> and I ſhall <hi>fear no danger:</hi> I ſhall be at once <hi>ſafe, and happy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Sun when it ſets ſhould bid <hi>us goodnight for all,</hi> what a ſad world would there be at his departure? now we are not troubled at it, becauſe we know <hi>it will riſe again:</hi> it ſhould be no otherwiſe with us <hi>upon the departure of godly friends and relations:</hi> why ſhould we grieve ſo immoderately, many times, for them, <hi>as if we had no hope,</hi> when we know that they ſhall as ſurely <hi>riſe again at the laſt day, as the Sun ſhall ariſe the next morning?</hi> we have the aſſurance of Gods own word for it, that <hi>if we believe that</hi> Jeſus <hi>died, and roſe again, even ſo thoſe alſo which ſleep in</hi> Jeſus <hi>he will bring with him;</hi> and that, with this further advantage to them, that they ſhall then appear in glory, and <hi>ſhine like the Sun in the Kingdome of their father, never to ſet more:</hi> what would we have more? Lord teach us to <hi>comfort one another with athewwords.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:107494:88"/>
               <p>It is obſerved that <hi>a clear evening,</hi> is for the moſt part, <hi>a forerunner of a fair morning,</hi> eſpecially if (as our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf hath told us) <hi>the Skie be red.</hi> O my God, grant that at <hi>my laſt end,</hi> I may leave <hi>a clear memory behind me,</hi> and diſcern <hi>a red skie</hi> over me, tinctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his moſt precious blood; and it ſhall be a <hi>prognoſtick</hi> to me of <hi>an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſtingly happy good morrow.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="meditation">
               <head>
                  <hi>MEDITAT. XXII.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my lying down to reſt.</head>
               <p>MEthinks, I have had <hi>a long daies journey in the world, and a wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſome;</hi> accompanied with <hi>bluſtering weather,</hi> and <hi>rugged ill waies;</hi> and now, <hi>a bed would do well:</hi> there is a <hi>time to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very purpoſe under heaven; a time to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and a time to reſt; a time to wake, and a time to ſleep; a time to be born, and a time to die;</hi> the <hi>longeſt day hath a night,</hi> and the <hi>longeſt life, a death;</hi> the one is the emblem of the other: thoſe
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:107494:89"/> fathers before the floud, <hi>Adam, Jared, Methuſalem,</hi> that made nothing of <hi>a journey of nine hundred years,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, had their <hi>bed time,</hi> as well as <hi>their riſing;</hi> and after their reckoning of ſo many Ages, what do we read of them, but that <hi>they died,</hi> and <hi>they died,</hi> and <hi>they died?</hi> this <hi>is the end of all men, and the living will lay it to heart!</hi> It <hi>is late,</hi> and I cannot but confeſs <hi>I am tir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and <hi>my bones would gladly be at reſt;</hi> yet ſuch is my infirmity, that when death is ready to come in, <hi>to help me to bed,</hi> I am ſtartled, and more willing <hi>to ſit up,</hi> and <hi>keep him out of doors,</hi> like <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horams</hi> Meſſenger, then to be troubled with <hi>ſuch an attendance.</hi> O my ſoul, what is the matter? it is for <hi>children</hi> to apprehend <hi>bull-beggers,</hi> and to be afraid to lie <hi>to ſleep in the dark:</hi> be not frighted with <hi>a name:</hi> death is <hi>no more the thing he was;</hi> the <hi>King of fear is departed; death is dead,</hi> as to any hurt it can do thee; and yet I may ſay, <hi>ſo far alive, as to ſerve thee: he is thine,</hi> without any more tergiverſations; therefore, O my Soul, <hi>prepare thy ſelf for thy laſt reſt,</hi> and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:107494:89"/> in order thereunto, acquaint thy ſelf with this <hi>pale complexioned Servant</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, that his face may <hi>not be ſtrange</hi> unto thee: we do not affect to have <hi>ſtrangers</hi> about us, to <hi>help us off with our cloths,</hi> but ſuch as we know well: <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom thy ſelf to entertain communion with him;</hi> go down <hi>to the Potters houſe,</hi> as God commanded <hi>the Prophet;</hi> that is, as ſome Expoſitors ſay, <hi>deſcend to the conſideration of mortality;</hi> and <hi>ſo live to day, as if thou wert to be taken from me to night;</hi> ſo ſhall death never be a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe to thee, but whenſoever he comes, he ſhall find thee ready for him: <hi>That perſon is in a ſad condition, that</hi> looks for death, and cannot find it; <hi>but he is in a ſadder, whom</hi> death finds, <hi>before he looks for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The way to <hi>ſleep well at night,</hi> is <hi>to exerciſe well in the day: the ſleep of a labouring man is ſweet,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Preacher.</hi> Death is but <hi>a long ſleep;</hi> and if we would hereafter <hi>reſt with happineſs from our labours,</hi> we muſt <hi>ſo labour here,</hi> that <hi>our works may follow us hereafter:</hi> if we <hi>ſo ſleep, we ſhall do well!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:107494:90"/>
               <p>We are not troubled when <hi>we lie down</hi> to take our natural reſt, upon the confidence we have in Gods <hi>ordinary providence,</hi> that <hi>he will raiſe us up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain;</hi> why ſhould Chriſtians, that do, or ſhould know the Scriptures, and the power of God, be more anxious, and doubtful of <hi>their eternal,</hi> then of their <hi>natural reſt?</hi> this is nothing but our infidelity, for upon a true account there is more uncertainty of <hi>our waking out of our beds,</hi> then there is of <hi>our riſing out of our graves.</hi> None can tell when he lies down, whether he ſhall ſee any to morrow in this World, or riſe no more till the Heavens be no more, but as to our Reſurrection, we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſo far raiſed, as Chriſt <hi>our head is riſen,</hi> who is <hi>our reſurrection, and our life. Lord increaſe our faith!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what is it troubles us? is it the thought, that we ſhall <hi>live no longer?</hi> We may as well lament that we were <hi>born no ſooner;</hi> it is but <hi>a meaſuring caſt,</hi> between the time <hi>when we were not,</hi> and <hi>the time when we ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot be,</hi> one is <hi>as inconſiderable</hi> as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:107494:90"/> if it be <hi>a matter of ſorrow</hi> to think that we <hi>are mortal,</hi> it may be a juſt <hi>cauſe of rejoycing,</hi> to conſider that we are <hi>ſo near being immortal:</hi> it was (as ſome hold) the mercy of God, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our firſt Parents had eaten of the <hi>forbidden fruit,</hi> and thereby made <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their poſterity miſerable,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them that they ſhould not eat <hi>of the tree of life;</hi> for then both <hi>they, and we,</hi> had been <hi>everlaſtingly miſerable. Mortality is a mercy!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But poſſibly it is <hi>not death,</hi> but <hi>dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (that which the Philoſopher calls, <hi>the pomp of death</hi>) that is <hi>ſo much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended:</hi> the <hi>pangs and convulſions of death</hi> have a horrid Aſpect: certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thoſe things, we do many times but <hi>fright our ſelves with our own fancies;</hi> for when we think <hi>thoſe agonies inſupportable, nature</hi> is <hi>ſpent,</hi> and often <hi>ſenſleſs.</hi> But admitting the worſt; as our <hi>deſire to ſleep</hi> makes us bear with ſome <hi>toſſings, and tumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi> and <hi>diſquietings,</hi> before we can <hi>well ſettle to reſt;</hi> ſo ſhould our <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to depart,</hi> and <hi>to ſleep in Jeſus,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:107494:91"/> with us to endure <hi>thoſe ſufferings,</hi> which are but <hi>for a moment,</hi> but are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with <hi>a quiet happy reſt</hi> in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of our Saviour <hi>to all eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is a diſmal thing to fleſh and bloud, to think that after death, we <hi>muſt lie rotting, and corrupting in a dark ſilent grave;</hi> and that when we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced <hi>to duſt,</hi> as we <hi>were graſs,</hi> when we <hi>lived</hi> (in regard of our frailty) ſo we may come to be <hi>graſs again</hi> after we <hi>are dead</hi> (in a litteral ſenſe) and ſo paſs away into <hi>ſeveral other ſubſtances:</hi> this, I confeſs, might juſtifie ſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy thoughts, <hi>if we had no hope;</hi> But when we are taught of God, that <hi>after this Life ended, our ſpirit ſhall return unto God who gave it:</hi> and that after this <hi>World ended,</hi> our duſt ſhall be <hi>raiſed again,</hi> and <hi>recompacted</hi> into a <hi>glorious body, cloathed with immortality, and honour,</hi> and reunited to our Soul; both, to be for ever with the Lord; we may bid defiance both to death, and the grave. <hi>O death where is thy ſting? O grave where is thy victory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what needs all this perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:107494:91"/> 
                  <hi>is it in our choice, whether to die, or not?</hi> if we <hi>muſt die (as die we muſt)</hi> it is a perfect folly to be <hi>unwilling to do that,</hi> which <hi>of neceſſity we muſt do,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we <hi>will, or not:</hi> take courage then, O my Soul, and <hi>act thy laſt part hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely:</hi> it is <hi>a degree toward dying well, to be willing to die?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>I am dead;</hi> what do I talk of <hi>dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or <hi>the fear of dying?</hi> my whole life, is but <hi>a continued death.</hi> I have more reaſon to be apprehenſive of <hi>my living, then of my dying;</hi> for I can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hope <hi>to live, till I die;</hi> that which we <hi>call death,</hi> being in truth, but <hi>the dying day of our death,</hi> and <hi>the birth day of our everlaſting life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, I am <hi>not only dead,</hi> but in a great part <hi>buried: how much of my ſelf, is already laid in the duſt?</hi> death hath taken <hi>three of my ribs</hi> from me, and ſo many of <hi>my limbs,</hi> as I have loſt <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> by his ſtroke. My deareſt rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are <hi>gon to bed before me;</hi> to what purpoſe ſerves <hi>this fragment, this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder</hi> of me here? Lord, <hi>take all to thee;</hi> let me not lie <hi>half in the bed, and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:107494:92"/> half out:</hi> thy bed is <hi>not too little, nor thy coverlet too narrow, but thou haſt room enough for me:</hi> receive me I humbly beſeech thee, as thine; <hi>I am thine, O ſave me. Lord now letteſt thou thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant depart in peace! In thy name, I lay me down to reſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="169" facs="tcp:107494:92"/>
            <head>A DAILY DIRECTORY.</head>
            <p>EVery day is a life in little; in the account whereof, we may reckon our growth from the womb of the morning; our growth, from thence to noon (when we are as the Sun in his ſtrength) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which (like a ſhaddow that declin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) we haſten, to the evening of our age, and ſo to our Sun ſet, when we come to cloſe our eyes in ſleep, the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and repreſentative of death. Our whole life, is but this tale of a day told over, and over. I would therefore ſo ſpend every day, as if it were all the dayes I had to live; and in purſuance of this reſolution, I would by the aſſiſtance of divine grace, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to obſerve this following dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:107494:93"/>1. I Would awake with God, as early as I could. <hi>David</hi> hath a high expreſſion for this, <hi>In the morning ſhall my Prayer prevent thee;</hi> as if he meant to be up firſt. But to ſpeak in a ſtile, that may be fit ſuch a worme as I am; whenſoever I awake, I would willingly have my mouth prevent mine eyes, and open firſt, to ſhew forth his praiſe; that ſo God may awake for me, and make the habitation of my righteouſneſs proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous. To this end, I would be careful to ly down the night before, in the peace of God, who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that his commandement ſhall keep me when I ſleep, and talk with me when I awake; otherwiſe I may juſtly fear, that thoſe corruptions that bid me laſt good night, may be ready to bid me firſt good morrow.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I would ariſe as early as I could, that courſe being moſt profitable both for Soul, body, and eſtate. In Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, I would be up by five; in <note place="bottom">Pſal. 88. 13.</note>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:107494:93"/> winter, by ſix, or ſoon after, as my health would permit, and if nothing intervene of neceſſity to hinder me. However by Gods grace, it ſhould be mine indevour to preſerve my bed, and heart undeſiled, and to yeild as little as might be to the foulding of the hands.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I would make my ſelf ready as quickly as I could, with a ſpecial care, while I were dreſſing my body, not to neglect the adorning of my Soul, but to be ſure to keep that in a grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful faſhion; in order whereunto I would indeavour (in that time) to call to mind (by ſome ejaculatory Meditations) the benefit of putting on the Lord Jeſus; the advantage of being furniſhed with the Spiritual Panoply; the armour of light, and of righteouſneſs, on the right hand, and on the left; and the bravery of wearing a meek, and quiet Spirit, which in the ſight of God himſelf is of a great price. <note place="bottom">
                  <hi>Rom. 13. 14. Eph. 6. 11. Rom. 13. 12. 2 Cor. 6. 7. 1 Pet.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:107494:94"/>4. I would pray with my Wife (if I omitted to do it before I roſe) and together with the confeſſion of our ſins, acknowledg the mercy of God to us both, in bringing us together, and in conjoyning not only our hands by his ordinance, but our hearts, and affections by the Sacred bond of his love; and implore the Sanctification of our condition, that this happy union might continue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further provocations between us, then to love, and good works; or other contention, then that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Vine, and the Olive, which of us ſhould bring forth the beſt fruit.</p>
            <p n="5">5. So ſoon as I went out of my Chamber, I would retire into my Cloſet, and there lift up my heart with my hands, as an heave-offering to God, in private prayer: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho I would not abſolutly limit my ſelf here in to one place more then to another; yet I would perform that duty there, as conſtantly as I could,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:107494:94"/> becauſe I have found there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the place, that makes impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon the memory; and my thoughts are eaſilier recollected, and come in ſooner, where they have been formerly accuſtomed to a call.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In prayer, whether with my Wife, or alone, I would labour to ſtir up all that is within me; firſt to an awful, reverent apprehenſion of the Majeſty, Power, Wiſdom, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God; and Secondly, to a care, not to utter <note n="1" place="bottom">Eccleſ. 5. 2</note> haſtily any thing before him; not to uſe vain <note n="2" place="bottom">Matth. 6. 7.</note> repetitions; and not to ask <note n="3" place="bottom">Jam. 4. 3.</note> amiſs; but to adopt, and ſute my <note n="4" place="bottom">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> requeſts to his Will; and that in as few words as conveniently might be, <note n="5" place="bottom">Eccleſ. 5. 2.</note> conſidering that he is in heaven, and I upon earth. But yet I would not ſo contract my ſelf, as to make an end before I had done; but ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in prayer, and watch in the ſame, till I found mine affections thoroughly warmed, and quickened. For incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:107494:95"/> to this perſeverance without fainting, I would indeavour to make uſe of theſe, or ſuch like conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; as firſt, that I pray to a God hearing prayer, unto whom all fleſh ſhould come; a God, that heareth, when none elſe can hear; when the children (the departed Saints) are in bed with him, and aſleep, ignorant of our condition; That heareth, when none elſe will hear; at midnight, in the darkeſt time of our condition; and is willing to be importuned, and to have no reſt given him; That hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth while we are yet ſpeaking, and is ready to anſwer before we can call; That is ſo willing to open the door, when we knock, that he hath made himſelf the door to give us admiſſion. Secondly, that I pray unto a God, that commandeth us to pray unto him in time of trouble; and (if I may ſpeak it with humble reverence) prayeth us <note place="bottom">Pſal. 65. 2. Luke 11. 3. Iſaiah 63. 16. Luke 11. 5. Luke 18. 7. Iſaiah 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 7. Iſaiah 65. 24. John 10 9. Pſal. 50. 15.</note>
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:107494:95"/> to pray unto him, and is delighted with our voice. And thirdly, that this God is, 1. The Father, and in Chriſt Jeſus my Father, that knows better then I my ſelf, what I ſtand in need of before I ask him, and is able to do exceeding abundantly, above all that I can either ask, or think. 2. The Son, who is not aſhamed to call me brother; my Mediator, and Advocate, who ever lives to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for me. 3. The Spirit, (and my comforter) who helpeth mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, when <hi>I</hi> know not what I ſhould pray for, as I ought. Laſtly, that I have a promiſe from this good God, to be heard in what I ask accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will, which ſhould ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently imbolden me to come unto the Throne of grace; his hearing being a granting, either of what I pray for; or of what is better, or of what is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for me.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I would make it my firſt ſtudy, <note place="bottom">Cantic. 2. 14. Math. 6. 8. Epheſ. 3. 20. Hebr. 3. 11. Hebr. 7. 25. Rom. 8. 16. 1 John 5. 14</note>
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:107494:96"/> to read ſome portion of the Holy Scripture, both begining and ending it, with ſome ſhort Prayer to God for his bleſſing upon it, that it might be of edification to me: That my reading of it might (according to that advice of <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Iſaith.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, 23.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> for the hearing of it) not only ſerve for the preſent, but be of uſe for the time to come, as a rule, and Canon of righteouſneſs unto me, in the courſe, and practiſe of my life.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I would walk half an hour, and intertaine my ſelf with as good thoughts as I could; that whilſt my body were in exerciſe, my mind might neither be idle, nor miſemploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The time intercurrent between this and noone, I would give either to ſtudy, or to buiſineſs, or to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; but if I could chooſe, the moſt of it to ſtudy; which is the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Becauſe in reading, <note n="‖" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.</note> as in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:107494:96"/> many books, there is no end; and much ſtudy is a wearineſs of the fleſh; I would eſpecially apply my ſelf to the knowledge of divinity, as that which moſt directly tendeth to the cleanſing of the inſide of the Cup; and leadeth me to the obſervation of my Saviours rule, <hi>To ſeek firſt the Kingdome of God, and his Righteouſneſs;</hi> which is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of wiſdome, and the end, and concluſion of the whole matter. But yet, <hi>I</hi> would not altogether lay by the ſtudy of Morality, but labour to make uſe of it in a ſanctified way; and ſo, as that that learning ſhould ſtill be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to the ſtudy, and practice of piety; the eyes of the Maiden ſhould look unto the hand of the Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p n="11">11. After a convenient time ſpent in my Cloſet, I would, if I had a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al calling, apply my ſelf unto that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> termeth, the doing of ones own buſineſs; and I would be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in the purſuance of it: no day (ſo far as I had liberty) ſhould paſs without a line. But however in the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:107494:97"/> want of ſuch a calling, I would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to that general calling which I have taken upon me, and wherein I would be a law unto my ſelf, which is (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s injunction) to do good as I had opportunity, unto all, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially unto thoſe who are of the Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith. This I would have to be the Decretal end, (as <hi>Seneca</hi> phraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it) the bent, and aim of my whole life, whereunto all mine undertakings ſhould collineate: without ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign as this, men live they know not why; they live by fits, and ſnatches, and according to particular accidents, but as to their general, and main courſe, without any certain purpoſe at all; their lives are made up of ſhreds, and fragments, and there can be no conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, nor ſutableneſs in their actions, becauſe they are not of a whole piece, nor all of the ſame ſtuff. <hi>I</hi> would therefore make it my daily buſineſs, in all conditions (whether in my ſpecial, or general calling) to be one, and the ſame man in well doing.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:107494:97"/>12. <hi>I</hi> would conſtantly obſerve to have prayers at noon with my family, and to be preſent my ſelf at the duty; and that, both for mine own comfort, and for example to my Servants; who are then moſt likely to be wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and made ſuch as <hi>I</hi> deſire, when <hi>I</hi> ſhew my ſelf to be ſuch as <hi>I</hi> deſire to make them. <hi>I</hi> look upon the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <note n="1" place="bottom">Gen. 18. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> as in this particular ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to turn all Maſters of Families into examples: what he commanded his houſhold to do in the ſervice of God, that he firſt of all performed <note n="2" place="bottom">Gen. 17. 6. 27.</note> himſelf; and therefore as <hi>I</hi> deſire the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> upon my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and Family, ſo it ſhould be my care, both to order them to keep the way of the Lord, and by mine own example to guide them into that way, which <hi>I</hi> would have them keep.</p>
            <p n="13">13. At Meals, <hi>I</hi> would obſerve a moderation; a mean between eating by the ounce, and by the pound; a ſober competent enough, is the beſt
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:107494:98"/> diet. He that exceeds that, makes his Table a ſnare. In an eſpecial manner, <hi>I</hi> would avoid drinking, further then for the ſatisfaction of nature; for of all ſins, that is the moſt beſtial. Indeed <hi>I</hi> wrong the beaſts when <hi>I</hi> ſay ſo, (for moſt beaſts are ſober); but what a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful creature is a brutiſh man, a man ſunk beneath his Species? It is no Hyperbole to ſay, that drunkenneſs is all ſins, in the complication of it, ſo that it is a difficult matter to be ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply drunk, and no more; to be drunk, and to be guilty of no more then being drunk. Let the jolly good fellowes of the World deride this as a moroſe, and (it may be) a nice preciſe humour, <hi>I</hi> would have them know, that <hi>I</hi> ſcorn to make my ſelf a beaſt in a civility, for any mans pleaſure. That is the worſt good manners in the World.</p>
            <p n="14">14. I would in the choiſe of my Company, wherever I were, aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate (if I could) with thoſe only, that
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:107494:98"/> went mine own way (as I would do, when I went a journy); all my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light ſhould be in the Saints, <note n="1" place="bottom">Pſal. 16. 3</note> who are the only excellent ones. But yet becauſe it is impoſſible, altogether to avoide the meeting with vain, or vicious <note n="2" place="bottom">1 <hi>Cor. 5. 10.</hi>
               </note> perſons (for then I muſt needs go out of the world); I would in mine ordinary converſation, labour to obſerve theſe rules,</p>
            <p n="1">1. According to the direction of the <note n="3" place="bottom">1 Cor. 5. 11.</note> Apoſtle, to keep a reſolved ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led diſtance with thoſe people that are called Brethren, and are but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals; thoſe that look one way in their profeſſion, and row another way in their <note n="4" place="bottom">Jude 12.</note> practiſe; and with ſuch ſpots in feaſts, and meetings, not to commaculate my ſelf, by keeping them company, or by <note n="5" place="bottom">1 Cor. 5. 11.</note> eating with them willingly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To avoid, as much as I could, the ſociety of vain, as well as of ſcandalous company; and if I could
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:107494:99"/> not do that, yet to ſtay as little as might be with them; for that (at the beſt) they do but (in a civil kind of Felony) rob a man of his time.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In caſe I were neceſſitated to be in ill Company, then to obſerve their miſcarriages, but this, not to deride them, and to make a jeaſt of them (for he that, doth that, doth but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Devils victories) but to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void them, and from their evil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to gather good inſtruction, as the <note n="1" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 30. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> wiſe man, when he went by the field of the ſlothful, became the wiſer by remarking his Sloth. It is no paradox to ſay, that wiſe men learn more from fools, than fools learn from wiſemen.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To make profit of the abilities, and parts of thoſe that are perſons of underſtanding, as I ſhould have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity in their Company (if they were ſuch as I might be free with) by leading them on to diſcourſe, and by putting queſtions unto them
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:107494:99"/> whereby to provoke them to ſhew where their ſtrength lay (as we put water into a Pump, to make the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter come) which would be at once a civility to them, in giving them op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to make demonſtration of their worth, and a benefit to my ſelf, whereby I might receive inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="15">15. In reference to the right order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my ſelf in Company, I would ſet as ſtrict a watch, as I could, upon my thoughts, words, and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Upon my Thoughts, that they might be free from Impiety, Pride, Covetouſneſs, Wrath, Impurity, and Vanity. To which end, I would ſtudy to keep my heart with all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible diligence. 1. By poſſeſſing it with a deep, and awful apprehenſion of the Majeſty, Holineſs, Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and Omniſcience of God; the ſenſe whereof was that, <note n="1" place="bottom">Job. 13. 4.</note> which prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally ſecured <hi>Job</hi> from exorbitant
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:107494:100"/> fancies. 2. By directing, and fixing it upon the love of the law of God; <note n="1" place="bottom">Pſal. 119. 37.</note> O how love I thy law, ſaith <hi>David,</hi> it is my Meditation all the day. Where the love is ſettled, there the thoughts will be amuſed, and buſied; as where the carkſe is, there the eagles will be gathered together. 3. By in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uring my ſelf to frequent, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ejaculations unto God, that the Meditations of my heart might be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in his ſight; and this was a peece of <hi>Davids</hi> method too. 4. And laſtly by committing my way to God, according to <hi>Solomons</hi> direction, that my thoughts might be eſtabliſhed: and though I knew I could never keep the door ſo cloſe ſhut, but that ſome wicked, and vain imaginations would be crowding in upon me, yet however by the aſſiſtance of divine grace, I would make it my worke, to uſe them like vagrants, and to whip them out again. Thoſe Sparrows, and Swallows, might keep a fluttering
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:107494:100"/> about me, but they ſhould never be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly admitted by me to houſe, and to neſtle, and to lay near Gods Altar in my heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>I</hi> would ſet a guard upon the door of my lips, that <hi>I</hi> might not ſin in my words; for in the multitude of words, there cannot want ſin. The talking Devil is of more danger, then the dumb Devil, and therefore <hi>I</hi> had rather at any time be put to repent the ſaying too little, then the ſaying too much; for <hi>I</hi> could remedy the one, but not the other; That which is not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken may in good time be uttered, but that which is once uttered, cannot be unſpoken. According to this caution, <hi>I</hi> would be careful not to offend. 1. By Atheiſtical Speeches (words cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with death) as <hi>Syracides</hi> rightly termeth them) tending to the contempt of God, and of Religion, and Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to the profanation of his name; all which kind of expreſſions may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be reckoned among the unfruitful works of darkneſs, as bringing forth
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:107494:101"/> nothing either of profit or pleaſure to thoſe that affect them. 2. By uſing ſlanderous, defamatory words, which commonly are repaid again in the ſame Coin; and therefore he that will take the freedome to talk of others, what he pleaſes, muſt be contented many times to hear that from others which pleaſes him not. This venome may be vented, either a malicious whiſpering way, the which is many times more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrative, than that which is delivered in a publick manner, as a wind at a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow may do one more hurt, than in the air; or in a jeſting way, which is a caſting of firebrands, arrows, and death in ſport, as <hi>Solomon</hi> expreſſeth it; or under a mask of friendſhip com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending a man with a But that ſhall be ſure to ſpoil all the commendation; or with a pretended pity, that ſuch a one ſhould be ſo, and ſo; or as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the report, which we would have believed: ſuch tongues as theſe are worſe than Dog's tongues, for they are healing, theſe wounding. To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:107494:101"/> this baſeneſs, <hi>I</hi> would not onely look to my tongue, but to mine ears; there may be a ſlander in hearing, and liſtening, as well as in ſpeaking. <hi>I</hi> would not make talebearers by liſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to miſreports; the receiver makes the Thief: if the Maſter hearken to lies, all his Servants are wicked, and will take the Wind of him: ſo ſaith <note n="1" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon.</hi> But ſuch Maſters are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome wiſe, and ſuch Servants ſeldome honeſt. <hi>Midas</hi> his ears ſhewed what he was. 3. By taking a liberty to ſpeak obſcenely, which the Apoſtle calleth corrupt communication; this is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then the ſemen of luſt, when it is ſet on boiling by the fire of Hell, and there is a contagion in it, corrupting, or (at the beſt) offending the hearers. 4. By uſing words of heat, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation in argument, or other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with any; for paſſion will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver convert reaſon. In ſuch a caſe, when <hi>I</hi> met with that diſtemper in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or found it in my ſelf, <hi>I</hi> would not heap wood on the fire, by conteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:107494:102"/> but either divert the diſcourſe, or end it in ſilenee. The beſt way to keep the peace, is to hold ones peace. But this will not be ſo handſomly done, if it be not done at firſt, and before the diſcourſe grow too warme; <note n="1" place="bottom">Prove. 17. 14.</note> as the opening of a watercourſe is better ſtopt in the beginning, before it have gained too much paſſage, then when it hath blown up the flood-gates, and overthrown the banks. For pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the worſt, <hi>I</hi> would be wary not to be too poſitive, or peremptory in mine own opinion, but to deliver my ſenſe, with a ſubmiſſion to better reaſon, and with a willingneſs to be better informed; which was noted to have been <hi>Socrates</hi> his way in argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and whereby he gained ſo much upon others and brought them to a concurrence with him; under the notion of one that deſired to find out the truth, and to be ſatisfied in it, but not as impoſing his own opinions upon any in a magiſterial way. 5. By
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:107494:102"/> uttering untruths; by falſe ſpeaking; than which there can be nothing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agined more ſervile and baſe. It is a quality befiiting none, but ſuch as go in fear of a Rod, or a Cudgel; Children, or Cowards; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one cannot be too wary in avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. In order to that end, I would be careful in my diſcourſe, to keep to the plain rode way of truth; and to be clear, and moderate in mine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. I would not affect telling wonders: I would neither tell ſuch truths willingly, as in their incredibil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity might reſemble lies; nor tell ſuch lies, as in their probability might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble truths. Whatever I ſaid, tho poſſibly I might from the report of others, tell that which were a lie; yet I would be ſure not to lie, by tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that for a truth, which I knew to be a lie. I would ſpeak the truth in my heart. <note n="1" place="bottom">Pſal. 15. 2.</note> He that believes himſelf in what he ſayes, never lies. 6. By unadviſed promiſes to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:107494:103"/> much more by any raſh vowes to God, leaſt in keeping them, <hi>I</hi> might inſnare my ſelf; or in violating them injure others, and ſin againſt God. He that promiſes more then he is able to perform, is a vaine weak man; he that promiſes more then he means to performe, is a falſe unworthy man. The word of a perſon of honour ſhould be led by his thought, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by his deed. Above all, there is no dallying with God, in what we have promiſed, or vowed to him. He hath no pleaſure in fools; <note n="1" place="bottom">Eccloſ. 5. 4. 6.</note> ſuch as after vowes make inquiry. <note n="2" place="bottom">Prov. 20. 25.</note> It is not enough for one to ſay, it was an error, and then (as upon better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſement) to vow, not to perform his vow, <note n="3" place="bottom">Plut in Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on.</note> as that Heathen did. God will not be mockt. He expects in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delaid paiment. I would therefore be cautelous before hand how I bound my Soul with any ſuch bond, but having once taken the obligation
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:107494:103"/> upon me, I would by all lawful means, and with as much ſpeed as I could, reſolve, and indeavour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it. 7. By oſtentation, and bragging of any thing done or to be done by me; for this vanity is moſt tedious to the Company, and in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual matters, odious to God. It is offenſive to others, who, for the moſt part, are lovers of themſelves too, and apt to look upon it as a diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their worth, to hear another ſo exalt, and proclaim his own; and it is a ſin againſt God, to rob him of his honour, and glory, by Idol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>izing our ſelves, and Sacrificing to our own parts, and abilities, when we have nothing, but what we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from his Divine beneficence. If therefore thorough the grace of God actuating my weakneſs, I had, or might have done any thing in any meaſure commendable, I would (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Salomons</hi> advice) <note n="1" place="bottom">Prov. 27. 2.</note> let an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other man extoll it, and not mine own
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:107494:104"/> mouth. He is hard put to it, that muſt be fain to be his own trumpeter. There is no greater ſign of emptineſs then for a man to be full of himſelf. 8. By unadviſed diſcloſing of matters of ſecrecy, whether concerning my ſelf, or my friend, or the publick. He that ſuffers for that fatality, can juſtly blame none but himſelf; for why ſhould another man be tied to keep his Counſel, that could not keep his own? 9. By taking a freedome to chide in my family in a violent paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate way, and with unſeemly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. <note n="1" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 13.</note> So did not <hi>Job,</hi> and ſo would not I: for every Maſter, hath a Maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in heaven, <note n="2" place="bottom">Epheſ. 6. 9.</note> with whom there is no reſpect of perſons: from the higheſt to the loweſt, all are in the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, fellow ſervants unto him. He that made me, made them, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his free grace put the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between us; without which, I might have held a Trencher to them, as well as they to me. I would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:107494:104"/> ſo uſe them, as I would be uſed by them, if I were in their quality. My indevour ſhould be to give them that which were juſt, and equal; to take care of them upon all occaſions; to ſhew my ſelf affable to them, <note n="1" place="bottom">Epheſ. 6. 9.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing threatning, and harſhneſs; and by that crriage to oblige them to be, not only faithful Servants to me, but (according to <hi>Seneca</hi>'s phraſe) <note n="2" place="bottom">Sen. Ep. 47.</note> humble friends. But in caſe <hi>I</hi> ſhould find my ſelf neceſſitated to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of faults, and to expreſs a ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon it, as ſometimes, and too often, there might be occaſion for it, (which if I ſhould not be ſenſible of, I might quickly be Servant-ridden, and reduced to that Proverbial condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Major of <hi>Senegalia</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> to command, and do it my ſelf) I would be careful to bridle my paſſion ſo, as that it might not run away with me, but that I might be able to manage it, and to keep it within the ring, and compaſs of theſe conſiderations. 1. I
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:107494:105"/> would ſhew a preſent ſence of any diſhonor offered to God, either by prophane Speeches, or wicked acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with a further allowance to my ſelf to chide in this caſe, then in any elſe, both as the concernment is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and as I might with more ſafety truſt my dull heavy affections for mounting too faſt upward: But then I would intermingle mine anger with greif (as our Saviour did) <note n="1" place="bottom">Mark. 3. 5.</note> for the hardneſs of their hearts that had ſo offended, and indevour to convince them of their ſin, and to reduce them to repentance. 2. I would not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover mine anger too often, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on light occaſions, for that (like the frequent, and ordinary giving of hot water) would abate the operation of it, and at laſt render it ineffectual, and deſpicable. 3. I would not chide the air, when my Servant had miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaned himſelf, but ſix the blame up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the perſon, and that (as <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked <hi>Peter</hi>) to his face: <note n="2" place="bottom">Galat. 2. 11.</note> for to make
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:107494:105"/> a clamour againſt any behind their backs, and to ſay nothing to them when they came in preſence, would be but a diſturbance to my ſelf, a jeaſt to thoſe that ſhould have the reproof, and an emendation to no body. 4. I would be moderate in chiding, when ſoever I were put to it. He that goes beyond that meaſure, deſerves to be chidden himſelf; as <hi>Plutarch</hi> was juſtly told his own, and reproached as a perſon not worthy to be called a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, for that having written ſo much againſt anger, he himſelf gave ſo much way unto it againſt his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. 5. I would be careful not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mine anger too long, leaſt it ſhould grow ſower; there may be a paſſant anger in a wiſe man, <note n="1" place="bottom">Eccleſ. 7. 9.</note> but we know in what boſome it reſteth. 6. I would avoid occaſions of anger, and not be too curious, an dinquiſitive after all words that are ſpoken, leaſt I ſhould hear my Servant curſe me; <note n="2" place="bottom">Eccleſ. 7. 21.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if my Servant would not amend
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:107494:106"/> by fair means, I would reſolve to part with him, rather then to keep him, to the hazard of my making my ſelf the worſe by my paſſion, becauſe he would not be bettered by my reaſon. Laſtly if at any time I ſhould find my ſelf tranſported to ſin in this way, I would labour to be humbled for it, and to be angry with my ſin, which is the right way to be angry without ſin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I would take heed unto mine actions: 1. Not to do any thing that might give occaſion of Scandal, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I ſhould at once diſhonor God, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the mouths of the wicked to blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, greive the Spirits of good people, and wound mine own conſcience. I like not the humour of thoſe that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe a bad fame, for none do that ſo much as thoſe that deſpiſe the vertues that produce a good fame: and this ſhewes worſt in thoſe that are greateſt, as the ſcandals they give are more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary then others; for the faults of great men can never be ſmall. But there is a twofold ſcandal; the one
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:107494:106"/> real, the other imaginary, and in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance only: I would if I could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void both; but it ſhould be with more ſolicitude for the one, than the other. For the firſt, I hope I ſhould as ſoon chooſe to dive into the bottom of the Sea with a Mill-Stone about my neck, as in a real way be guilty of it, as to the ſcandalizing of the leaſt of Chriſts little ones; but for the other (which I reckon an offence taken, and not giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en) ſuch as is grounded upon unſound, and depraved opinions about things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, or impertinent, I would not aſſervile my ſelf to any mens fancies, and Chymera's, and I know not what dominations, and ſpirits of the Air, but either give a rational ſatisfaction for what I did, or (if that would not be taken for good payment) acquieſce in the ſatisfaction of mine own conſcience, and ſtand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt had made me free. I had rather never have been, born than that it ſhould be ſaid of me, that I had committed murder, or adultery, or felony; but if any
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:107494:107"/> ſhould charge me with preciſeneſs, or fanaticiſm, for not going to a Play, or a Tavern, or for not uſing that free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and liberty in my diſcourſe, and converſation, that others did, I ſhould be ſo far from being troubled at it, that it ſhould be a comfort to me to be found guilty of ſuch innocent ſcandals. I would be wary not to give the men of the World advantage to tax me in the courſe of my life with any thing of diſhonor; but if all the occaſion they could find againſt me, were but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the law of my God, and my devotion to his ſervice, I hope I ſhould never ſhut the window for it. I would therefore make it my care, and conſtant indevour to provide that whatſoever I did, might not only be good but of good report, and hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in the ſight of honeſt, and good men, that my good might not be evil ſpoken of by them: But for thoſe that are without; I ſhall ſay no more. 2. I would be careful, as to do good, ſo to do that good in a good manner, which
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:107494:107"/> is to do it well; for a thing done, may be good in the ſubſtance of the work, and yet vitiated in the manner of the doing of it. <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee and the Publican performed both the one, and the other, the ſame du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but with ſo much difference in the manner of their performance that God had reſpect unto the one, and not unto the other; he juſtified the one, and rejected the other. For my better direction herein, I would indevour. 1. To be good; for as things be, ſo they operate; <note n="1" place="bottom">Math. 7. 17</note> every good tree bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth good fruit; and herein I ſhould be conforme to the nature of God himſelf, whoſe character it is, <note n="2" place="bottom">Pſal. 119. 68.</note> to be good, and to do good. 2. Not to reſt upon a moral goodneſs, but upon mine implantation in Jeſus Chriſt, <note n="3" place="bottom">Job. 15. 5.</note> and to bring forth fruit in him. 3. In doing good, to make uſe of none but good meanes; I would not do a wrong to do a right; <note n="4" place="bottom">Iſay. 61. 8</note> God hates robbery for
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:107494:108"/> burnt-offering. 4. To place the good I would do, upon a right object; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that want, and not upon thoſe that have enough. What is pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a full veſſel is ſo much Spilt; <note n="1" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.</note> and therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> putteth that which is given to the rich, into an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual ſcale, with that which is taken from the poor, with a ſevere denuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of poverty againſt thoſe that do it. 5. To do the good I did, for good ends. It is the end, that denominates, and qualifies, and Crowns the action. They that do good for evil ends, and they that do evil that good may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, are both evil whilſt they do good. 3. I would not do that to another, which I would not have done to my ſelf, or mine, but I would admeaſure mine actions by the rule of my bleſſed Saviour in that particular, and make that my ſtandard 4. I Would not be abuiſiy body in affecting multiplicity of ingagements, and the having many Irons in the fire at once, for that kind
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:107494:108"/> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>agmatical undertaking ſeldome effects any thing to the purpoſe, and is no better then a buiſy doing nothing. Neither would I intrude my ſelf into other folkes matters, when I had no call, nor power to do good; yet not forgetting Gods command, <note n="1" place="bottom">Levit. 19. 17.</note> Not to hate my Brother, but in any wiſe to rebuke him, and not to ſuffer ſin upon him; (or as it is in the margent) that thou bear not ſin for him. In Gods account, he is interpreted to hate his Brother, that doth not rebuke him, and his ſuffering his Sin upon him, is reputed a taking of it upon himſelf: but then, this muſt be done with great ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and in the Spirit of meekneſs; in the ſpirit of the Dove, that kiſſes, when it bils, and ſeemes to bite. Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reprehenſions make deepeſt impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; like the Snow, that falls ſoft, and yet ſoaks, and penetrates to the root. 5. I would not intangle my ſelf in too many friendſhips; for there is a kind of incontinency in it, and a man
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:107494:109"/> doth but proſtitute himſelf thereby, and make himſelf common. <note n="1" place="bottom">Prov. 5 17.</note> In this caſe <hi>Solomons</hi> Council is good, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw thy ſelf from thy Neiehbours houſe; or (as ſome read it, out of the Original, inſtead of withdraw) make thy ſelf precious: that is, make thy ſelf valluable, do not wear out every mans threſhold; by obtruding thy ſelf upon them; do not make thy ſelf vulgar, and cheap; for thereby, a man doth but imbaſe himſelf, as a mean commodity, that is every bodies mony. I would hold a fair civility with as many as I could, <note n="2" place="bottom">Eul. 6 6.</note> but (according to the advice of <hi>Syracides</hi>) I would have but one Counſellor of a thouſand. 6. As I would not affect a multitude, <note n="3" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Sen. de benef. 1. 6. c.</hi> 33.</note> or (as <hi>Seneca</hi> calls it) a people of friends, ſo I would be very wary, how I received any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that number, without weighing, and trying them, as I would do gold. I like not thoſe friendſhips that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in the Parlour, and concluded in the Cellar: He that cloſeth overhaſtily
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:107494:109"/> with a friend, before he hath eaten a good deal of ſalt with him, and had ſufficient proof of his piety, fidelity, and ability, may quickly come to take the name of friend in vain. 7. I would not captivate my ſelf to any mans friendſhip, ſo as to render my ſelf obnoxious unto him, whereby it might be in his power to ruine me, if he ſhould prove falſe; but I would ſo govern my carriage (if I could) as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to truſt to far, nor to ſeem to miſtruſt at all. He that ſhews that he doubts his friend, teaches his friend to doubt him. It is a ſafe, and (with the allowance of ſome graines) no ill advice, ſo to look upon a friend, as one that may become an enemy, and ſo to look upon an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, as one that may become a friend. The beſt way in converſation is the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle way, between ungirt, and ſtraight la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; between a confidence, and a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; an open facility, and a cloſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. But in caſe of ſuſpicion, I ſhould think the faireſt way to clear it were the openeſt, that is, to communicate it freely to the party ſuſpected, <note n="1" place="bottom">Bacon Eſſ.</note> whereby
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:107494:110"/> (as it hath been well obſerved) a man ſhall both know more of the truth of the buiſineſs, then he did before; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al make that party (if he have any inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity in him) the more deſirous to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge himſelf of it, and the more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect, not to give further cauſe of jealouſy. 8. I would not affect any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations, or games, but ſuch as were lawful, and innocent; unprejudicial to my ſelf, and Company; either as to health, or eſtate; without ſcandal, or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: and thoſe which I did give my ſelf a liberty to uſe, I would be as moderate, in, as in eating, drinking, and ſleeping, making uſe of them for the refreſhment, and releif ofnature, and no further; ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as little time at them, as <hi>I</hi> could, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe I ſhould think my ſelf a looſer, although I plaied for nothing.</p>
            <p n="16">16. After dinner about an hour, or ſo ſoon as might conſiſt with the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of my health, <hi>I</hi> would retire to prayer, with the ſame cautions above mentioned in reference to that duty.</p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>I</hi> would returne to mine employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either in ſtudy, or buiſineſs, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:107494:110"/> of Company, according to the occaſion offered; and with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer cautions.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Upon all emergencies, I would, as frequently as I could, lift up my heart unto God, either by confeſſion, upon any ſenſible failing (altho but in a ſinful thought); or by thankſgiving upon any accident of wellcome importance, or by requeſt, in caſe of any want wherein I <hi>I</hi> ſhould deſire to be releived.</p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>I</hi> would carefully obſerve to have praiers with my family before ſupper, or in a fit time after, if I ſhould be then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from it, by any avocation, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption. God requires, and expects, an evening, as well as a morning ſacrifice.</p>
            <p n="20">20. At Supper, <hi>I</hi> would indeavour to keep the ſame watch, both upon mine appetite, and converſation, as at dinner.</p>
            <p n="21">21. I would be as careful, as <hi>I</hi> could, with civility, to break up company after ſupper in a good hour, leaſt ſitting up late ſhould make me ſleepy, and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me to the concluding duties of the day, or inforce me to redeem that time, with the expence of ſo much time the next morning.</p>
            <p n="22">
               <pb n="206" facs="tcp:107494:111"/>22. Between ſupper, and going to bed, I would be careful to read again ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the Scripture, after the former preſcript, as near as poſſibly I could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it; and this I would do, to leave my heart with a good relliſh in it.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Before I went to bed, I would conſtantly examine my ſelf, and take a view of what I had done in the ſeveral paſſages of the day paſt, as God did of every thing he had made in the creation, and as far as I were able to recollect my ſelf, I would ſumm up, how often, and wherein I had offended God in thought, word, or deed; in commiſſion, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; thorough ignorance, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; alone, or in company, or both wayes: with an eſpecial eye upon thoſe ſins which were moſt predominant in my corrupt nature. I would obſerve mine improvements, or decayes in grace, what I had gained, or loſt; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſtate of mine account, I would make my application to the throne of grace by Confeſſion, Petition, or Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving. I would with all humbleneſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my ſins unto God, in all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularity
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:107494:111"/> I could, and accknowledg my unworthineſs of the leaſt of all his mercies, imploring his gracious pardon for what is paſt, and his preventing grace for the time to come; beſeeching him to take an intire poſſeſſion of me, as his own (tho moſt unworthy) by purchaſe; and ſo to preſerve me, that there might be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in me, but what were his; that there might be no ſtrong holds of habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſins held out againſt him; nor any preſumptuous imaginations exalted in oppoſition to his ſaving knowledge; but that every thought in me might be led captive unto his obedience; laſtly, I would bleſs and praiſe him with lips un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained, and with all that were within me for all his mercies renewed, and continued to me from day to day; and above all for Chriſt Jeſus the mercy of all mercies; and fountain of all bleſſing, in whom alone I deſired to be found. Thus I would indev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to waſh off the ſoile of the day, and to make all clean at evening, as under the law.</p>
            <p n="24">24. I would reckon that day for loſt, wherein I could not give ſome account
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:107494:112"/> to my ſelf, that I had either done, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſome good.</p>
            <p n="25">25. When I were in bed, I would not ſettle to reſt, untill I had asked my Heavenly father bleſſing and laid my head in the boſome of his Son my graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saviour, with an humble recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of my body, and Soul into his hands, by ſome ſhort ejaculatory praier. Thus ſleeping, and thus awaking, I ſhould hope, that whilſt I ſlept, my heart might be kept awake: and that when I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked, I might be ſtill with him, whom my Soul loveth.</p>
            <p n="26">26. I would have Jeſus Chriſt to be the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the beginning and determination of all my purpoſes, and actions. He alone is my wiſdom, and righteouſneſs, and ſanctification and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; mine only all, and without whom I can do nothing; unto whom, with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, one infinitly glorious God, be all honor, and glory, and praiſe, and adoration for ever and ever,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107494:112"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
